<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<tmx version="1.4">
<header creationtool="Olifant" creationtoolversion="3.0.8.0" datatype="unkown" segtype="paragraph" adminlang="BO" srclang="BO" o-tmf="Olifant" creationdate="20170418T102617Z" creationid="CloudedCat" changedate="20170418T103530Z" changeid="CloudedCat">
</header>
<body>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཕགས་པ་ཀུན་རྫོབ་དང་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་བསྟན་པ</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Teaching the Relative and Ultimate Truths</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སངས་རྒྱས་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་སྐད་བདག་གིས་ཐོས་པ་དུས་གཅིག་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Thus have I heard at one time.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཁབ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One was dwelling in Rājagṛha,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱ་རྒོད་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོའི་རི་ལ་དགེ་སློང་བརྒྱད་སྟོང་གི་དགེ་སློང་གི་དགེ་འདུན་ཆེན་པོ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>on Vulture Peak Mountain, together with a large monastic saṅgha of 8,000 monks</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་བདུན་ཁྲི་ཉིས་སྟོང་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and 72,000 bodhisattvas,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདོད་པ་ན་སྤྱོད་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>as well as gods living in the desire</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གཟུགས་ན་སྤྱོད་པའི་ལྷའི་བུ་རྣམས་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and form realms.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཁོར་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མས་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྐོར་ཅིང་མདུན་གྱིས་བལྟས་ནས་ཆོས་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>There, the Blessed One taught the Dharma, surrounded and honored by a retinue of many hundreds of thousands of beings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་བུ་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བ་རྣམ་པར་དུལ་བའི་དབང་ཕྱུག་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་འཁོར་དེར་འདུས་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ་འདུག་པ་དེས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Present in the assembly was a god, called Lord of Peace and Calm.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཞབས་ལ་སྤྱི་བོས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>He prostrated at the feet of the Blessed One and,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེ་ལོགས་སུ་ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་བ་བཏུད་ནས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>bowing with joined palms in the direction of the Blessed One,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>asked the Blessed One,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ད་ལྟར་གང་ན་མཆིས་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, where is Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta now?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་དང་འཁོར་མང་པོ་འདི་རྣམས་ཀྱང་སྐྱེས་བུ་དམ་པ་དེས་ཆོས་བསྟན་པར་རབ་ཏུ་འཚལ་ལོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Blessed One, I myself and everyone here would like that sublime being to teach the Dharma.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་འདི་ནས་ཤར་ཕྱོགས་སུ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བཅོ་བརྒྱད་འདས་པ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, if one travels east of this buddha realm and passes beyond 18,000 other buddha realms,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཞིག་ཡོད་དེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>there is a buddha realm called Jewel World.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ན་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་ད་ལྟར་བཞུགས་པ་འཚོ་ཞིང་གཞེས་ལ་ཆོས་ཀྱང་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>There, the Thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Ratnaketu at present lives and teaches the Dharma;</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པའང་ད་ལྟར་དེ་ན་འདུག་གོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta is there now.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ལྷའི་བུ་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བ་རྣམ་པར་དུལ་བའི་དབང་ཕྱུག་གིས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god Lord of Peace and Calm said to the Blessed One,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་ཅི་ནས་དེ་མཚན་མ་རིག་པས་འདིར་མཆི་བར་སེམས་པ་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་མཚན་མ་ཞིག་མཛད་ན་ལེགས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, it would be wonderful if a sign were made such that Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta, upon seeing it, would wish to return here.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The reason is,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཇི་ལྟར་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལས་ཐོས་པ་ལྟ་བུར་ཉན་ཐོས་དང་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Blessed One, that Dharma teachings such as those of Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta are not to be heard from any of the hearers,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>solitary buddhas,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་རྣམས་ལས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>or those bodhisattvas who rely on reference points.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་མི་ཐོས་ཏེ། དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་མ་གཏོགས་པར་གཞན་སུ་ཡང་དེ་ལྟ་བུར་ཆོས་སྟོན་མི་ནུས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Except for the Thus-gone One, no one else at all is capable of teaching the Dharma in that manner.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ནམ་འཇམ་དཔལ་ཆོས་སྟོན་པ་དེ་ན་བདུད་ཀྱི་ཁང་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་མོག་མོག་པོར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Blessed One, when Mañjuśrī teaches the Dharma, all the dwellings of the demons lose their luster.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བདུད་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་གླགས་མི་རྙེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Moreover, all demons become unable to inflict any harm.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཕ་རོལ་རྒོལ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་ཤིན་ཏུ་ཚར་ཆོད་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>All opposition is utterly defeated.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དམིགས་པ་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱང་དམིགས་པ་མ་མཆིས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Those with reference points are left without reference.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དམ་པའི་ཆོས་ཀྱང་ཡུན་རིང་དུ་གནས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The sacred Dharma also remains for a long time.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཡང་དེ་ལ་རྗེས་སུ་ཡི་རང་ཞིང་རབ་ཏུ་གཟུང་བ་མཛད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Thus-gone One will also rejoice in this and approve of it.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ལྷའི་བུ་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བ་རྣམ་པར་དུལ་བའི་དབང་ཕྱུག་གསོལ་བ་འདེབས་པར་མཁྱེན་ནས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One knew that the god Lord of Peace and Calm would make this request,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཞལ་གྱི་མཛོད་སྤུ་ནས་འོད་ཟེར་གཅིག་བཏང་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and sent out a beam of light from the ūrṇa hair on his brow.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེས་སྟོང་གསུམ་གྱི་སྟོང་ཆེན་པོའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་འདི་སྣང་བ་ཆེན་པོས་སྣང་བར་བྱས་ནས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>That ray of light illuminated the great trichiliocosm with its intense luminescence and,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བཅོ་བརྒྱད་པོ་དེ་དག་ལས་ཐལ་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>passing through those 18,000 other buddha realms,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག་དེའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་། འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དེ་སྣང་བ་ཆེན་པོས་ཁྱབ་པར་བྱས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>its intense radiance spread throughout the Jewel World, the buddha realm of the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Ratnaketu.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག་བཞུགས་པ་ལ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Ratnaketu who resided there,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ཁ་ཅིག་གིས་གསོལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Witnessing this radiance, some bodhisattva great beings asked the Blessed,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འདི་ལྟར་འོད་ཆེན་པོ་རབ་ཏུ་གདའ་བ་འདི་སུའི་ལྟས་སྔོན་དུ་བྱུང་བ་ལགས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, there was such a bright light just now; who caused that sign?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག་གིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Son of noble family,” replied the Blessed Ratnaketu,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་འདི་ནས་ནུབ་ཕྱོགས་སུ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བཅོ་བརྒྱད་འདས་པ་ན་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་མི་མཇེད་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་ཡོད་དེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“to the west of this buddha realm, past 18,000 buddha realms, is the Sahā world.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ན་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ་ད་ལྟ་ན་བཞུགས་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>There, the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Śākyamuni currently</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཚོ་ཞིང་གཞེས་ལ་ཆོས་ཀྱང་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>lives and teaches the Dharma.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ་དེས་ཞལ་གྱི་མཛོད་སྤུ་ནས་འོད་ཟེར་གཅིག་བཏང་བས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Śākyamuni sent out a beam of light from the ūrṇa hair on his brow,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོད་ཟེར་གྱི་སྣང་བ་དེས་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བཅོ་བརྒྱད་ལས་ཐལ་ནས་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་འདི་སྣང་བ་ཆེན་པོས་སྣང་བར་བྱས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and the luminescence of that beam of light passed through 18,000 buddha realms and illuminated this world with its intense radiance.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དག་གིས་གསོལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One,” asked those bodhisattva great beings,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་དེས་འོད་ཟེར་འདི་བཏང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“why did that blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha emit this beam of light?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག་གིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed Ratnaketu replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་སྦྲན་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“He did so in order to summon Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་དེར་འོང་བར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>To make him return there.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་བགྲང་བ་ལས་འདས་པ་རྣམས་དང་། ལྷ་དང་། ཀླུ་དང་། གནོད་སྦྱིན་དང་། དྲི་ཟ་མང་པོ་ལ་སོགས་པ་འཁོར་དེར་ཚོགས་པ་དེ་དག་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>In that buddha’s retinue there are numerous bodhisattva great beings as well as many gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, and so forth.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་བལྟ་བ་དང་། ཆོས་ཉན་པར་འདོད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They all want to behold Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta and hear him teach the Dharma.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག་གིས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Thus-gone Ratnaketu then said to Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ་དང་། འཁོར་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཁྱོད་ལ་ལྟ་འདོད་ཀྱིས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, since the Blessed, Thus-gone Śākyamuni and all those in his retinue would like to see you,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་མི་མཇེད་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་དེར་སོང་ཤིག །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>you should go to that Sahā world.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་གསོལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Yes, Blessed One,” replied Mañjuśrī.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་གིས་ཀྱང་ལྟས་སྔོན་དུ་བྱུང་བ་འདི་འཚལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“I had also noticed that sign.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བཅུ་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག་གི་ཞབས་ལ་མགོ་བོས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>So Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta, along with ten thousand bodhisattvas, bowed at the feet of the Thus-gone Ratnaketu.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག་ལ་ལན་གསུམ་དུ་བསྐོར་བ་བྱས་ནས་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They circumambulated the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Ratnaketu three times,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྐྱེས་བུ་སྟོབས་པོ་ཆེས་ལག་པ་བསྐུམ་པ་ལས་རྐྱོང་བའམ། ལག་པ་བརྐྱང་བ་ལས་སྐུམ་པ་བཞིན་དུ་སྐད་ཅིག་ཡུད་ཙམ་ཐང་ཅིག་དེ་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་མི་མཇེད་འདིར་ཕྱིན་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and then instantaneously traveled to this Sahā world, arriving as quickly as it takes a strong person to extend and retract his arm.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་བར་སྣང་ལ་ལུས་མི་སྣང་བར་འདུག་ནས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Remaining in midair with their bodies invisible,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ་ལ་མཆོད་པ་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>they sent down a great shower of fragrant, colorful, and delightful flowers,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མེ་ཏོག་སྔོན་མ་མཐོང་མ་ཐོས་པ། དྲི་ཞིམ་པ་ཁ་དོག་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཡིད་དུ་འོང་བའི་ཆར་ཆེན་པོ་མངོན་པར་ཕབ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>such as had never been seen or heard of before, in order to honor the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Śākyamuni.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མེ་ཏོག་གི་ཆར་ཆེན་པོ་ཕབ་པ་དེས་སྟོང་གསུམ་གྱི་སྟོང་ཆེན་པོའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་འདི་པུས་མོ་ནུབ་ཙམ་དུ་གང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This great shower of flowers filled the whole great trichiliocosm to knee height.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་འཁོར་དེ་ཐམས་ཅད་མེ་ཏོག་གི་ཆར་ཆེན་པོ་མཐོང་ནས་ངོ་མཚར་དུ་གྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Seeing these flowers, everyone assembled there was amazed</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་གསོལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and asked,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སུའི་མཐུས་འདི་ལྟ་བུར་བལྟ་ན་སྡུག་པའི་མེ་ཏོག་གི་ཆར་ཆེན་པོ་མངོན་པར་ཕབ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, who caused this great shower of blossoms, so pleasant to behold, to fall?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བཅུ་དང་འགྲོགས་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta, accompanied by ten thousand bodhisattvas,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་མི་མཇེད་འདིར་ཕྱིན་ནས་དེ་དག་གི་ལུས་མི་སྣང་བར་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ལ་མཆོད་པའི་ཕྱིར་འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་མེ་ཏོག་གི་ཆར་ཆེན་པོ་མངོན་པར་ཕབ་པོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>has come from the Jewel World to this Sahā world. With their bodies invisible, they all sent down this great shower of flowers to honor the Thus-gone One.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཁོར་དེ་དག་གིས་གསོལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Those in the retinue said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་དེ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དག་བདག་ཅག་གིས་བལྟའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, we would like to see Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta and those bodhisattva great beings.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སྟོང་ཕྲག་བཅུ་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ་བར་སྣང་ལས་བབས་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>At that point, Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta and the ten thousand bodhisattvas descended from the sky.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཞབས་ལ་མགོ་བོས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ནས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Having prostrated at the Blessed One’s feet,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དག་དང་། འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་རང་རང་གི་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱིས་སྤྲུལ་པའི་སྟན་ལ་འཁོད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta and the bodhisattva great beings each sat down on their own miraculously emanated seat.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་བུ་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བ་རྣམ་པར་དུལ་བའི་དབང་ཕྱུག་གིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ག་ལ་བ་དེ་ལོགས་སུ་ཐལ་མོ་སྦྱར་བ་བཏུད་ནས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Then the god Lord of Peace and Calm bowed to the Blessed One</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and said, with joined palms,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཁོར་འདི་དག་ཉན་འཚལ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, all of us would like to listen,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་མཆིད་ཀྱི་རྒྱུད་འགའ་ཞིག་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་སྨྲར་གསོལ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>so please ask Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta to teach.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཁྱོད་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་གང་འདོད་པ་དྲིས་ཤིག །ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, you yourself should make that request.” So the god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག་དེའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ན་ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་དག་འབྱུང་ན་དེར་མངོན་པར་དགའ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, it would be wonderful if you could give us a Dharma teaching similar to what is taught in the buddha realm of the Blessed, Thus-gone Ratnaketu.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་འདོད་ཆགས་བསྐྱེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་མ་ཡིན། འདོད་ཆགས་ཟད་པར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Ultimately, the Dharma is not about generating attachment; nor is it about bringing attachment to an end.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཞེ་སྡང་བསྐྱེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་མ་ཡིན། ཞེ་སྡང་ཟད་པར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, it is not about generating anger; nor is it about bringing anger to an end.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་གཏི་མུག་བསྐྱེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་མ་ཡིན། གཏི་མུག་ཟད་པར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, it is not about generating delusion; nor is it about bringing delusion to an end.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཡེ་ཤེས་བསྐྱེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་མ་ཡིན། ཡེ་ཤེས་ཟད་པར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, it is not about generating wisdom; nor is it about bringing wisdom to an end.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, how is that?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་མི་སྐྱེ་བ་ལ་སྐྱེ་བའམ། ཟད་པ་གང་ཡང་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, in the unborn, there is no birth or ending whatsoever.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ལ་རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་པ་སྐྱེས་པའམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, divine son, the bodhisattva great beings have no thoughts at all, none that have arisen,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྐྱེ་བའམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>none that are arising,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྐྱེ་བར་འགྱུར་བ་གང་ཡང་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and none that will arise.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And why is that?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་རང་བཞིན་གྱིས་མ་སྐྱེས་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Because ultimately all phenomena are inherently unborn.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god asked,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དེ་ཅི་ཞིག་སྤང་བའི་ཕྱིར་ཆོས་སྟོན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, so what does that Thus-gone One wish to see abandoned through his teaching the Dharma?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་རང་བཞིན་གྱིས་མི་སྐྱེ་མི་ཟད་པའི་ཕྱིར་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དེ་ཆོས་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“That Thus-gone One teaches the Dharma because ultimately things are neither inherently born, nor do they inherently end.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དག་ནི་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་ལ་ལྷུར་བྱེད་པ་ཡིན་གྱི་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Because bodhisattva great beings apply themselves assiduously to the ultimate truth.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཀྱི་བདེན་པ་ལ་ཡང་ལྷུར་བྱེད་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>However, they do not apply themselves diligently to the relative truth.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་གང་ཡིན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, what is the ultimate truth?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་གལ་ཏེ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་ལུས་དང་། ངག་དང་། ཡིད་ཀྱི་ཡུལ་གྱི་རང་བཞིན་དུ་འགྱུར་ན་ནི་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་གྲངས་སུ་མི་འགྲོ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, if, on the ultimate level, ultimate truth becomes an object of body, speech, or mind, that is not ‘ultimate truth’</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཀྱི་བདེན་པ་ཉིད་དུ་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>but relative truth itself.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོན་ཀྱང་ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་ནི།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Rather, divine son, on the ultimate level, ultimate truth transcends all conventions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཐ་སྙད་ཐམས་ཅད་ལས་ཡང་དག་པར་འདས་པ། བྱེ་བྲག་མེད་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>It is without specific instances;</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མ་སྐྱེས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>it does not arise,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མ་འགགས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>does not cease,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྨྲ་བར་བྱ་བ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and is free from something to be expressed,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྨྲ་བ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>an expression,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤེས་པར་བྱ་བ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>something to be known,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤེས་པ་དང་བྲལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and knowledge.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་ནི་རྣམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་མཆོག་དང་ལྡན་པ་དང་། ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཀྱི་ཡུལ་གྱི་བར་ལས་ཡང་དག་པར་འདས་པ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, the ultimate truth transcends everything up through the domain of omniscient wisdom that is endowed with the supreme of all aspects.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་ལ་རྟོག་པ་དང་རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་འཇུག་པའང་མེད།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, it has no engagement with,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྡོག་པའང་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>nor any turning back of, concepts and thoughts.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་དེ་ལ་ཕ་རོལ་ཡང་མེད། ཚུ་རོལ་ཡང་མེད།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, there is no ‘far shore,’ there is no ‘this shore,’</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དབུས་ཀྱང་མེད་དེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>nor is there a middle.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་འདི་ནི་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་ཞེས་སྒྲོ་བཏགས་ཏེ་བརྗོད་མོད་ཀྱི།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, although one indeed makes the exaggerated claim,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཇི་ལྟར་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པའོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ལྟར་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>‘This is ultimate truth,’ that is not the same as saying, ‘Ultimate truth is like this.’</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་ནི་དོན་དམ་པར་མི་སྐྱེ་བ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, ultimately, reality is unborn;</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ལ་ཐ་སྙད་ཐམས་ཅད་མི་འཇུག་གོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>thus, no conventions apply to it.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་གང་ལ་ཐ་སྙད་ཐམས་ཅད་མི་འཇུག་པ་དེ་ནི་ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་སྟེ། ཇི་ལྟར་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>That to which, on the ultimate level, no conventions apply, divine son, is ultimate truth.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཞེས་བརྗོད་པ་ལྟར་ན་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Thus, that is not like saying,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>‘Ultimate truth is like this.’ Divine son, the Thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha also says that ultimately all phenomena</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྒྲ་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་བརྫུན་ཏེ་སླུ་བའི་ཆོས་སོ་ཞེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and all terms are false and deceptive phenomena.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཇི་ལྟར་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་ཆོས་བཤད་པ་དེ་བརྫུན་དུ་མི་འགྱུར་རམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“How is it then, Mañjuśrī, that the Dharma taught by the Thus-gone One is not false?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ནི་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བརྫུན་དུའང་མི་འཆད།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, on the ultimate level, the Thus-gone One does not speak falsely.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བདེན་པར་ཡང་མི་འཆད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Nor does he speak truly.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And why is that?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ནི་མ་སྐྱེས་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, divine son, the Thus-gone One has not arisen.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བདེན་པ་དང་བརྫུན་པར་མི་འཆད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And so, ultimately he speaks neither falsely nor truly.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་ཇི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, what do you think?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་སྤྲུལ་པས་བཤད་པ་དེ་བདེན་ནམ་འོན་ཏེ་བརྫུན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Are explanations given by magical creations of the Thus-gone One true or false?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་སྤྲུལ་པས་བཤད་པ་ནི་བདེན་པའང་མ་ཡིན་བརྫུན་པའང་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, explanations given by magical creations of the Thus-gone One are not true, nor are they false.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Why is that?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་སྤྲུལ་པ་ལ་ཡང་དག་པར་ཡོངས་སུ་གྲུབ་པ་གང་ཡང་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī, ultimately there is nothing truly established in that which is emanated by the Thus-gone One.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་དེ་བཞིན་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, so it is.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་དོན་དམ་པར་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོངས་སུ་མ་གྲུབ་པར་མཁྱེན་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Thus-gone One knows that all phenomena are unestablished in the ultimate sense.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གང་དོན་དམ་པར་ཡོངས་སུ་མ་གྲུབ་པ་དེ་ནི་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བདེན་པ་ཞེས་ཀྱང་མི་བྱ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Whatever is unestablished in the ultimate sense should not be called true</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བརྫུན་པ་ཞེས་ཀྱང་མི་བྱའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>nor should it be called false in the context of the ultimate.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Why is that?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་མ་སྐྱེས་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Because ultimately all phenomena are unborn.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཅི་འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་སྟོན་ཏམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, how does the Thus-gone One teach the ultimate truth?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་ནི་བསྟན་པར་མི་ནུས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“The ultimate truth, divine son, cannot be taught.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གང་སྟོན་པ་དང་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Because the topic,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གང་གིས་སྟོན་པ་དང་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the teacher,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཅི་སྟོན་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the method of teaching,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གང་ལ་སྟོན་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the student,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་སྟོན་པའི་ཆོས་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་རབ་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and the reason for teaching are all ultimately utterly unborn.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རབ་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་པའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་པའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་བཤད་མི་ནུས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Phenomena that are utterly unborn cannot themselves express utterly unborn phenomena.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་བསྟན་པ་འདི་མི་སྟོན་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བསྟན་པ་ན་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>When Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta had given this teaching on the ultimate truth without teaching,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དགེ་སློང་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་ལེན་པ་མེད་པར་ཟག་པ་རྣམས་ལས་སེམས་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་ལོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the minds of five hundred monks were freed from defilements without further clinging.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་བགྲང་བ་ལས་འདས་པ་རྣམས་ནི་མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ་མ་སྐྱེས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བཟོད་པ་སྐྱེས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Countless bodhisattva great beings developed, without developing it, the acceptance that phenomena are unborn.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་ལ་མོས་པར་དཀའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, it is difficult to feel conviction in the ultimate truth.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་ལ་ནི་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་མོས་པར་དཀའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, it is difficult for anyone who relies on reference points to feel conviction in the ultimate truth.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པར་དཀའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, it is difficult to understand the ultimate truth.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་མི་བརྩོན་པས་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པར་དཀའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, it is difficult for those who do not exert themselves to understand the ultimate truth.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་དགེ་སློང་མངོན་པར་བརྩོན་པ་ཡིན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, how do monks exert themselves?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ནམ་ཡོངས་སུ་ཤེས་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, ultimately, when they are without exertion that aims to understand,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྤང་བ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>relinquish,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བསྒོམ་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>cultivate,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མངོན་དུ་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>or actualize,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བརྩོན་པར་མ་གྱུར་ན་ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་ལྟར་དགེ་སློང་མི་བརྩོན་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་མངོན་པར་བརྩོན་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>that is how monks exert themselves without exerting themselves.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གང་འདི་སྙམ་དུ་དོན་དམ་པར་འདི་ཡོངས་སུ་ཤེས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Because one might think, ‘Ultimately, this is to be understood,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་སྤང་བར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>this is to be relinquished,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་བསྒོམ་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>this is to be cultivated,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་མངོན་དུ་བྱའོ་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and this is to be actualized.’</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྙམ་དུ་སེམས་པའི་སྦྱོར་བ་དེ་ནི་མཚན་མ་དང་བཅས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>However, such thinking involves conceptual marks</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྤྲོས་པ་དང་བཅས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and elaborations.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དམིགས་པ་དང་བཅས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>It involves reference points</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཉོན་མོངས་པ་དང་བཅས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and disturbing emotions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཁྲུག་པ་དང་བཅས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>It involves tumult</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇིགས་པ་དང་བཅས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and fear.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ནད་དང་བཅས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>It involves illness</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྡུག་བསྔལ་དང་བཅས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and suffering.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཟུག་རྔུ་དང་བཅས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>It involves pain</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དུག་དང་བཅས་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and poison.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེའི་སྦྱོར་བ་དེ་ནི་ཡང་དག་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Thus, engagement of that type is not authentic.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཡང་དག་པར་སྦྱོར་བ་ནི་གང་ཡིན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, what is authentic engagement?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, whatever is the same as suchness,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the sphere of reality,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་སྐྱེ་བ་གང་དང་མཉམ་པ། དོན་དམ་པར་ན་མཚམས་མེད་པ་ལྔ་པོ་དག་ཀྱང་དེ་དང་མཉམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and the utterly unborn on the ultimate level is also the same as the five acts with immediate consequence on the ultimate level.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Whatever is the same as suchness,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the sphere of reality,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་སྐྱེ་བ་གང་དང་མཉམ་པ། དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ལྟ་བར་གྱུར་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་དེ་དང་མཉམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and the utterly unborn on the ultimate level is also ultimately the same as views.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Whatever is the same as suchness,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the sphere of reality,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་སྐྱེ་བ་གང་དང་མཉམ་པ། དོན་དམ་པར་ན་སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ཀྱང་དེ་དང་མཉམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and the utterly unborn on the ultimate level is also ultimately the same as the dharmas of ordinary beings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Whatever is the same as suchness,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the sphere of reality,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་སྐྱེ་བ་གང་དང་མཉམ་པ། དོན་དམ་པར་ན་སློབ་པའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ཀྱང་དེ་དང་མཉམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and the utterly unborn on the ultimate level is also ultimately the same as the dharmas of those who are training.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Whatever is the same as suchness,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the sphere of reality,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་སྐྱེ་བ་གང་དང་མཉམ་པ། དོན་དམ་པར་ན་མི་སློབ་པའི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ཀྱང་དེ་དང་མཉམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and the utterly unborn on the ultimate level is also ultimately the same as the dharmas of those who are no longer training.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Whatever is the same as suchness,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the sphere of reality,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་སྐྱེ་བ་གང་དང་མཉམ་པ། དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་རྣམས་ཀྱང་དེ་དང་མཉམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and the utterly unborn on the ultimate level is also ultimately the same as the dharmas of the completely perfect Buddha.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་རྣམས་གང་དང་མཉམ་པ། དོན་དམ་པར་ན་དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Whatever is the same as the dharmas of the completely perfect Buddha on the ultimate level is also ultimately the same as suchness,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the sphere of reality,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་སྐྱེ་བའང་དེ་དང་མཉམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and the utterly unborn.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་རྣམས་གང་དང་མཉམ་པ། དོན་དམ་པར་ན་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པ་ཡང་དེ་དང་མཉམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Whatever is the same as the dharmas of the completely perfect Buddha on the ultimate level is also ultimately the same as nirvāṇa.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པ་གང་དང་མཉམ་པ། དོན་དམ་པར་ན་འཁོར་བ་ཡང་དེ་དང་མཉམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Whatever is the same as nirvāṇa on the ultimate level is also ultimately the same as saṃsāra.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་འཁོར་བ་གང་དང་མཉམ་པ། དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ཡང་དེ་དང་མཉམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Whatever is the same as saṃsāra on the ultimate level is also ultimately the same as affliction.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་གང་དང་མཉམ་པ། དོན་དམ་པར་ན་རྣམ་པར་བྱང་བ་ཡང་དེ་དང་མཉམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Whatever is the same as affliction on the ultimate level is also ultimately the same as purification.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་རྣམ་པར་བྱང་བ་གང་དང་མཉམ་པ། དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་དེ་དང་མཉམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Whatever is the same as purification on the ultimate level is also ultimately the same as all phenomena.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ལྟར་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་མཉམ་པ་ཉིད་ལ་ཡང་དག་པར་སྦྱོར་བའི་དགེ་སློང་ནི་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“A monk who genuinely engages in the equality of all phenomena on the ultimate level in this way,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཡང་དག་པར་སྦྱོར་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་སྟེ་ཇི་སྐད་བརྗོད་པ་བཞིན་དུ་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>divine son, is called one with authentic engagement on the ultimate level. However, it is not like the way it is expressed.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་མཉམ་པ་ཉིད་གང་གིས་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་རྣམ་པར་བྱང་བའི་བར་དུ་གང་དང་མཉམ་པ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་དེ་དང་མཉམ་ཞེས་བྱ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, what is the sameness by which everything up to purification is said to be ultimately the same, and also to be ultimately the same as all phenomena?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བར་མཉམ་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Ultimately, all phenomena are the same in that they are unarisen.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་སྐྱེ་བར་མཉམ་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, all phenomena are the same in that they are unborn.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་དངོས་པོ་མེད་པར་མཉམ་པས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, all phenomena are the same in that they are unreal.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་མཉམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Therefore, divine son, ultimately all phenomena are the same.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And why is that?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་ཕྱིར་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཐ་དད་དུ་བྱ་བ་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Since ultimately, divine son, all phenomena are unarisen, they cannot be distinguished.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ་དཔེར་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, it is like this analogy.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཁམ་པའི་སྣོད་ཀྱི་ནང་གི་ནམ་མཁའ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The space within a clay vessel</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་སྣོད་ཀྱི་ནང་གི་ནམ་མཁའ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་ནམ་མཁའི་ཁམས་ཉིད་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and the space within a precious vessel are both the element of space;</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ལ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆུང་ཟད་ཀྱང་ཐ་དད་དུ་བྱ་བ་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>ultimately, not the slightest distinction can be made between them.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་དུ་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, in the very same way,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཉོན་མོངས་པ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བ་ཉིད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>disturbing emotions are themselves unarisen on the ultimate level.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རྣམ་པར་བྱང་བ་གང་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ཡང་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བ་ཉིད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Purification itself is also unarisen on the ultimate level.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་འཁོར་བ་ཡང་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བ་ཉིད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, saṃsāra itself is also unarisen.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པའི་བར་དུ་ཡང་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བ་ཉིད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, all phenomena up through nirvāṇa itself are unarisen.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ལ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཐ་དད་དུ་བྱ་བ་ཆུང་ཟད་ཀྱང་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, not even a slight distinction can be made with respect to these.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Because ultimately all phenomena are unarisen.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོས་འཕགས་པའི་བདེན་པ་དག་ལ་ཇི་ལྟར་བརྩོན་པར་བྱ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattva great beings exert themselves with respect to the truths of the noble ones?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་གལ་ཏེ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་འཕགས་པའི་བདེན་པ་དག་ལ་བརྩོན་པར་མི་བྱེད་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, if bodhisattva great beings did not apply themselves to the truths of the noble ones,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ཉན་ཐོས་རྣམས་ལ་མི་སྟོན་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་ཆོས་སྟོན། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>how could they teach, without teaching, the Dharma to the hearers?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་ལྟ་མོད་ཀྱི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་བདེན་པ་སྒོམ་པ་ནི་ལྟ་བ་དང་བཅས་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Yet, divine son, although indeed that is the case, the bodhisattva great beings’ meditation on the truths involves consideration,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བདེན་པ་སྒོམ་པ་ནི་མི་ལྟ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>while the hearers’ meditation on the truths does not involve consideration.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Why is that?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ནི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ལྟ་བ་སྟེ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, on the relative level the bodhisattva great beings consider all sentient beings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བདེན་པ་རྣམས་མི་སྒོམ་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་ཀྱང་སྒོམ་མོད་ཀྱི།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Although they do meditate on the truths without meditating,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དངོས་པོ་མེད་པར་དམིགས་པའི་རྣམ་པས་ཡང་དག་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་མཐའ་དེ་ཡང་མངོན་དུ་མི་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>they do not actualize the limit of reality by focusing on lack of substance.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ཐབས་མཁས་པ་བསྒྲུབ་པའི་ཕྱིར་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དག་བདེན་པ་རྣམས་ལ་མི་སྒོམ་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་སྒོམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, in order to acquire skill in means, the bodhisattva great beings meditate on the truths without meditating.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་འཁོར་བ་དང་། མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པའི་བདེན་པ་ཡང་མི་འདོར་ལ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level they do not discard the truths of saṃsāra, nor of nirvāṇa.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཡེ་ཤེས་ལ་སོ་སོར་བརྟག་པའི་ཕྱིར་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དག་བདེན་པ་རྣམས་ལ་མི་སྒོམ་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་ཀྱང་སྒོམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, in order to individually discriminate the wisdoms of the buddhas, the bodhisattva great beings meditate on the truths without meditating.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, it is as in the following analogy.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དཔེར་ན་འདྲོན་པ་མང་པོ་བཅིངས་ནས་སྐྱེས་བུ་གཅིག་བྲོས་ཏེ། འདྲོན་པ་མང་པོའི་ནང་ནས་བྱུང་ནས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>A person who had been caught by many strangers</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འབྲོག་དགོན་པར་ཞུགས་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>He escapes from among those many strangers and enters a jungle.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཡིད་འཇིགས་ཤིང་སྐྲག་ནས་ཕྱིར་མི་ལྡོག་པར་འབྲོག་དགོན་པ་ལས་འདས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>But he becomes frightened, panics, and leaves the jungle, never to return.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཉན་ཐོས་རྣམས་འཁོར་བས་འཇིགས་ཤིང་སྐྲག་ནས་འཁོར་བ་ལས་བྲོས་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, in the same way the hearers are frightened of saṃsāra and flee in panic.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་འདིར་ཕྱིར་མི་འོང་ཞིང་གཅིག་པུ་གཉིས་སུ་མེད་པར་བདེན་པ་སྒོམ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They do not return to this world but meditate one-pointedly on the truths in solitude.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཐབས་ཀྱི་རིགས་པ་དང་བྲལ་བས་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་མི་ལྟ་བ་ནས་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Thus, since they lack the intelligence of various methods, they do not consider all sentient beings,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཀྱི་བར་ལ་མི་ལྟ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and so forth up to not considering the wisdom of omniscience.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, it is like the following analogy.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དཔེར་ན་དེད་དཔོན་གཡོག་མང་པོ་ལམ་རྒྱགས་ཐམས་ཅད་འབྱོར་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>A leader acquires many servants and all necessary provisions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཟོང་ཆེན་པོ་བསྡུ་བའི་ཕྱིར་འགྲོའོ་སྙམ་ནས་སྐྱེ་བོ་མང་པོ་བསྡུས་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Thinking that he should set out to gather many goods, he rounds up many people and, without fear or panic,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་འཇིགས་ཤིང་སྐྲག་པ་མེད་པར་འབྲོག་དགོན་པ་དེ་ལས་འདའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>he leaves the wild forest.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ཡང་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་དེད་དཔོན་ཆེན་པོ་ལྟར་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་སྤྱོད་པས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Similarly, divine son, the bodhisattva great beings resemble that great leader as they engage in worldly conduct on the relative level.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཉེ་བར་འཚོ་བ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Thereby, they provide for all sentient beings and engage with great compassion,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གཡོག་མང་པོ་སྙིང་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོའི་སྦྱོར་བ་ཅན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>which can be likened to the many servants.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ལམ་རྒྱགས་འབྱོར་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They acquire all the roots of virtue, which are the provisions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ་དྲུག་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They possess the great profit that is comprised of the six perfections,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བསྡུ་བའི་དངོས་པོས་ཡོངས་སུ་བཟུང་ཞིང་བླ་ན་མེད་པའི་བསོད་ནམས་དང་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཡང་དག་པར་བསྡུ་བའི་ཁེ་ཆེན་པོ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཡང་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the means of attracting disciples, and unsurpassed merit and wisdom.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སེམས་ཅན་གྱི་ཁམས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་དོན་བྱེད་ཅིང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They act for the welfare of all realms of sentient beings</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ནས་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་དུ་འགྲོ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and proceed from buddha realm to buddha realm.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཉེ་བར་འཚོ་བར་གྱུར་ཅིང་ཐབས་ལ་མཁས་པས་བདེན་པ་རྣམས་ལ་སྒོམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Thus, they provide for sentient beings and meditate on the truths through being skilled in means.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, consider this analogy.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དཔེར་ན་ཤ་ནའི་རས་ལ་མེ་ཏོག་ཙམ་པ་ཀ་དང་མེ་ཏོག་འབར་ཤི་ཀས་བསྒོས་ན་དེའི་དྲི་མྱུར་དུ་ཡལ་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>If one infuses a hempen cloth with campaka and vārṣika flowers, their scent fades quickly.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བདེན་པ་ལ་སྒོམ་པ་ནི་ཡུན་ཐུང་བར་བལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, similarly, the hearers’ meditation on the truths is observed for just a short period of time.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་མྱུར་དུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་ནས་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Passing quickly into nirvāṇa, they do not bring forth the fragrance of the buddhas’ discipline,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཐོས་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>hearing,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>absorption,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤེས་རབ་དང་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>knowledge,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཡེ་ཤེས་ཀྱི་དྲི་ཡང་མི་འབྱིན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and wisdom.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བག་ཆགས་ཀྱི་མཚམས་སྦྱོར་བའི་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ཡང་སྤོང་མི་ནུས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Furthermore, they are unable to relinquish the disturbing emotions that are conjoined with the habitual tendencies.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, now consider another analogy.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དཔེར་ན་ཡུལ་ཀ་ཤི་ཀའི་གོས་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ལ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>If one were to infuse a cloth of precious Benares silk</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མི་དང་ལྷའི་སྤོས་དང་། མེ་ཏོག་གི་དྲིས་བསྐལ་པ་ཆེན་པོ་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་བསྒོས་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>for hundreds of thousands of great aeons with the scent of perfume and flowers from the human and divine realms,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེའི་ལྷའི་དྲི་དེ་རྟག་ཏུ་བྲོ་ཞིང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>its divine fragrance would be experienced in perpetuity,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དྲི་གཙང་མས་ལྷ་དང་མི་ཟིལ་གྱིས་གནོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and that pure aroma would overwhelm both gods and men.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་བདེན་པ་སྒོམ་པ་མི་སྒོམ་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བསྐལ་པ་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་གྲངས་མེད་པར་བསྒོམས་པ་ནི།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, similarly, the bodhisattva great beings without meditating meditate on the truths for incalculably many hundreds of thousands of eons.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རྣམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་མཆོག་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་མ་ཐོབ་ཀྱི་བར་དུ་བར་མ་དོར་དེ་ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་མི་འདའ་ཞིང་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They do not relinquish doing so until they have attained omniscient wisdom endowed with the supreme of all aspects and pass into complete nirvāṇa.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རྣམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་མཆོག་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཀྱི་དྲི་མི་དམིགས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་ཤིན་ཏུ་དྲི་ཞིམ་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And so, without reference points, they become exceedingly fragrant with the scent of omniscient wisdom endowed with the supreme of all aspects.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཐ་སྙད་དུ་ཉོན་མོངས་པའི་བག་ཆགས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་སྤོང་ཞིང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>In terms of worldly conventions, they abandon all their habitual tendencies toward the disturbing emotions</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷ་དང་། མི་དང་། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་དུ་བཅས་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་རྣམས་ཀྱང་འདུ་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and attract the worlds of gods, men, and demigods.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་བུ་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བ་རྣམ་པར་དུལ་བའི་དབང་ཕྱུག་གིས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Then the god Lord of Peace and Calm asked Mañjuśrī</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག་དེའི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་དགེ་འདུན་དེ་ཅི་འདྲ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Kumārabhuta, “Mañjuśrī, how is the spiritual community of hearers that belong to the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Ratnaketu?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་དད་པའི་རྗེས་སུ་འགྲོ་བ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Ultimately, they are not devoted followers,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གཞན་ལ་དད་པས་འགྲོ་བ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>but they are also not devotedly turning to someone else.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་རིགས་ཀྱི་རྗེས་སུ་འགྲོ་བ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ། དོན་དམ་པར་ན་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་རིགས་ཀྱང་མི་གཏོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, they are not followers of the family, but neither do they ultimately abandon the family of the Thus-gone One.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྗེས་སུ་འགྲོ་བ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ། དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་གང་ཡང་མི་དམིགས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, they are not following the Dharma; indeed, ultimately they do not observe any Dharma at all.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བརྒྱད་པ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ། ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ལོག་པའི་ཆོས་བརྒྱད་དང་ཡང་བྲལ་ལོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, they do not possess the eight mistaken dharmas, but neither are they relatively free from them.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་རྒྱུན་དུ་ཞུགས་པ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ། འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཐ་སྙད་ཀྱི་བདེན་པར་ན་ངན་སོང་ཐམས་ཅད་ལས་ཀྱང་འདས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Ultimately they are not stream-enterers, yet in terms of the conventional truth of the world, they are beyond all the lower realms.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ལན་ཅིག་ཕྱིར་འོང་བ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ། ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་སེམས་ཅན་ཡོངས་སུ་སྨིན་པར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་འོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately they are not once-returners, yet relatively they do return in order to ripen beings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཕྱིར་མི་འོང་བ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ། ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལས་འོང་བ་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately they are not non-returners, yet relatively from all phenomena there is no return.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately they are not worthy ones,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཐ་སྙད་དུ་ན་ལྷ་དང་བཅས་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱིས་བླ་ན་མེད་པའི་མཆོད་པར་འོས་པ་ཡང་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>yet according to worldly conventions they are supremely worthy of veneration by the world along with its gods.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱང་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately they are not hearers,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མི་དམིགས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལས་ཐོས་པ་ཡང་འཛིན་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>yet, without conceptually apprehending them, they do listen to all the blessed buddhas.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་འདོད་ཆགས་དང་བྲལ་བ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Ultimately they are not without attachment,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་འདོད་ཆགས་ཀྱི་ཡོངས་སུ་གདུང་བས་ཀྱང་མི་གདུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>yet relatively they are unharmed by the torments of attachment.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཞེ་སྡང་དང་བྲལ་བ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately they are not without anger,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ཞེ་སྡང་གི་ཡོངས་སུ་གདུང་བས་ཀྱང་མི་གདུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>yet relatively they are unharmed by the torments of anger.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་གཏི་མུག་དང་བྲལ་བ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately they are not without delusion,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་མུན་པ་མུན་ནག་དང་བྲལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>yet relatively all phenomena are free from darkness.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་དང་བྲལ་བ་ཡང་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately they are not without disturbing emotions,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་གདུལ་བའི་ཕྱིར་ཡང་བརྩོན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>yet relatively they endeavor to tame the disturbing emotions of all beings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཐོག་མ་ནས་མ་སྐྱེས་པ་ངེས་པར་ཞུགས་ཀྱང་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately they have abided definitively in non-origination from the very beginning,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བསམས་བཞིན་དུ་སྲིད་པ་ལེན་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>yet relatively they consciously take up existence.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་འཁོར་བ་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་འཛིན་མོད་ཀྱི།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Relatively they embrace cyclic existence,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་གང་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་འཛིན་པ་དང་གཏོང་བ་ཡང་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>yet ultimately there is no grasping to or abandoning of any phenomenon.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་དྲན་པ་དང་བྲལ་བར་མི་མཐོང་བས་མཐོང་བ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Ultimately, without intense mindfulness regarding all phenomena, they see without seeing.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་དྲན་པ་ཉེ་བར་གཞག་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་སྒོམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Relatively, however, they train in the foundations of mindfulness.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་མ་འགགས་པར་མི་ཤེས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་ཀྱང་རབ་ཏུ་ཤེས་ལ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, without knowing, they know that all phenomena are unborn and unceasing.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་སྤྱོད་པར་ན་ཡང་དག་པར་སྤོང་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་སྒོམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>In terms of worldly experience, however, they train in the thorough relinquishments.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ལུས་དང་སེམས་མེད་པ་ཡང་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཀྱི་བདེན་པར་ན་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱི་རྐང་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་སྒྲུབ་བོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, they have neither body nor mind yet, in the relative truth of the world, they have accomplished the bases of miraculous power.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་དབང་པོ་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་བྲལ་ཡང་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately they are without any faculties,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་དབང་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་སྒྲུབ་བོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>yet relatively they have accomplished all the faculties.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་རབ་ཏུ་དངོས་པོ་མེད་པར་མི་མཐོང་བའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་མཐོང་ཡང་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, without seeing, they see that all phenomena are unreal.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ང་རྒྱལ་ཅན་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཚར་གཅོད་པའི་ཕྱིར་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>However, in order to eradicate the conceit and conceptual apprehension of everyone who is conceited and engages in conceptual apprehension,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མི་སྒོམ་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་སྟོབས་ཀྱང་སྒོམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>they train, without training, in the power‌s.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་དངོས་པོ་མེད་པར་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, in order to make it understood that all phenomena are unreal,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མི་སྒོམ་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཡན་ལག་རྣམས་ཀྱང་སྒོམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>they train, without training, in the branches of awakening.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་དངོས་པོ་མེད་ཀྱང་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་སྒོམ་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་ལམ་ཡང་སྒོམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Although ultimately utterly unreal, relatively they train in the path by means of not training.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་ལ་ཞི་གནས་མངོན་པར་སྒྲུབ་བོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, they accomplish tranquillity within the limit of reality.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ལྷག་མཐོང་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་སྐྱེ་བར་མི་སྒོམ་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་མཐོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, by not training, they see insight to be utterly unarisen.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་མ་རིག་པ་ཟད་པ་ཉིད་དུ་མི་དམིགས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་རིག་པ་སྐྱེད་དེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, their knowledge is born through not apprehending ignorance as something to be exhausted.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཟད་པའམ་སྐྱེ་བ་མི་དམིགས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, neither exhaustion nor arising is observed.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཤའི་མིག་གིས་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་། སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་མཐོང་ལ་དེ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཅི་ཡང་མི་མཐོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Although they see all beings and all buddha realms with their physical eye, ultimately they see nothing whatsoever.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ལྷའི་མིག་གིས་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་འཆི་འཕོ་དང་སྐྱེ་བ་ཡང་དག་པ་ཇི་ལྟ་བ་བཞིན་དུ་མཐོང་ཡང་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཅི་ཡང་མི་མཐོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Although they see all the deaths, transmigrations, and rebirths of all beings so clearly with their divine eye, ultimately they see nothing whatsoever.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱི་མིག་གིས་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སེམས་ཀྱི་སྤྱོད་པ་དང་། གཡོ་བ་རྣམས་ཡང་དག་པ་ཇི་ལྟ་བ་བཞིན་དུ་ཤེས་ཀྱང་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཅི་ཡང་མི་ཤེས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Although they know all the experiences and movements of the minds of all beings with their eye of wisdom, ultimately they know nothing whatsoever.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་མིག་གིས་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡང་དག་པ་ཇི་ལྟ་བ་བཞིན་དུ་མཐོང་ཡང་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཅི་ཡང་མི་མཐོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Although they see all dharmas with their dharma eye, ultimately they see nothing whatsoever.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་སྤྱན་གྱིས་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་མཛད་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་བྱེད་ཀྱང་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཅི་ཡང་མི་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Although they perform all the acts of a buddha with their buddha eye, ultimately they perform nothing whatsoever.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ལྷའི་རྣ་བས་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་ཐོས་ཀྱང་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཅི་ཡང་མི་ཐོས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Although with their divine ear they hear the teachings of all the blessed buddhas, ultimately they hear nothing whatsoever.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་སེམས་གཅིག་གིས་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སེམས་ལ་ལྟ་ཡང་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཅི་ཡང་མི་ལྟའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Although with their single mind they view the minds of all beings, ultimately they view nothing whatsoever.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་རྗེས་སུ་དྲན་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཀྱིས་སྔོན་གྱི་མཐའ་ཡང་རྗེས་སུ་དྲན་མོད་ཀྱི་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཅི་ཡང་མི་དྲན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Although with their wisdom of recollection they surely recollect the very dawn of time, ultimately they recollect nothing whatsoever.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱིས་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་པར་འགྲོ་ཡང་དོན་དམ་པར་ན། འོང་བའམ་འགྲོ་བ་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Although they visit the inconceivable buddha realms by means of their miraculous powers, ultimately there is no coming or going.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནི་ཟག་པ་ཟད་ཀྱང་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཟད་པའི་ཆོས་ཅན་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Although their defilements are exhausted, ultimately there is nothing to be exhausted.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྣང་ཡང་སྣང་ལ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་དེའི་ལུས་ཡོངས་སུ་གྲུབ་པ་ཡང་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Although they appear as beings, ultimately their bodies are devoid of true existence.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྨྲ་ཡང་སྨྲ་ལ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཡི་གེར་ཡང་མི་བརྗོད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Although they speak, ultimately their speech is not pronounced in the form of syllables.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སེམས་ཀྱང་སེམས་ལ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་སེམས་དང་སེམས་ལས་བྱུང་བའི་ཆོས་སུ་བརྗོད་པར་བྱ་བ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Although they think, ultimately thought is not something that can be expressed as mind or mental phenomena.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་གཟུགས་སུ་ཡང་མི་སྣང་ལ་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་སྐྱེས་བུ་ཆེན་པོའི་མཚན་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་ནི་བརྒྱན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately they do not appear as form, but relatively they are adorned with the thirty-two marks and ornamented with the excellent signs of great beings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དཔེ་བྱད་བཟང་པོས་ནི་སྤྲས། བསོད་ནམས་དང་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཀྱི་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས་ནི་བརྒྱན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They are adorned with the accumulations of merit and wisdom.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གཟི་བརྗིད་ནི་བསྙེན་པར་དཀའ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Their splendor is dazzling.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བརྗོད་པ་ནི་རྣམ་པར་བསྒྲགས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Their speech resounds.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ཀྱི་བྱུག་པས་ནི་བྱུགས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They have been anointed with the unguent of discipline.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ངན་དུ་སྨྲ་བའི་ཚིག་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ནི་ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མོངས་པར་གྱུར་པ་མེད།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Words spoken with ill intent cause them no disturbing emotions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པས་ནི་རྣམ་པར་རོལ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They sport in clairvoyant powers.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཐོས་པས་ནི་རྣམ་པར་ཤིགས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Their learning sets them free.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྤོབས་པས་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་སྒྲོག །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>With their eloquence they make declarations.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཀྱིས་ནི་རྣམ་པར་འཕྲུལ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Relatively, they produce emanations by means of wisdom;</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཡེ་ཤེས་ཀྱི་འོད་ཀྱིས་ནི་མུན་པ་མུན་ནག་སེལ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>with the light of wisdom they dispel all darkness;</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱིས་ནི་སྣང་བར་བྱེད།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>with knowledge they illuminate;</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མཐའ་ཡས་པར་བསྟན་པ་ནི་རྟོགས་པར་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>their teaching knows no limit, and is assimilated as realization.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ནི་སྐྱབས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Relatively, for all beings they are the refuge, and because of their awakening they constantly consider beings—</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ནི་རྟག་ཏུ་གཟིགས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>who are continuously beheld by the blessed buddhas,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཉན་ཐོས་དང་རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དང་། མུ་སྟེགས་ཅན་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་ནི་མི་བལྟ་ཞིང་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཕྱིར་ནི་རྟག་ཏུ་བལྟ་བ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>but who are not considered by the hearers, solitary buddhas, and the extremists with reference points— so that,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བསྟན་པ་ནི་ཟད་མི་ཤེས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>relatively, their teaching knows no exhaustion,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དྲན་པ་ནི་རྒྱ་མཚོ་དང་འདྲ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>their mindfulness is like the ocean,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ནི་རི་རབ་དང་མཚུངས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>their absorption is comparable to the central mountain,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཟོད་པ་ནི་ས་དང་འདྲའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and their patience is like the earth.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་སེལ་བའི་ཕྱིར་དཔའ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Relatively, they are courageous when it comes to clearing away all thoughts;</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མི་ཤེས་པའི་མུན་པ་མུན་ནག་སེལ་བའི་ཕྱིར་ཉི་མ་ལྟ་བུའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>they shine like the sun to dispel the deep darkness of ignorance;</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རབ་ཏུ་སྣང་བའི་ཕྱིར་ཟླ་བ་དང་འདྲའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>they shine like the moon in order to illuminate the world.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་འདུ་བའི་ཕྱིར་དབང་པོ་དང་མཚུངས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Relatively, they are like a ruler in order to attract others.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་སེམས་ལ་དབང་བྱེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཚངས་པ་དང་འདྲའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Relatively, they are like Brahmā in order to master the mind.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་དབང་བྱེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་མི་མཉམ་པ་དང་མཉམ་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Relatively, they are incomparable in order to master space.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ཐམས་ཅད་རྗེས་སུ་སོང་ཡང་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་གང་དུ་སོང་བའམ་འོངས་པའམ། འདུག་པ་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Relatively they have followed, but ultimately there is no one who goes, comes, or remains.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Why is that?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་བྱུང་བའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Because ultimately all phenomena are utterly unarisen.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག་དེའི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་དགེ་འདུན་ནི་དེ་དང་འདྲ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, such is the spiritual community of hearers belonging to the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Ratnaketu.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་བས་ཀྱང་ལྷག་པར་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་པའི་ཆོས་དང་ཡང་ལྡན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Moreover, the dharma that they possess is even more inconceivable than that.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་མི་དམིགས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བསྟན་པ་འདི་བཤད་པ་ན་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>When Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta delivered this teaching in a manner beyond reference points,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དགེ་སློང་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>five hundred monks,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དགེ་བསྙེན་ལྔ་བརྒྱ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>five hundred laypeople,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ལྔ་སྟོང་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and five thousand gods who held reference points all made this supplication:</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ཅག་ཀྱང་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག་དེའི་ཉན་ཐོས་སུ་གྱུར་ཅིག །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, may we also become hearers belonging to the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Ratnaketu.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī replied, “Well, my friends, in that buddha realm no-one with reference points is born!</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀྱེ་གྲོགས་པོ་དག་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་དེར་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་མི་སྐྱེའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>My friends, only bodhisattva great beings who are free from reference points are born there without being born.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀྱེ་གྲོགས་པོ་དག་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དམིགས་པ་མེད་པ་རྣམས་ནི་མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་དེར་སྐྱེའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>My friends, if you aspire to that realm, you must strive in the perfection of knowledge in a manner free from reference points.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀྱེ་གྲོགས་པོ་དག་གལ་ཏེ་ཁྱེད་ཀྱང་དེར་འདོད་ན་ཁྱེད་ཀྱིས་མི་དམིགས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས། ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ་ལ་བརྩོན་པར་གྱིས་ཤིག །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>My friends, when you strive in the perfection of knowledge in a manner that is free from reference points,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀྱེ་གྲོགས་པོ་དག་ཁྱེད་ནམ་ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ་ལ་མི་དམིགས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བརྩོན་པར་གྱུར་པ་དེའི་ཚེ། གྲོགས་པོ་དག་ཁྱེད་ལ་རྣམ་པའི་མཆོག་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་ལྡན་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>then, my friends, it will not be difficult to discover omniscient wisdom that is endowed with the supreme of all aspects.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཀྱང་རྙེད་པར་མི་དཀའ་ན། སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ཡོངས་སུ་དག་པར་སྐྱེ་བ་ལྟ་སྨོས་ཀྱང་ཅི་དགོས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>So what need is there to mention that you will also be born in the pure buddha realms!”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བ་རྣམ་པར་དུལ་བའི་དབང་ཕྱུག་གིས་ཡང་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god Lord of Peace and Calm then asked Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་འདུལ་བ་ནི་ཇི་ལྟ་བུ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, what is the vinaya of the hearers like?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་འདུལ་བ་ནི་ཇི་ལྟ་བུ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And how is the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཁམས་གསུམ་གྱིས་སྐྲག་པས་བཏུལ་བ་ནི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, the vinaya that is well known in the three worlds is the vinaya of the hearers.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བའི་ཚོགས་ཐམས་ཅད་བསགས་ཤིང་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་དབུགས་འབྱིན་པ་དང་། ཁམས་གསུམ་དུ་བསམས་བཞིན་དུ་སྐྱེ་བས་བཏུལ་བ་ནི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>However, on the relative level, the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings gathers all accumulations of roots of virtue, comforts all beings, and tames them by taking birth in the three realms.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་སྡང་བ་ནི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“The vinaya of the hearers opposes all disturbing emotions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་སྤོང་བའི་ཕྱིར་རྗེས་སུ་བཏུལ་བ་ནི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>However, relatively, the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings goes further in order to eliminate the disturbing emotions of all beings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཕྱོགས་གཅིག་རིག་པ་ནི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“The vinaya of the hearers is aware of just one place.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཕྱོགས་བཅུ་མཐའ་ཡས་མུ་མེད་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་ཐམས་ཅད་རིག་པ་ནི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>However, relatively, the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings is aware of all the limitless and boundless worlds in the ten directions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བདུད་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་བཏང་སྙོམས་པ་ནི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“The vinaya of the hearers maintains equanimity with regard to all demons.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཕྱོགས་བཅུ་མཐའ་ཡས་མུ་མེད་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་སུ་གཏོགས་པའི་བདུད་ཀྱི་རིགས་ཐམས་ཅད་དཀྲུགས་ཤིང་། ཕྱིར་རྒོལ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་འཇོམས་པ་ནི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>However, relatively, the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings disturbs all classes of demons in all the limitless and boundless worlds in the ten directions, and conquers all hostile forces.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བདག་གི་རྒྱུད་གསལ་བར་བྱེད་པ་ནི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“The vinaya of the hearers clarifies one’s own mind stream.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་རྒྱུད་གསལ་བར་བྱེད་ཅིང་། ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་སྣང་བར་བྱེད་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings clarifies the mind streams of all beings, causes the wisdom of omniscience to manifest,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་བསྒྲིབས་པ་མེད་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་མཐོང་བ་སྣང་བར་བྱེད་པ་ནི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>However, relatively, and causes the vision of stainless wisdom with regard to all phenomena to manifest.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རང་གི་སེམས་ཀྱིས་བསམས་པ་ནི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“The vinaya of the hearers is contemplated by individual minds.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདས་པ་དང་། མ་བྱོན་པ་དང་། ད་ལྟར་གྱི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་དགོངས་པ་ནི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>However, relatively, the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings is the intent of all the buddhas in the past, the present, and the future.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རྡོ་ཆག་པའི་འཕྲོ་མི་འབྱོར་པ་ལྟ་བུ་ནི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“The vinaya of the hearers is like a stone that cannot be repaired when broken.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གསེར་དང་། དངུལ་ཆག་པའི་འཕྲོ་འབྱོར་པ་ལྟ་བུ་ནི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>However, relatively, the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings is like gold and silver, which can be mended when broken.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་། ཐབས་མཁས་པ་དང་བྲལ་བ་ནི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“The vinaya of the hearers does not contain all the teachings of the Buddha, and it also lacks skillful means.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཐབས་མཁས་པ་ཆེན་པོ་དང་། སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་བསྡུ་བས་བསྡུས་པ་ནི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>However, relatively, the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings has great skillful means and comprises all the teachings of the Buddha.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྟོབས་བཅུ་དང་། མི་འཇིགས་པ་དང་། མ་འདྲེས་པ་དང་། ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་དང་བྲལ་བ་ནི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“The vinaya of the hearers does not embody the ten strengths, the various types of fearlessness, the unique qualities, or omniscient wisdom.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྟོབས་བཅུ་དང་། མི་འཇིགས་པ་དང་། མ་འདྲེས་པ་དང་། ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་སུ་བསྡུ་བས་བསྡུས་པ་ནི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>However, relatively, the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings contains the ten powers, the various types of fearlessness, the unique qualities, and omniscient wisdom.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མེས་ཚིག་པ་ལས་འབྲོས་པ་ལྟ་བུ་ནི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“The vinaya of the hearers is like escaping from being burned by a fire.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྐྱེད་མོས་ཚལ་དང་། གཞལ་མེད་ཁང་ལྟ་བུར་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དགའ་བས་དགའ་བ་ནི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>However, relatively, the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings is to be delighted by the joy of Dharma, just as one would enjoy a park or a palace.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བག་ཆགས་ཀྱི་རྒྱུན་མ་ཆད་པ་ནི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“The vinaya of the hearers does not interrupt the stream of habitual patterns.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བག་ཆགས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡང་དག་པར་བཅོམ་པ་ནི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>However, relatively, the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings overcomes all habitual patterns.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་མདོར་ན་ཚད་དུ་གཏོགས་པ་ཚད་ཀྱི་ཆོས་ཀྱིས་དྲངས་པ་ནི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, in short, the vinaya of the hearers is derived from a Dharma that is limited and confined.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཚད་དུ་གཏོགས་པ་མ་ཡིན་པ་ཚད་མེད་པའི་ཆོས་ཀྱིས་དྲངས་པ་ནི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>However, relatively, the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings follows a Dharma that is limitless and beyond measure.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཚད་ཡོད་པའི་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“The vinaya of the hearers brings the attainment of limited discipline,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཐོས་པ་དང་། ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དང་། ཤེས་རབ་དང་། རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བ་དང་། རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་མཐོང་བ་ཐོབ་པར་བྱེད་པ་ནི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>learning, absorption, knowledge, liberation, and vision of the wisdom of liberation.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཚད་མེད་པའི་ཡོན་ཏན་དང་ལྡན་ཞིང་། ཚད་ཡོད་པ་མ་ཡིན་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>possesses limitless qualities,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཚད་མེད་པའི་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དང་། ཐོས་པ་དང་། ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དང་། ཤེས་རབ་དང་། རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and makes one attain limitless discipline, learning, absorption, knowledge, liberation,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་མཐོང་བ་ཐོབ་པར་བྱེད་པ་ནི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and vision of the wisdom of liberation.” However, relatively, the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings knows no bounds,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་ལེགས་སོ། །ཞེས་བྱ་བ་བྱིན་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>At this point, the Blessed One expressed his approval of Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta: “Well said, Mañjuśrī!</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་འདུལ་བ་ལེགས་པར་བཤད་པ་ལེགས་སོ་ལེགས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>You have explained the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings well on the relative level. Well done, well done.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཡང་འདི་ལྟར་དོན་དེ་ཉིད་བསྟན་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཁྱོད་ལ་དཔེ་བསྟན་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Now, Mañjuśrī, in order to illustrate the meaning of this, I will give you some examples.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དཔེར་ན་སྐྱེས་བུ་གཉིས་ཤིག་ཡོད་ལ། དེ་ལས་སྐྱེས་བུ་གཅིག་ནི་བ་ལང་གི་རྗེས་ཀྱི་བསྔགས་པ་སྨྲ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>imagine two men: one of them praises the hoofprints of an ox,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྐྱེས་བུ་གཅིག་ནི་རྒྱ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོའི་བསྔགས་པ་སྨྲ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>while the other man praises the ocean.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་ཇི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī, what do you think?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྐྱེས་བུ་དེས་བ་ལང་གི་རྗེས་ཀྱི་བསྔགས་པ་ཇི་སྙེད་ཅིག་བརྗོད་ནུས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>How extensively would the first man be able to praise the hoofprints of an ox?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་གསོལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བ་ལང་གི་རྗེས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་ཆུང་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, since all ox hoofprints are so small,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེའི་བསྔགས་པ་ལྟ་ཅི་སྨོས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>what is even the use of praising them?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་བ་ལང་གི་རྗེས་ཆུང་བ་ལྟར་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་འདུལ་བར་བལྟའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Just as the ox hoofprints are small, so you should view the vinaya of the hearers.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ཇི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Now, Mañjuśrī, what do you think?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྐྱེས་བུ་ཅིག་ཤོས་དེས་རྒྱ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོའི་བསྔགས་པ་ཇི་ཙམ་ཞིག་བརྗོད་ནུས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Would the other man be able to express a fitting praise of the ocean?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་གསོལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྒྱ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོའི་བསྔགས་པ་ནི་ཤིན་ཏུ་མང་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, the praises of the ocean could be incredibly numerous,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དཔག་ཏུ་མ་མཆིས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>limitless,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་བོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and inconceivable.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་རྒྱ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོའི་བསྔགས་པ་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་པ་ལྟར་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་འདུལ་བར་བལྟའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, just as the praises of the ocean are boundless, so you should view the vinaya of the bodhisattvas on the relative level.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་བསྟན་པ་འདི་མི་སྟོན་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བཤད་པ་ན་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>As he delivered this teaching without teaching,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཁྲི་ཉིས་སྟོང་གིས་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་མ་སྐྱེས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་སེམས་སྐྱེས་ནས་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>12,000 gods, without ultimately forming anything, formed the wish for unexcelled and completely perfect awakening.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཚིག་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་ཀྱང་སྨྲ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They all declared,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ཅག་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་བསླབ་པ་འདི་ལ་མི་སློབ་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་སློབ་བོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, without training, we will practice the trainings of the bodhisattvas.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་ལྷའི་བུ་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བ་རྣམ་པར་དུལ་བའི་དབང་ཕྱུག་གིས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god Lord of Peace and Calm asked Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཅི་འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་འདུལ་བ་ལ་བསླབས་སམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, do you train in the vinaya of the hearers</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོན་ཏེ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་འདུལ་བ་ལ་བསླབས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>or in the vinaya of the bodhisattvas?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī answered,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་འདི་ཇི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, what do you think?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རྒྱ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོར་མི་ཤོང་བའི་ཆུ་གང་ཡང་ཡོད་དམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Is there any water that cannot be contained in the ocean?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་རྒྱ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོར་མི་ཤོང་བའི་ཆུ་གང་ཡང་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“No, Mañjuśrī, there is no water anywhere that cannot be contained in the ocean.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་འདུལ་བ་ནི་རྒྱ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོ་དང་འདྲའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, in the same way the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings is like the ocean.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god asked,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འདུལ་བ་འདུལ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཚིག་གི་དོན་གང་ཡིན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, that word vinaya, what does that mean?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī answered,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་འདུལ་བ་ནི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, on the relative level vinaya refers to taming the disturbing emotions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་ཤེས་པའང་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Vinaya also means understanding disturbing emotions.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་འདུལ་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, how does one tame the disturbing emotions?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཇི་ལྟར་ན་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་ཤེས་པ་ཡིན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>How does one understand disturbing emotions?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་མ་བྱུང་མ་སྐྱེས་དངོས་པོ་མེད་པ་ཡིན་ན་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་མེད་པ་ལ་ཕྱིན་ཅི་ལོག་ཏུ་གྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Ultimately, all phenomena are unborn, unarisen, and unreal. Yet this absence is misunderstood on the relative level.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མེད་པ་ལས་ཕྱིན་ཅི་ལོག་ཏུ་གྱུར་པ་དེ་ལས་ཀུན་ཏུ་རྟོག་པ་དང་། རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Misunderstanding this absence produces concepts and thoughts.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་ཏུ་རྟོག་པ་དང་། རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་པ་དེ་ལས་ཚུལ་བཞིན་མ་ཡིན་པ་ཡིད་ལ་བྱེད་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Out of concept and thought appears mistaken conceptual activity.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཚུལ་བཞིན་མ་ཡིན་པ་ཡིད་ལ་བྱེད་པ་དེ་ལས་བདག་ཏུ་སྒྲོ་འདོགས་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mistaken conceptual activity then gives rise to the superimposition of a self.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བདག་ཏུ་སྒྲོ་འདོགས་པ་དེ་ལས་ལྟ་བ་ཀུན་ནས་ལྡང་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>From the superimposition of a self comes the manifestation of views.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྟ་བ་ཀུན་ནས་ལྡང་བ་དེ་ལས་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་རྣམས་འབྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Based on the manifestation of views, disturbing emotions appear.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གང་ཡང་ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་མ་བྱུང་དངོས་པོ་མེད་པར་མི་ཤེས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་རབ་ཏུ་ཤེས་པ་དེ་ནི་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཕྱིན་ཅི་མ་ལོག་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, whoever knows, without knowing, that ultimately all phenomena are utterly unborn, utterly unarisen, and utterly unreal, is unmistaken in terms of the ultimate.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གང་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཕྱིན་ཅི་མ་ལོག་པ་དེ་ནི་རྟོག་པ་མེད་ཅིང་རྣམ་པར་མི་རྟོག་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Whoever is unmistaken in terms of the ultimate does not form concepts or thoughts.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གང་རྟོག་པ་མེད་ཅིང་རྣམ་པར་མི་རྟོག་པ་དེ་ནི་ཚུལ་བཞིན་རབ་ཏུ་སྦྱོར་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Whoever does not form concepts or thoughts is applying himself correctly.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གང་ཚུལ་བཞིན་རབ་ཏུ་སྦྱོར་བ་དེ་ལ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བདག་ཏུ་སྒྲོ་འདོགས་པ་མི་འབྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Whoever applies himself correctly does not ultimately form superimpositions of a self.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གང་ལ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བདག་ཏུ་སྒྲོ་འདོགས་པ་མི་འབྱུང་བ་དེ་ལ་ལྟ་བ་ཀུན་ནས་ལྡང་བར་མི་འགྱུར་བ་ནས་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པར་ལྟ་བ་ཀུན་ནས་ལྡང་བར་ཡང་མི་འགྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>When superimpositions of a self do not ultimately arise, manifest views also do not arise, and ultimately even the views related to passing beyond suffering do not arise.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ལྟར་མ་སྐྱེས་པ་ལ་སྤྱོད་པ་དེ་ནི་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྣམ་པར་དུལ་བར་མི་ལྟ་བའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བགྱི་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>In that way one comes to experience the unborn, and pacifies disturbing emotions in a manner free from views.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་འདི་ནི་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་འདུལ་བ་ཞེས་བྱའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, this is what is meant by taming disturbing emotions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ནམ་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་རྣམས་ལ་སྣང་བ་མེད་པའི་ཤེས་རབ་དང་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཀྱིས་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་སྟོང་པ་དང་། ཤིན་ཏུ་མཚན་མ་མེད་པ་དང་། ཤིན་ཏུ་སྨོན་པ་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, disturbing emotions are ultimately utterly empty, utterly signless and utterly wishless due to the insight and wisdom to which no disturbing emotions ever appear.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་མ་བྱུང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>When one has the insight that ultimately they are utterly unborn, utterly unarisen,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དངོས་པོ་མེད་པར་མི་ཤེས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་རབ་ཏུ་ཤེས་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and utterly unreal,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེའི་ཚེ་མི་ཤེས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་རྣམས་ཡོངས་སུ་ཤེས་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>then, divine son, one knows disturbing emotions in a manner free from knowing.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, consider this analogy.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དཔེར་ན་སྦྲུལ་ཁ་གདུག་པའི་རིག་སྔགས་འདོན་པ་དེས་ནི་སྦྲུལ་ཁ་གདུག་པའི་གདུག་པ་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>If you chant an incantation against a viper’s venom, it is possible to neutralize the snake’s poison.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་གང་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་རིགས་རབ་ཏུ་ཤེས་པ་དེའི་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་རྣམས་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་དམིགས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, in the same way, whoever understands the types of disturbing emotions will neutralize his disturbing emotions in a manner that is beyond reference points.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཉོན་མོངས་པའི་རིགས་དེ་གང་ཡིན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, what are the types of disturbing emotions?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་མ་བྱུང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utterly unborn, utterly unarisen, and utterly unreal.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དངོས་པོ་མེད་པ་ལ་གང་ཀུན་ཏུ་རྟོག་པ་དེ་ནི་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་རིགས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Any conceptualization of that state is a form of disturbing emotion.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཀུན་ཏུ་མི་རྟོག་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མི་མོངས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, there are no conceptualizations, so therefore there are also no disturbing emotions whatsoever.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མོངས་པས་ཀུན་གཞི་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, because there are no disturbing emotions, there is no all-ground.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་གཞི་མེད་པས་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་མི་གནས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Because there is no all-ground, there is ultimately no abiding.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མི་གནས་པས་དོན་དམ་པར་མི་འཚིག་གོ །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Because there is no abiding, there is ultimately no scorching.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མི་འཚིག་པས་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཉེ་བར་ཞི་བ་ཞེས་བྱའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Because there is ultimately no scorching, there is said to be peace.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཇི་སྐད་སྨྲས་པ་བཞིན་དུ་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the ultimate level, things are not as they are expressed in words.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་འདི་ནི་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་འདུལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Still, divine son, relatively this is how disturbing emotions are tamed.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་རྣམས་འདུལ་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, how are disturbing emotions tamed?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཅི་ཡོད་པ་ཞིག་གམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Are they something?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོན་ཏེ་མེད་པ་ཞིག །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Or nothing?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ་ལྷའི་བུ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, this is how it is.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དཔེར་ན་སྐྱེས་བུ་ཞིག་གཉིད་ཀྱིས་ལོག་པའི་རྨི་ལམ་ལ་སྦྲུལ་ཁ་གདུག་པས་ཟིན་ནས་དེ་སྡུག་བསྔལ་གྱིས་གཙེ་བ་ལས་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Imagine a man who has a nightmare in which he is bitten by a venomous viper.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཡང་དུག་སྨན་བཏང་ནས། དེའི་གདུག་པ་མེད་པར་གྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Although he is suffering, he is treated with an antidote and recovers.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གདུག་པ་མེད་པར་གྱུར་པས་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཡང་མེད་པར་གྱུར་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>As the poison is neutralized, his pain disappears.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་ཇི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, what do you think?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྐྱེས་བུ་དེ་ཡང་དག་པར་ཟིན་ཏམ་འོན་ཏེ་ཡང་དག་པ་མ་ཡིན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Was this man actually bitten or not?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་ཡང་དག་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, ultimately it did not truly happen.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཇི་ལྟར་དུག་དེ་མེད་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, how was the poison neutralized?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ཟིན་པ་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་བདེན་པ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་དུག་མེད་པར་གྱུར་པ་ཡང་ཤིན་ཏུ་བདེན་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, just as the bite was not truly real, the neutralization of the poison was also not truly real.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་འཕགས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱང་དོན་དམ་པར་མི་བལྟ་བའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བལྟའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, in the same way the noble ones view, without viewing, all disturbing emotions on the ultimate level.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་གང་ཡང་འདི་སྐད་དུ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་རྣམས་འདུལ་བར་འགྱུར་ཞེས་ཟེར་བ་ནི་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, you ask how disturbing emotions are tamed.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཇི་ལྟར་བདག་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བདག་མེད་པ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་རྣམས་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Well, divine son, just as the ego ultimately is egoless, so, divine son, disturbing emotions are not ultimately disturbing emotions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་སྟེ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བདག་དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་ཡིན་ན་ནི་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, ultimately this self is suchness.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ཡང་དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་དུ་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Therefore, divine son, disturbing emotions also ultimately become suchness.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་འདི་ལྟར་བདག་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བདག་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, in this way, the self is not ultimately the self.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བས་ན་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱང་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Therefore, divine son, disturbing emotions are also not ultimately disturbing emotions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་ལ་གང་གི་དོན་དམ་པར་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་འདུལ་བར་དམིགས་པར་འགྱུར་བ་ནི་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་གང་ཡང་མི་དམིགས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, whoever focuses on taming disturbing emotions on the ultimate level is not ultimately focusing on anything.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་བྱུང་བའི་ཕྱིར་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཞི་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, because on the ultimate level nothing manifests, and therefore all phenomena are pacified.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་འཛིན་པ་མེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཉེ་བར་ཞི་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, on the ultimate level, there is no grasping, and therefore all phenomena are fully pacified.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་སྒྲོ་བཏགས་པ་མེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, on the ultimate level, all phenomena are free from superimposition, and therefore all phenomena are completely pacified.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་མི་ཟད་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, on the ultimate level, all phenomena are utterly unborn, and therefore they are also beyond ceasing.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་དངོས་པོ་མེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, the ultimate level is utterly unreal and therefore all phenomena are utterly unborn.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྒོ་གང་ཡིན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, what is the gateway to all dharmas?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་སྨྲ་བར་བྱ་བ་དང་། སྨྲ་བ་དང་ཤེས་པ་དང་། ཤེས་པར་བྱ་བ་དང་བྱ་བ་དང་ཐ་སྙད་དང་། བྱེད་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་འཇུག་པའི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཀྱི་བདེན་པ་ནི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, the relative truth, which employs all forms of statements, speech, cognition, objects of cognition, activities, conventions, and acts, is a gateway to all dharmas.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྨྲ་བ་དང་། སྨྲ་བར་བྱ་བ་དང་། ཤེས་པ་དང་། ཤེས་པར་བྱ་བ་དང་། བྱ་བ་དང་། ཐ་སྙད་དང་། བྱེད་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལས་རྣམ་པར་ལོག་པའི་ཕྱིར་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་ནི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The ultimate truth, which is so because it is the opposite of all forms of speech, statements, cognition, objects of cognition, activities, conventions, and acts, is a gateway to all dharmas.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཡང་ལྷའི་བུ་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ཚུལ་བཞིན་མ་ཡིན་པའི་ཡིད་ལ་བྱེད་པ་ནི་འཁོར་བའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Moreover, divine son, on the relative level, the incorrect conceptual workings of the mind are a gateway to saṃsāra.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ཚུལ་བཞིན་ཡིད་ལ་བྱེད་པ་ནི་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, the correct conceptual workings of the mind are a gateway to nirvāṇa.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ཐེ་ཙོམ་ནི་སྒྲིབ་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“On the relative level, doubt is a gateway to obscuration.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བ་ནི་སྒྲིབ་པ་མེད་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, liberation is a gateway to the absence of obscuration.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ཀུན་ཏུ་རྟོག་པ་ནི་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“On the relative level, conceptuality is a gateway to disturbing emotions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ཀུན་ཏུ་མི་རྟོག་པ་ནི་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་མེད་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, non-conceptuality is a gateway to the absence of disturbing emotions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་རྣམ་པར་གཡེང་བ་ནི་རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“On the relative level, distraction is a gateway to thought.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ཞི་གནས་ནི་ཉེ་བར་ཞི་བའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, tranquility is a gateway to peace.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ལྟ་བར་གྱུར་པ་རྣམས་ནི་ང་རྒྱལ་གྱི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“On the relative level, holding views is a gateway to pride.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་སྟོང་པ་ཉིད་ནི་ང་རྒྱལ་མེད་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, emptiness is a gateway to the absence of pride.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་སྡིག་པའི་གྲོགས་པོ་དང་སྟེན་པ་ནི་མི་དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“On the relative level, relying on evil company is a gateway to all roots of non-virtue.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་དགེ་བའི་བཤེས་གཉེན་དང་སྟེན་པ་ནི་དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, relying on a virtuous spiritual friend is the gateway to all roots of virtue.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ལོག་པར་ལྟ་བ་ནི་སྡུག་བསྔལ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“On the relative level, wrong view is a gateway to all suffering.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ཡང་དག་པར་ལྟ་བ་ནི་བདེ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, correct view is a gateway to all happiness.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་སེར་སྣ་ནི་དབུལ་བའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“On the relative level, miserliness is a gateway to poverty.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་སྦྱིན་པ་ནི་ལོངས་སྤྱོད་ཆེན་པོའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, generosity is a gateway to great wealth.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ངང་ཚུལ་ངན་པ་ནི་ངན་འགྲོ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“On the relative level, a bad character is a gateway to all lower realms.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ནི་ལྷ་དང་མིར་སྐྱེ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, discipline is a gateway to all human and divine births.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་གནོད་སེམས་ནི་བྱད་གཟུགས་ངན་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“On the relative level, ill will is a gateway to an ugly appearance.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བཟོད་པ་ནི་གཟུགས་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, patience is a gateway to a beautiful appearance.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ལེ་ལོ་ནི་མི་རྟོགས་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“On the relative level, laziness is a gateway to a lack of realization.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་ནི་རྟོགས་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, diligence is a gateway to realization.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་པ་ནི་རྒོད་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“On the relative level, thought is a gateway to agitation.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བསམ་གཏན་ནི་སེམས་ཤིན་ཏུ་སྦྱངས་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, concentration is a gateway to pliability of mind.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་འཆལ་པའི་ཤེས་རབ་ནི་ཁོང་དུ་མི་ཆུད་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“On the relative level, faulty knowledge is a gateway to a lack of understanding.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ཤེས་རབ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཕྱོགས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་བདུན་གྱི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, knowledge is a gateway to the thirty-seven factors of awakening.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱམས་པ་ནི་ཁོང་མི་ཁྲོ་བའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“On the relative level, love is a gateway to not becoming angry.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་སྙིང་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོ་ནི་ལྷག་པའི་བསམ་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, great compassion is a gateway to an altruistic mind.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ལྷག་པའི་བསམ་པ་ནི་གཡོ་མེད་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, an altruistic mind is a gateway to the absence of deceit.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་དགའ་བ་ནི་ཆོས་ལ་མོས་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, joy is a gateway to conviction in the Dharma.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བཏང་སྙོམས་ན་ཉེས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་བྲལ་བའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, equanimity is a gateway to being free from all faults.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་དྲན་པ་ཉེ་བར་གཞག་པ་རྣམས་ནི་དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོངས་སུ་མི་འབྲི་བའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“On the relative level, the applications of mindfulness are a gateway to not letting any roots of virtue diminish.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ཡང་དག་པར་སྤོང་བ་རྣམས་ནི་ཡང་དག་པའི་ནན་ཏན་གྱི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, the thorough relinquishments are a gateway to genuine perseverance.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱི་རྐང་པ་རྣམས་ནི་ལུས་དང་སེམས་ལས་སུ་རུང་བའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, the bases of miraculous power are a gateway to pliancy of body and mind.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་དབང་པོ་རྣམས་ནི་དད་པ་ཐོབ་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, the faculties are a gateway to attaining faith.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་སྟོབས་རྣམས་ནི་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་འཇོམས་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, the power‌s are a gateway to conquering all disturbing emotions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཡན་ལག་རྣམས་ནི་ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པ་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, the branches of awakening are a gateway to realizing omniscience.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་འཕགས་པའི་ལམ་ཡན་ལག་བརྒྱད་པ་ནི་ལམ་ངན་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལས་འདའ་བའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, the eightfold path of the noble ones is a gateway to transcending all unwholesome paths.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་གཞན་ཡང་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སེམས་ནི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Moreover, divine son, on the relative level, the mind set on awakening is a gateway to all buddha qualities.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་དམ་པའི་ཆོས་ཡོངས་སུ་འཛིན་པ་ནི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་དབང་ཕྱུག་གི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, upholding the sacred Dharma is a gateway to becoming a lord of all dharmas.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་སེམས་ཅན་སྨིན་པར་བྱེད་པ་ནི་དམ་པའི་ཆོས་ཡོངས་སུ་འཛིན་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, ripening beings is a gateway to upholding the sacred Dharma.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ཐབས་ནི་གནས་དང་གནས་མ་ཡིན་པ་ལ་མཁས་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, method is a gateway to becoming learned regarding the correct and the incorrect.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ་ནི་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པའི་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the relative level, the perfection of knowledge is a gateway to nirvāṇa.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བ་ནི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྒོའོ།། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“On the ultimate level, the unarisen is a gateway to all dharmas.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་སྒོ་གང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, what is the gateway to the utterly unborn?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བ་ནི་ཀུན་ནས་སྒོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, on the ultimate level, the utterly unarisen is a gateway in every way.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བའི་རང་བཞིན་གང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, what is the nature of the utterly unarisen?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་དངོས་པོ་མེད་པ་ནི་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བའི་རང་བཞིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, on the ultimate level, the utterly unreal is the nature of the utterly unarisen.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བ་ལ་ཆ་ཤས་དབྱེ་བ་གང་ཡང་ཡོད་དམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, does the utterly unarisen have any divisions?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་ཇི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, what do you think?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་ཆ་ཤས་དབྱེ་བ་གང་ཡང་ཡོད་དམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Does the sky have any divisions?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god answered,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“No, Mañjuśrī, it does not.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཇི་ལྟར་ན་ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་ཆ་ཤས་དབྱེ་བ་མེད་པ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ལྷའི་བུ་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་པ་ལ་ཡང་ཆ་ཤས་དབྱེ་བ་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, in the same way, just as the sky does not have any divisions, so, divine son, does the utterly unborn also not have any divisions.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་ཤེས་སམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, do you comprehend the utterly unarisen on the ultimate level?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བས་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བ་ཡོངས་སུ་མི་ཤེས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, the utterly unarisen does not comprehend the utterly unarisen.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་ཤིང་མ་བྱུང་ལ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Because, divine son, all phenomena are utterly unborn, utterly unarisen,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དངོས་པོ་མེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and utterly unreal.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god asked,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཆོས་གང་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་ཤེས་ཤིང་གང་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པས་འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་སྤོབས་པར་གྱུར།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, are you this eloquent because you know and understand any phenomenon whatsoever?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་འདི་ཇི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, what do you think?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྲག་ཅས་ཆོས་གང་ཡོངས་སུ་ཤེས་ན། གང་དེ་ལས་སྒྲ་འབྱུང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Does an echo make a sound because it knows phenomena?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་བྲག་ཅས་ཆོས་གང་ཡང་ཡོངས་སུ་ཤེས་པ་མེད་མོད་ཀྱི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་རྐྱེན་ལས་སྒྲ་འབྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, of course an echo does not know any phenomena.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Instead, on the relative level, the sound appears from circumstances.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་དམིགས་པའི་རྐྱེན་གྱིས་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་མི་སྨྲ་བའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་སྨྲའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, in the same way, based on the circumstance of observing all beings, on the relative level a bodhisattva great being speaks without speaking.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god asked,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་ཅི་ལ་གནས་ཏེ་དེ་སྟོན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, on what basis do you teach?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་སྤྲུལ་པ་གང་ལ་གནས་ཏེ་དེ་སྟོན་པ་ལའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, on what type of emanation does the Thus-gone One base himself as he teaches?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་སྤྲུལ་པ་ནི་དོན་དམ་པ་ན་ཅི་ལའང་གནས་པ་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, the Thus-gone One does not ultimately base himself on any emanation whatsoever.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་མི་གནས་པར་བདག་མི་སྟོན་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, in the same way, on the ultimate level, without basing myself on any phenomena, I teach without teaching.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་སྟེ་ཁྱོད་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་མི་གནས་པར་མི་སྟོན་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་སྟོན་ན་ཁྱོད་ཅི་ལ་གནས་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, if, on the ultimate level, without basing yourself on any phenomena, you teach without teaching,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱ་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>on what basis do you awaken to unexcelled and completely perfect buddhahood?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་བདག་ནི་མཚམས་མེད་པ་རྣམས་ལ་གནས་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, I base myself on the acts with immediate consequence and,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་མི་རྒྱ་བའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>without awakening to completely perfect buddhahood, I awaken to unexcelled and completely perfect buddhahood.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མཚམས་མེད་པ་རྣམས་ཅི་ལ་གནས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“How do you base yourself on the acts with immediate consequence?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་མཚམས་མེད་པ་རྣམས་ནི་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་བྱུང་ཞིང་དངོས་པོ་མེད་པ་ལ་མི་གནས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་གནས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, ultimately the acts with immediate consequence do not truly exist and do not have any substance. It is on them that I base myself without basing myself.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་མཚམས་མེད་པ་རྣམས་བྱེད་པ་ནི་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བར་བཤད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, the Thus-gone One has explained that beings are born in hell because of committing the acts with immediate consequence.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཇི་ལྟར་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་མཚམས་མེད་པ་བྱེད་པ་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བར་བཤད་པ</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, the Thus-gone One has explained that beings are born in hell because of committing the acts with immediate consequence.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>་དེ་བཞིན་དུ། ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་མཚམས་མེད་པ་བྱེད་པ་མི་གནས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་མཚམས་མེད་པ་ལ་གནས་ན་མྱུར་དུ་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱའོ་ཞེས་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>In the same way, divine son, the Thus-gone One teaches, without teaching, how to quickly awaken to unexcelled and completely perfect buddhahood when basing oneself on the acts with immediate consequence,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མི་སྟོན་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>without basing oneself on the acts with immediate consequence.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་མཚམས་མེད་པ་དེ་གང་ཡིན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, what are the acts with immediate consequence?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་མཚམས་མེད་པ་གང་གིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་མྱུར་དུ་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, the acts with immediate consequence are those by which the bodhisattva great beings quickly,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཚང་མི་རྒྱ་བའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱ་བའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མཚམས་མེད་པ་ནི་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>without awakening to unexcelled and completely perfect buddhahood, perfectly awaken. Such are the acts with immediate consequence of the bodhisattva great beings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་མཚམས་མེད་པ་ལྔ་པོ་དེ་དག་གང་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, you may wonder what the five acts with immediate consequence are.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་འདི་ལ་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Well, divine son, the first act with immediate consequence of the bodhisattva great beings is as follows.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ནམ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ལྷག་པའི་བསམ་པས་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་ནས་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>When a bodhisattva great being with pure motivation, without developing, has developed the mind set on unexcelled and completely perfect buddhahood,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བར་མ་དོར་ཉན་ཐོས་དང་རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དང་། དམིགས་པ་ཅན་དང་། མུ་སྟེགས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སར་སེམས་མི་སྐྱེད་པ་འདི་ནི་ལྷའི་བུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་མཚམས་མེད་པ་དང་པོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>he does not develop the mind-set that aims for the levels of the hearers, solitary buddhas, anyone with reference points, or the extremists.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་གཞན་ཡང་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Moreover, divine son, the second act with immediate consequence of the bodhisattva great beings is as follows.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ནམ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་བདོག་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་གཏོང་བ་ལ་མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་ནས། ནམ་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སྙིང་པོ་ལ་འདུག་གི་བར་དུ་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>until he reaches the essence of enlightenment.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སེར་སྣ་དང་ལྷན་ཅིག་མི་གནས་པ་འདི་ནི་ལྷའི་བུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་མཚམས་མེད་པ་གཉིས་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, when a bodhisattva great being, without producing, has produced the mind set on giving up all possessions, he will not entertain any feelings of miserliness</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་གཞན་ཡང་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Moreover, divine son, the third act with immediate consequence of the bodhisattva great beings is as follows.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ནམ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་བདག་གིས་རྣམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་ཡོངས་སུ་བསྐྱབ་བོ་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས་མི་སྐྱེད་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་དེ་ལྟར་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་ནས་བར་མ་དོར་མི་ནུར་བ་དེ་ནི་ལྷའི་བུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་མཚམས་མེད་པ་གསུམ་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, when a bodhisattva great being, without producing, has produced the mind-set that thinks, ‘I will protect all beings in any possible way,’ he will not yield from that.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་གཞན་ཡང་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Moreover, divine son, the fourth act with immediate consequence of the bodhisattva great beings is as follows.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་མཚམས་མེད་པ་བཞི་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, when a bodhisattva great being,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཟོད་པ་མ་ཐོབ་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>without attaining forbearance,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་རབ་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་པ། མ་བྱུང་བ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>has attained the forbearance that understands that ultimately all phenomena are utterly unborn, utterly unarisen,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དངོས་པོ་མེད་པའོ་ཞེས་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and utterly unreal,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཟོད་པ་ཐོབ་ནས་བར་དུ་རྫས་དང་། ངོ་བོ་དང་། དངོས་པོར་འཛིན་པ་ལེན་པས་མ་ཟིན་པ་འདི་ནི་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>he will not engender any clinging to substance, essence, or actuality.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་གཞན་ཡང་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Moreover, divine son, the fifth act with immediate consequence of the bodhisattva great beings is as follows.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ནམ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་སྐད་ཅིག་གཅིག་དང་ལྡན་པའི་ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱིས་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་རྣམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་བྱང་ཆུབ་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, when a bodhisattva great being, without engendering, has engendered the mind-set that thinks, ‘I will fully understand all phenomena by means of momentary knowledge,’ he will not rest under any circumstances</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཞེས་དེ་ལྟར་མ་སྐྱེས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་ནས། རྣམ་པའི་མཆོག་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་ལྡན་པའི་ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་མི་འཐོབ་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་མ་ཐོབ་ཀྱི་བར་དུ་མི་འདུག །ཀུན་ཏུ་མི་འདུག་པ་དེ་ནི་ལྷའི་བུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་མཚམས་མེད་པ་ལྔ་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>until he has obtained, without obtaining, the wisdom of omniscience that is endowed with all supreme features.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ལྟར་མི་གནས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་གནས་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་མྱུར་དུ་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་དོན་དམ་པར་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་མི་རྒྱ་བའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“By abiding in this way, without abiding, the bodhisattva great being quickly and perfectly awakens, without ultimately awakening, to unexcelled and completely perfect buddhahood.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་མཚམས་མེད་པ་གང་དག་གིས་བྱིས་པ་སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོ་རྣམས་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བར་འགྲོ་བར་འགྱུར་བའི་མཚམས་མེད་པ་དེ་ཉིད་ལ་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, those acts of immediate consequence that cause ordinary childish beings to be born in hell</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་གནས་ན་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་མི་རྒྱ་བའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱ་བར་འགྱུར་བ་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་རྣམ་གྲངས་ཡོད་དམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>are the very acts that cause a bodhisattva great being to awaken to unexcelled and completely perfect buddhahood without perfectly awakening. Is that correct?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཡོད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Yes, divine son, it is.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཤིན་ཏུ་སྟོང་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utter emptiness.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཤིན་ཏུ་སྟོང་པ་ཉིད་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, understanding this utter emptiness is awakening.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཅེས་ཇི་སྐད་དུ་བརྗོད་པ་ལྟར་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Yet, ultimately, awakening is not the way that it is expressed through words.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་མཚན་མ་མེད་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utter signlessness.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་མཚན་མ་མེད་པ་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, understanding this utter signlessness is awakening.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཅེས་ཇི་སྐད་དུ་བརྗོད་པ་ལྟར་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Yet, ultimately, awakening is not the way that it is expressed through words.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཤིན་ཏུ་སྨོན་པ་མེད་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utter wishlessness.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་སྨོན་པ་མེད་པ་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, understanding this utter wishlessness is awakening.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཅེས་ཇི་སྐད་དུ་བརྗོད་པ་ལྟར་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Yet, ultimately, awakening is not the way that it is expressed through words.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཤིན་ཏུ་གཟུང་བར་བྱ་བ་མེད་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, ultimately all phenomena do not exist as something that can be apprehended whatsoever.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཤིན་ཏུ་གཟུང་བར་བྱ་བ་མེད་པ་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, understanding this state of being beyond something to apprehend whatsoever is awakening.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཅེས་ཇི་སྐད་དུ་བརྗོད་པ་ལྟར་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Yet, ultimately, awakening is not the way that it is expressed through words.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཤིན་ཏུ་མངོན་པར་འདུ་མི་བྱེད་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utterly beyond formation.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཤིན་ཏུ་མངོན་པར་འདུ་མི་བྱེད་པའི་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, understanding this state where phenomena are utterly beyond formation is awakening.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཅེས་ཇི་སྐད་དུ་བརྗོད་པ་ལྟར་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Yet, ultimately, awakening is not the way that it is expressed through words.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཤིན་ཏུ་འདུས་མ་བྱས་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utterly unconditioned.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཤིན་ཏུ་འདུས་མ་བྱས་པ་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, understanding this utterly unconditioned state is awakening.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཅེས་ཇི་སྐད་དུ་བརྗོད་པ་ལྟར་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Yet, ultimately, awakening is not the way that it is expressed through words.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་མཐོང་བ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utterly unseen.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་མཐོང་བ་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, understanding this state of being utterly unseen is awakening.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཅེས་ཇི་སྐད་དུ་བརྗོད་པ་ལྟར་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Yet, ultimately, awakening is not the way that it is expressed through words.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utterly unborn.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་པ་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, understanding this utterly unborn state is awakening.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཅེས་ཇི་སྐད་དུ་བརྗོད་པ་ལྟར་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Yet, ultimately, awakening is not the way that it is expressed through words.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་བྱུང་བ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utterly unarisen.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་བྱུང་བ་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, understanding this utterly unarisen state is awakening.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཅེས་ཇི་སྐད་དུ་བརྗོད་པ་ལྟར་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Yet, ultimately, awakening is not the way that it is expressed through words.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཤིན་ཏུ་དངོས་པོ་མེད་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utterly unreal.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཤིན་ཏུ་དངོས་པོ་མེད་པ་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, understanding this state of being utterly unreal is awakening.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཅེས་ཇི་སྐད་དུ་བརྗོད་པ་ལྟར་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Yet, ultimately, awakening is not the way that it is expressed through words.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god then asked,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ལ་སུ་དད་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, who will have faith in this Dharma teaching?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ལ་ཡང་དད་པས་མི་འགྲོ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, since ultimately even the Thus-gone One does not have faith,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གང་ཉན་ཐོས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དང་། མུ་སྟེགས་ཅན་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལྟ་ཅི་སྨོས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>forget about the hearers, solitary buddhas, and all the extremists who rely on reference points.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god asked him,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སུ་དག་མོས་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Who will gain conviction in it?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གང་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་གང་ལ་ཡང་མངོན་པར་མི་ཆགས་པ་དེ་མོས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Those who ultimately are not attached to any phenomenon will gain conviction.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god asked him,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཡང་སུ་དག་ནན་ཏན་བྱེད་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Who will apply it earnestly?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གང་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་གང་ལ་ཡང་ནན་ཏན་མི་བྱེད་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Those who ultimately do not earnestly apply themselves to any phenomenon.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god asked him,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སུ་དག་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱ་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Who will become realized?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གང་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་གང་ཡང་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་མི་རྒྱའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Those who ultimately do not realize any phenomenon.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god asked him,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་སུ་དག་ཆོས་གང་ཡང་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་མི་རྒྱ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, who are those who ultimately do not realize any phenomenon?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī answered,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་རྣམ་པའི་མཆོག་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱ་བ་དག་གོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, those who, on the relative level, realize the omniscient wisdom that is endowed with the supreme of all aspects.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་དག་ཇི་ལྟ་བུའི་རང་བཞིན་དུ་འགྱུར།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, what kind of nature do they have?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་དེ་དག་རབ་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་པའི་རང་བཞིན་དུ་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, ultimately they have the utterly unborn nature.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god asked him,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་མདོ་སྡེ་འདི་ལྟ་བུ་སུ་དག་གི་ལག་ཏུ་འགྲོ །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, in whose hands will a sūtra such as this end up?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་གང་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་དམ་པའི་ཆོས་ཀྱི་ལག་སྦྱིན་པར་བྱེད་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, relatively, in the hands of those who offer the sacred Dharma to all beings.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་དག་ཇི་ལྟ་བུར་གནས་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, how will they abide?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས། མ་བྱུང་དངོས་པོ་མེད་པ་ལ་དེ་དག་གནས་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, ultimately they will abide in the utterly unborn, the utterly unarisen, and the utterly unreal.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god asked,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་དག་ཅིས་འགྲོ་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, in what way will they proceed?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་མ་སྐྱེས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, ultimately they will proceed within the utterly unborn,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མ་བྱུང་དངོས་པོ་མེད་པར་དེ་དག་འགྲོ་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the utterly unarisen, and the utterly unreal.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཕྱིར་མི་ལྡོག་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོས་ཅི་བྱང་ཆུབ་འཐོབ་བམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, how will the irreversible bodhisattva great being attain awakening?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་གང་ཕྱིར་མི་ལྡོག་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དེས་བྱང་ཆུབ་མི་འཐོབ་པ་ནི་གནས་མ་ཡིན་ཏེ། གོ་སྐབས་མེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, whoever is an irreversible bodhisattva great being has no chance and no opportunity not to attain awakening.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ཅི་ལས་ལྡོག་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, what do the bodhisattva great beings turn back from?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལས་ལྡོག་གོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, ultimately, bodhisattva great beings turn back from thoughts.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཉན་ཐོས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་། མུ་སྟེགས་ཅན་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་གྱི་ས་ལས་ལྡོག་གོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They turn back from the levels of all the hearers, solitary buddhas, and the extremists who rely on reference points.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ཅི་ལས་མི་ལྡོག །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, what does a bodhisattva great being not turn back from?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ནི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བའི་མཉམ་པ་ཉིད་ལས་མི་ལྡོག་གོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, bodhisattva great beings do not turn back from all phenomena being the same in being utterly unarisen.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>If you wonder why,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བར་མཉམ་པའི་ཕྱིར་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དག་མཉམ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>it is because ultimately all phenomena are the same in being utterly unarisen, and the bodhisattva great beings are the same.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་བས་ན་ཕྱིར་མི་ལྡོག་གོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>That is why they do not turn back.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god asked,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བར་མཉམ་པ་ཉིད་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་དེ་འཇམ་དཔལ་ཆོས་གང་གི་ཚིག་བླ་དགས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“When one speaks of the sameness of all phenomena in being utterly unarisen, Mañjuśrī, what phenomenon is that a designation for?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བར་མཉམ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ནི་ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་སྣ་ཚོགས་མེད་པའི་ཚིག་བླ་དགས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“The sameness of all phenomena in being utterly unarisen designates that ultimately there is no diversity.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བར་མཉམ་པ་ལ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་སྣ་ཚོགས་སུ་སྣང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, how does the sameness of all phenomena in being utterly unarisen manifest as diversity?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གང་ལྷའི་བུ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བར་མཉམ་པ་ལ་དོན་དམ་པར་རྫས་དང་། དངོས་པོ་དང་། ངོ་བོར་ཡོངས་སུ་རྟོག་པས་དེ་དག་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་སྣ་ཚོགས་སུ་སྤྱོད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, whoever conceptualizes the sameness of all phenomena in being utterly unarisen as ultimately having substance, materiality, and essence will ultimately experience diversity.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་དག་དོན་དམ་པར་སྣ་ཚོགས་སུ་སྤྱོད་པ་ལ་དམིགས་པའི་ལྟ་བ་མང་དུ་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>As for ultimately experiencing diversity, it develops into many views involving reference points.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་དག་དམིགས་པའི་ལྟ་བ་མང་པོས་འགྲོ་བ་རྣམ་པ་ཐ་དད་པ་རྣམས་སུ་དབང་མེད་པར་འཁྱམ་མོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Those who hold these many views that involve reference points wander helplessly in all the various forms of existence.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གང་ལྷའི་བུ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བར་མཉམ་པ་ལ་དོན་དམ་པར་ངོ་བོ་དང་། རྫས་དང་། དངོས་པོ་ཡོངས་སུ་མི་རྟོག་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, whoever does not conceptualize the sameness of all phenomena in not occurring as ultimately having substance, materiality, and essence,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་དག་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་སྣ་ཚོགས་སུ་མི་སྤྱོད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>does ultimately not experience diversity.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་དག་དོན་དམ་པར་སྣ་ཚོགས་སུ་མི་སྤྱོད་ན། དོན་དམ་པར་ཤིན་ཏུ་དངོས་པོ་མེད་པར་འགྲོ་བའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་དོན་དམ་པར་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་པའི་མཚན་ཉིད་དང་མཉམ་པར་ཁོང་དུ་ཆུད་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Since he ultimately does not experience diversity, he ultimately understands the utterly unreal. In this way he comes to understand that all phenomena ultimately are the same in being characterized as utterly unborn.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god asked,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རྣམ་གྲངས་གང་གིས་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་དང་བཅས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཡོད་ཀྱི་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་མེད་པ་ལ་མ་ཡིན་པའི་རྣམ་གྲངས་ཡོད་དམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, is there a method that can awaken a bodhisattva great being with disturbing emotions, but not someone without disturbing emotions?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཡོད་དོ། ། དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, there is.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་འབྱུང་བ་ཡང་འབྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, relatively, all phenomena continuously emerge</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མི་འབྱུང་ཡང་མི་འབྱུང་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and disappear.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱང་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་འབྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>In this way, the awakening of bodhisattva great beings also appears, relatively.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་མེད་ཅིང་མི་སྐྱེ་མི་འགག་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, ultimately, all phenomena are without disturbing emotions, unborn and unceasing.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཆོས་གང་དོན་དམ་པར་མི་སྐྱེ་མི་འགག་པ་དེ་དོན་དམ་པར་གང་གིས་ཀྱང་མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་སངས་མ་རྒྱས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Any phenomenon that is ultimately unborn and unceasing is also ultimately beyond being realized.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་རྒྱ་བར་མི་འགྱུར་རོ། །མངོན་པར་རྫོགས་པར་འཚང་མི་རྒྱའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>It will never be realized, nor was it ever realized.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, because ultimately all phenomena are utterly unborn.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་རྣམ་གྲངས་དེ་ལྟ་བུས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་དང་བཅས་པ་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་འབྱུང་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Therefore, divine son, through such a method a bodhisattva great being with disturbing emotions can awaken,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཉོན་མོངས་པ་མེད་པ་ལ་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>yet someone who is devoid of disturbing emotions cannot.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་རྣམ་གྲངས་གང་གིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་སེར་སྣ་ཅན་ལ་སྦྱིན་པའི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, is there a method by which a bodhisattva great being who is miserly can complete the perfection of generosity,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གཏོང་བ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ལ་མ་ཡིན་པའི་རྣམ་གྲངས་ཡོད་དམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>yet those who are generous cannot?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཡོད་དེ་ལྷའི་བུ་རྣམ་གྲངས་གང་གིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་སེར་སྣ་ཅན་གྱི་སྦྱིན་པའི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པར་འགྱུར་གྱི་གཏོང་བ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ལ་མ་ཡིན་པའི་རྣམ་གྲངས་ཡོད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Yes, divine son, there is a method by which a miserly bodhisattva great being can complete the perfection of generosity, yet those who are generous cannot.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གང་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ཡོངས་སུ་མི་གཏོང་མི་འདོར་བ་དེ་ནི་ལྷའི་བུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་སེར་སྣའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Because to never let go of, or cast away, any sentient being, or any of the buddha qualities, on the relative level, is the miserliness of the bodhisattva great beings.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ངན་པའི་ངང་ཚུལ་ཅན་ལ་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ཀྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པར་འགྱུར་གྱི་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དང་ལྡན་པ་ལ་མ་ཡིན་པའི་རྣམ་གྲངས་ཡོད་དམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, is there a method by which a bodhisattva great being who is ill behaved can complete the perfection of discipline, yet those who are disciplined cannot?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཡོད་དེ་ལྷའི་བུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་གང་སེམས་ཅན་ཡོངས་སུ་སྨིན་པར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་སེམས་ཅན་ལ་ལྟའི་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ལ་མ་ཡིན་པ་དེ་ནི་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“There is. Divine son, when a bodhisattva great being avoids superficial discipline in order to ripen beings,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ཀྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>that is the perfection of discipline of a bodhisattva great being on the relative level.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོས་གང་བཟོད་པ་བོར་ལ་བཟོད་པ་ཅན་གྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་ཡོད་དམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, is there a method of patience for a bodhisattva great being who has forsaken patience?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཡོད་དེ་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, there is.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་གང་ལ་ལ་དོན་དམ་པར་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་རྫས་དང་དངོས་པོ་དང་། ངོ་བོར་མི་བཟོད་པ་དེ་ནི་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Any bodhisattva great being who ultimately has no patience with any phenomena having substance, actuality, or essence is</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྨྲས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བླ་ན་མེད་པའི་བཟོད་པ་དང་ལྡན་པར་འགྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>in fact, in an ineffable manner, in possession of the supreme patience.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་ནི་མི་དམིགས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་བཟོད་པ་དམ་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, in a manner free from reference points, that is the supreme patience of a bodhisattva great being.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ལེ་ལོ་ཅན་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་དང་ལྡན་པར་འགྱུར་བའི་རྣམ་གྲངས་ཡོད་དམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, is there a method by which a lazy bodhisattva great being can be diligent?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ་ལྷའི་བུ་ཡོད་དེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ལེ་ལོ་ཅན་དུ་གྱུར་པ་ནི་བླའི་ཉན་ཐོས་དང་རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དང་། མུ་སྟེགས་ཅན་དམིགས་པའི་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་ཀྱིས་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་དང་ལྡན་པ་ནི་དེ་ལྟ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, there is. A lazy bodhisattva great being is unlike those diligent hearers, solitary buddhas, and extremists who employ an easy form of diligence that involves focus.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་བརྗེད་ངས་པ་གང་མཉམ་པར་གཞག་པར་འགྱུར་བའི་རྣམ་གྲངས་ཡོད་དམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, is there a method by which a bodhisattva great being who is forgetful can rest in equipoise?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཡོད་དེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, there is.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་གང་ལ་ལ་རྨི་ལམ་དུ་ཡང་དོན་དམ་པར་རྫས་དང་། ངོ་བོ་དང་། དངོས་པོའི་སེམས་མི་སྐྱེ་བ་དེ་ནི་མི་དམིགས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་ཤིན་ཏུ་མཉམ་པར་གཞག་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>A bodhisattva great being, who, even in his sleep, does not give rise to thoughts of substance, essence, or actuality on the ultimate level, is resting in equipoise in a manner devoid of reference points.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་གང་ཤེས་རབ་མེད་པ། ཤེས་རབ་ཆེན་པོར་འགྱུར་བའི་རྣམ་གྲངས་ཡོད་དམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, is there a method by which a bodhisattva great being who has no knowledge can come to possess great knowledge?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཡོད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, there is.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱིས་རྣམ་པར་དཔྱད་དེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are discerned by knowledge.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཙལ་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་མེད་ཅིང་མི་དམིགས་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>However, when one searches for phenomena, they disappear and cannot be observed.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤེས་རབ་དེ་ཡང་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་མེད་ཅིང་མི་དམིགས་པས་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Knowledge is also like that; ultimately it also does not exist and cannot be observed.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་ཤེས་རབ་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱ་སྟེ། ཤེས་རབ་དེ་ཡང་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་པ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Therefore, relatively, one speaks of ‘possessing knowledge,’ even though that knowledge is ultimately utterly unborn.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་རྣམ་གྲངས་དེས་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, according to that method,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ཤེས་རབ་མེད་པ་ནི་ཤེས་རབ་ཆེན་པོ་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>a bodhisattva great being who has no knowledge is called one who possesses great knowledge,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤེས་རབ་བྱེ་བྲག་ཏུ་འཕགས་པ་ཞེས་བྱའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>or one who possesses especially exalted knowledge,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤེས་རབ་དམ་པ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཞེས་བྱའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>or one who possesses sacred knowledge,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤེས་རབ་གྱ་ནོམ་པ་ཞེས་བྱའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>or one who lays hold of knowledge,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མི་དམིགས་པའི་ཤེས་རབ་ཅན་ཞེས་བྱ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>or one who possesses knowledge devoid of a focus.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཇི་སྐད་དུ་བརྗོད་པ་ལྟར་ནི་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, things are not as they are described.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One now addressed Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལ་ལེགས་སོ། །ཞེས་བྱ་བ་བྱིན་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Excellent!” he said.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལེགས་སོ། །ལེགས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Excellent, excellent!</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་བྱ་བ་དང་། མི་བྱ་བ་མི་བསྟན་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བསྟན་པ་ནི། ཚིག་འདི་ལེགས་པར་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī, you have spoken well and explained, without explaining, the acts and non-acts of bodhisattva great beings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་སྐྱེས་བུ་བཀྲེས་པ་ལྟོགས་པས་ཉམ་ཆུང་བ་མནགས་པ་བླའི། མི་ཤེས་པས་ཁ་ཟས་དུག་ཅན་ཟོས་པ་དེ་ལྟ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī, for a starving person, feeble and thin, it is better to suffer, and thus not to unknowingly eat poisonous food.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་མི་དམིགས་པའི་སེར་སྣ་ཅན་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>In the same way, Mañjuśrī, it is better for bodhisattva great beings to engage in nonconceptual miserliness,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ངན་པའི་ངང་ཚུལ་ཅན་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>bad behavior,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གནོད་སེམས་ཅན་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>ill will,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལེ་ལོ་ཅན་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>laziness,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བརྗེད་ངས་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>forgetfulness,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤེས་རབ་མེད་པ་བླའི་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and lack of knowledge,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཉན་ཐོས་དང་རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་གྱི་སེམས་ཀྱི་སྦྱིན་པ་དང་། ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དང་། བཟོད་པ་དང་། བརྩོན་འགྲུས་དང་། བསམ་གཏན་དང་། ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱི་སྦྱོར་བ་ནི་དེ་ལྟ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and thus not engage in the conceptual applications of generosity, discipline, patience, diligence, concentration, and knowledge of the hearers and solitary buddhas who rely on reference points.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དམིགས་པའི་དུག་གི་སྐྱོན་ཆགས་པའི་ཕྱིར་དེ་ལ་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་འཇིགས་པར་ཤེས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Because the latter give rise to the faults of poisonous reference points, and this must therefore be understood to be a danger on the relative level.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ལྷའི་བུ་མཚམས་བཟངས་ཀྱིས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>At this point the god Excellent Rule asked the Blessed One,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོས་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་རྣམས་ལ་འཇིགས་པར་མི་བགྱིའམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, are bodhisattva great beings not afraid of disturbing emotions?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོས་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་རྣམས་ལ་འཇིགས་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, relatively, bodhisattva great beings do fear disturbing emotions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་བས་ཀྱང་དེས་ཉན་ཐོས་དང་རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་གྱི་སེམས་ལ་ཤིན་ཏུ་འཇིགས་པར་བྱ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>But far more, they fear the mind-set of the hearers and solitary buddhas, who rely on reference points;</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཉོན་མོངས་པ་རྣམས་ལ་ནི་དེ་ལྟ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>their fear of the disturbing emotions is not comparable.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་གསོལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god asked,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་ཅིའི་སླད་ནས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, why is that?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One answered,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་ཁྱོད་ཉིད་ལ་དྲིས་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཅི་ནུས་པ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ལུང་སྟོན་ཅིག །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, that is something you should ask yourself! Why not explain it yourself, as best you can?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་འདི་ཡིད་ལ་ཇི་སྙམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Divine son, what do you think?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྐྱེས་བུ་འཚོ་བར་འདོད་པར་གྱུར་པས་ཡན་ལག་གཅད་པ་ལ་འཇིགས་པར་བྱའམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>If a person wishes to survive, would that person’s greatest fear be having his limbs severed,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོན་ཏེ་མགོ་གཅད་པ་ལ་རབ་ཏུ་འཇིགས་པར་བྱ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>or having his head cut off?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་གསོལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཡན་ལག་གཅད་པའི་སྐྱེས་བུ་ནི་འཚོ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, someone who loses his limbs could still survive.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བསོད་ནམས་འདོད་པ་བསོད་ནམས་ཀྱི་ལམ་ཡང་དག་པར་བླངས་ཤིང་གནས་པ་དེ་ནི་མཐོ་རིས་སུ་སྐྱེ་བའི་རྒྱུར་འགྱུར་གྱི།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Thus, if he wanted to acquire merit, he could still take up and follow a meritorious path, which in turn would become a cause for taking birth in the higher realms.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མགོ་བཅད་པ་ནི་འཚོ་བ་ལས་ཡོངས་སུ་ཉམས་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>However, Blessed One, someone who had his head cut off would be unable to survive.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བསོད་ནམས་འཚལ་བ་བསོད་ནམས་ཀྱི་ལམ་ཡང་དག་པར་ལེན་ཅིང་སྤྱོད་མི་ནུས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>In this way, even if he strove for merit, he would be unable to genuinely follow a meritorious path.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞིན་ཏེ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་མི་དམིགས་པ་ནི་སྤྱོད་པ་ཉམས་ཀྱང་བླའི།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, similarly, for bodhisattva great beings it is better to conduct themselves without reference points, even if it involves transgression,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཉན་ཐོས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་གྱི་ལྟ་བར་ལྟུང་བ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བསླབ་པ་དང་། སྦྱངས་པའི་ཡོན་ཏན་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་ལྡན་པ་ནི་དེ་ལྟ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and thus not have the qualities and trainings of those who fall into the views of the hearers and solitary buddhas who rely on reference points.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་སེར་སྣ་ཅན་ནི་བླའི།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>It is better to be a miserly bodhisattva,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོངས་སུ་བཏང་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and thus not abandon all sentient beings,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་འདོར་བ་ནི་དེ་ལྟ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>or even cast away all the qualities of a buddha.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ངན་པའི་ངང་ཚུལ་ཅན་དུ་གྱུར་པ་ནི་བླའི།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>It is better to be an ill-behaved bodhisattva great being</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོངས་སུ་སྨིན་པར་མི་བྱེད་པར་གྱུར་པ་ནི་དེ་ལྟ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>rather than someone who fails to ripen others.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དད་པས་སྤྱོད་པའི་ས་ལ་སྤྱོད་པ། མི་དམིགས་པ་ལ་མོས་ཤིང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>It is better to be a bodhisattva great being who faithfully practices on the level of action with conviction in the absence of focus,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཉོན་མོངས་པ་དང་བཅས་པ་བླའི།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>yet has disturbing emotions,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཉན་ཐོས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་ངེས་པར་གྱུར་པ་ཐོབ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>than to be a hearer or solitary buddha who relies on reference points,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཉོན་མོངས་པ་མེད་པ་ནི་དེ་ལྟ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>who attains certainty and is free from disturbing emotions.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུས་གསོལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The god said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་མི་སྤྱོད་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་སྤྱོད་པ་ནི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་མི་འཐུན་པ་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, the acts of the bodhisattva great beings, which are non-acts, are at odds with the entire world.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དམིགས་པའི་དུག་གི་སྐྱོན་ཆགས་པས་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Blessed One, when the poisonous faults of reference points have formed,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གང་ཉན་ཐོས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དེ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ངན་པའི་ངང་ཚུལ་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the discipline of the hearers and solitary buddhas, who rely on reference points, becomes an unwholesome state for bodhisattva great beings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཇི་ཙམ་དུ་གང་ཉན་ཐོས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་དེ་ནི་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>No matter how diligent the hearers and solitary buddhas, who rely on reference points, are, the poisonous faults of reference points have been formed,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དམིགས་པའི་དུག་གི་སྐྱོན་ཆགས་པའི་ཕྱིར་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་ལེ་ལོའི་བར་དུའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and thus their diligence is inferior to the laziness of bodhisattva great beings.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་གང་མི་དབུལ་པོའི་ཁ་ཟས་དེ་ནི་འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བའི་རྒྱལ་པོའི་དུག་གོ། །ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་གང་ཉན་ཐོས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་དང་། བརྩོན་འགྲུས་ཀྱི་བར་དུ་དེ་དག་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོའི་ངན་པའི་ངང་ཚུལ་དང་ལེ་ལོའི་བར་དུའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, just as the food of a destitute man is poison for a universal monarch, likewise, divine son, are the discipline and diligence of the hearers and solitary buddhas, who rely on reference points, for ill-behaved and lazy bodhisattva great beings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དམིགས་པའི་དུག་གི་སྐྱོན་ཆགས་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Because of involving the poisonous faults of reference points.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་གང་བདག་ཉིད་བསྒྲུབས་པའི་ལས་བྱེད་པའི་སྐྱེས་བུའི་ནོར་དེས་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་གྱི་སྐྱེ་བོ་ཐམས་ཅད་བདེ་བར་སྦྱོར་མི་ནུས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, just as the wealth of a person who is only concerned with his personal achievements is not sufficient to ensure the wellbeing of a whole city,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་གང་ཉན་ཐོས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་དབུལ་བའི་སེམས་དང་། དམན་པའི་སེམས་དང་། དམིགས་པའི་སེམས་དང་ལྡན་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་ཀྱི་བར་གྱིས་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་གི་སེམས་ཅན་ཡོངས་སུ་ཐར་བར་བྱེད་ཀྱང་མི་ནུས་ན་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལྟ་ཅི་སྨོས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>likewise, divine son, the diligence of those who have the impoverished, inferior, and conceptual attitude of the hearers and solitary buddhas is unable to liberate even the beings here in Jambudvīpa, let alone liberate all beings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་ནོར་ཆེན་པོ་ལོངས་སྤྱོད་ཆེན་པོ་གཏོང་བ་དང་ལྡན་པ། བྱམས་པ་ལ་གནས་པ། སྙིང་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོ་དང་ལྡན་པ་དེད་དཔོན་ཆེན་པོ་ནི།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Divine son, just as a leader who lovingly and compassionately</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་བླ་ན་མེད་པའི་བདེ་བར་བྱེད་པ་ལ་ཞུགས་པའི་ནོར་དེས་གྲངས་མེད་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་པའི་སེམས་ཅན་བདེ་བར་བྱེད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>grants great wealth and enjoyment to others may use his wealth to accomplish the happiness of limitless beings in order to give all beings unsurpassed happiness,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བུ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་གང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ལྷག་པའི་བསམ་པ་ལ་ཞུགས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>so likewise, divine son, whoever develops the superior attitude of the bodhisattva great beings</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་ཤེས་རབ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and inspires all beings with knowledge,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཐབས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>means,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྙིང་བརྩེ་བ་ཆེན་པོས་བསྐུལ་བ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>great love,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བསྐལ་པ་ཆེན་པོ་བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་གྲངས་མེད་པར་བསོད་ནམས་དང་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཀྱི་ཚོགས་བསགས་པའི་ནོར་ཆེན་པོ་མི་དམིགས་པའི་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་ཀྱི་བར་དུ་དེ་དག་གིས་སེམས་ཅན་གྲངས་མེད།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and compassion will ripen limitless beings through his diligence beyond focus and the great wealth of the accumulations of merit and wisdom, gathered over limitless trillions of great eons.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་པ་ཡོངས་སུ་སྨིན་པར་བྱེད་དོ། །མི་གཞོག་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་རྣམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པ་ཉིད་ལའང་རབ་ཏུ་འགོད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Without settling them, he will even settle all beings in omniscience.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་འོད་སྲུང་ཆེན་པོས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Venerable Mahākāśyapa now addressed the Blessed One.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱིས་འདུས་མ་བྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་རྣམས་མངོན་སུམ་དུ་བགྱིས་ལ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One,” he said, “the hearers actualize all unconditioned phenomena while,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ནི་འདུས་བྱས་སུ་གཏོགས་པ་ལགས་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Blessed One, bodhisattva great beings are classified under conditioned phenomena.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཇི་ལྟར་འདུས་མ་བྱས་སུ་གཏོགས་པའི་ཉན་ཐོས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཟིལ་གྱིས་གནོན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>How can that outshine all the hearers and solitary buddhas who rely on reference points, who are included under the unconditioned?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One answered him,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོད་སྲུང་དེའི་དོན་རབ་ཏུ་གྲུབ་པར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་དཔེར་བྱ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Kāśyapa, I will give you an analogy that illustrates this.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྐྱེས་བུ་མཁས་པས་སྨྲས་པའི་དོན་རིག་པ་ལ་ལ་དཔེས་དེའི་དོན་གོ་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Some people need an analogy to understand the meaning expressed by a skilled being.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་རྒྱ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོ་བཞི་མར་གྱིས་གང་བར་གྱུར་ལ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>It is like this: imagine that the four great oceans were filled with butter.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་སྐྱེས་བུ་ལ་ལས་སྐྲ་བརྒྱར་གཤེགས་པའི་རྩེ་མོའི་ཐོག་མས་མར་གྱི་ཐིགས་པ་གཅིག་བླངས་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Then, imagine that someone were to extract a drop of butter from the oceans using the very tip of a hair split into one hundredths.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོད་སྲུང་འདི་ཇི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Do you think, Kāśyapa,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྐྲར་བརྒྱར་གཤེགས་པའི་རྩེ་མོའི་ཐོག་མས་མར་གྱི་ཐིགས་པ་བཅུས་པས་རྒྱ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོ་བཞི་མར་གྱིས་གང་བ་ཟིལ་གྱིས་གནོན་པར་ནུས་སམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>that the drop of butter extracted with that very tip of a hair split into one hundredths would be able to outshine the four great oceans filled with butter?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོད་སྲུང་གིས་གསོལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Kāśyapa replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་མ་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“No, Blessed One, they would not.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ་དེ་མ་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Blissful One, they would not.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One asked,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཡང་འོད་སྲུང་དེ་དག་ལས་ཆེས་མང་བ་དང་། ཆེས་མཆོག་ཏུ་གྱུར་པ་དང་། ཆེས་དམ་པ་དང་། ཆེས་རིན་ཆེ་བ་གང་ཡིན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Moreover, Kāśyapa, which one among the two would be largest, best, foremost, and most valuable?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོད་སྲུང་གིས་གསོལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Kāśyapa replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འདི་ལྟར་རྒྱ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོ་གཅིག་གི་བྱེ་བ་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་གི་ཆ་ཤས་དེའང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, even one trillionth of a single ocean would be,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཤིན་ཏུ་མང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Blessed One, much larger,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤིན་ཏུ་མཆོག །ཤིན་ཏུ་དམ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>better, exalted,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤིན་ཏུ་རིན་ཆེ་བ་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and valuable than the single drop.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བརྒྱར་གཤེགས་པའི་སྐྲའི་རྩེ་མོའི་ཐོག་མས་མར་གྱི་ཐིགས་པ་བླངས་པ་དེ་ལྟ་མ་ལགས་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Blessed One, the drop that was extracted using that very tip of a hair split into one hundredths could not compare to that,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྒྱ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོ་བཞི་ལྟ་ཅི་སྨོས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>let alone all four great oceans.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།དཔེར་ན་བརྒྱར་གཤེགས་པའི་སྐྲའི་རྩེ་མོའི་ཐོག་མས་མར་གྱི་ཐིགས་པ་བླངས་པ་ཚད་ཡོད་པ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཉན་ཐོས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་གྱི་འདུས་མ་བྱས་ཀྱི་ཡེ་ཤེས་ནི་ཆུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“In the same way as in this analogy, the unconditioned wisdom of the hearers and solitary buddhas, who rely on reference points, is as insignificant as the drop of butter that was extracted from that very tip of a hair split into one hundredths,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དམིགས་པ་དང་བཅས་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>since it involves reference points.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོད་སྲུང་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་རྒྱ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོ་བཞི་མར་གྱིས་གང་བ་དེ་ཙམ་དུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དམིགས་པ་མེད་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Kāśyapa, the bodhisattva great beings are similar to the four great oceans filled with butter in this analogy. They are free from reference points.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དད་པ་སྤྱོད་པའི་ས་ལ་མི་སྤྱོད་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་སྤྱོད་པའི་རྣམ་པའི་མཆོག་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་ལྡན་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They are endowed with all supreme features of engaging, without engaging, the level of faithful practice.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བསོད་ནམས་དང་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཀྱི་ཚོགས་ཐམས་ཅད་བསྡུས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They embody all the accumulations of merit and wisdom.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདུས་བྱས་ཀྱི་ཡེ་ཤེས་སུ་མི་བལྟ་བའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བལྟའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Without viewing, they view conditioned wisdom.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཡང་དོན་དམ་པའི་མེ་འབར་བས་ཡོངས་སུ་སྨིན་པར་བྱས་པས་རྣམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་མཆོག་དང་ལྡན་པའི་ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་སུ་མི་དམིགས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Moreover, through the blazing fire of the ultimate, they ripen beings and thereby transform them, without relying on reference points, into the omniscient wisdom that is endowed with all supreme aspects.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོད་སྲུང་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ཡང་འདུས་མ་བྱས་ཐོབ་པའི་ཉན་ཐོས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་མི་དམིགས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་ཟིལ་གྱིས་གནོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Kāśyapa, this is how the bodhisattva great beings, without relying on reference points, outshine the hearers and solitary buddhas who rely on reference points and who have attained the unconditioned.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོད་སྲུང་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཆེན་པོར་ཆུད་པའི་མཆིང་བུའི་ནོར་བུ་ཁུར་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་གྱུར་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Kāśyapa, as another analogy, imagine a city that contains hundreds of thousands of semiprecious trinkets.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རྒྱ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོའི་ནང་ན་ཡོད་པ་གྲུར་བཅུག་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>At the same time, there is a boat on the ocean that easily and effortlessly brings to land precious and valuable gemstones of beryl.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རིན་ཆེ་བའི་བཻ་དཱུརྱ་ནོར་བུ་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་བདེ་ཞིང་ཉེ་ཞོ་མེད་པར་འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་དུ་ཕྱིན་ན་དེ་ཇི་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས། གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཆེན་པོར་ཆུད་པའི་མཆིང་བུའི་ནོར་བུས་གྲུའི་ནང་དུ་བཅུག་པ་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་བཻ་དཱུརྱ་ནོར་བུ་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ཟིལ་གྱིས་ནོན་པར་ནུས་སམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Now, what do you think: could the semiprecious stones found in the city outshine the precious gemstones of beryl?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོད་སྲུང་གིས་གསོལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Kāśyapa replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་མ་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, it could not.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ་དེ་མ་ལགས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Blissful One, it could not.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོད་སྲུང་ཇི་ལྟར་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཆེན་པོར་ཆུད་པའི་མཆིང་བུའི་ནོར་བུ་བཞིན་དུ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Kāśyapa, just like the semiprecious trinkets found in the city,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདུས་མ་བྱས་ཐོབ་པའི་ཉན་ཐོས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་བལྟའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>so should you view the hearers and solitary buddhas who rely on reference points and their attainment of the unconditioned.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོད་སྲུང་ཇི་ལྟར་ནོར་བུ་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ཆེན་པོའི་བཻ་དཱུརྱ་རྒྱ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོའི་ནང་ན་ཡོད་པ་གྲུར་བཅུག་པ་བདེ་ཞིང་ཉེ་ཞོ་མེད་པར་ཚོང་ཁང་གི་བར་དུ་འོངས་པར་གྱུར་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Kāśyapa, just like the most valuable gemstones of beryl, which are first discovered in the ocean, then boarded on to the ship, and easily and effortlessly arrive at the trading house,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོད་སྲུང་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་འཁོར་བའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར་གྱི་ཚོང་ཁང་གི་བར་དུ་འོངས་ན་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་བླ་ན་མེད་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཏུ་མི་འཇོག་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་རབ་ཏུ་འགོད་པར་བལྟའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>so, Kāśyapa, should you view the bodhisattva great beings who arrive at the trading houses in the city of cyclic existence and, without establishing anyone, establish all beings in unsurpassed and perfectly complete awakening.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོད་སྲུང་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Kāśyapa, consider a further analogy.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དཔེར་ན་དཔྱིད་ཟླ་ཐ་ཆུངས་ཀྱི་ཟླ་བ་ལ་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>During the third month of spring,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ས་ཆེན་པོ་ལོ་ཏོག་གིས་རབ་ཏུ་གང་བ་ལ་གྲོག་སྦུར་ཕྲ་མོས་ཟས་ཀྱི་འབྲུ་གཅིག་ཁྱེར་བ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the entire land is filled with crops.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ས་ཆེན་པོ་འདི་དེ་དག་གིས་གང་བ་གཉིས་གང་མང་བར་སེམས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>If, at that time, a small insect should carry off a single grain to eat, which would be larger, that single grain or all the grains found on the entire land?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོད་སྲུང་གིས་གསོལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Kāśyapa answered,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལོ་ཏོག་གིས་གང་བའི་ས་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དཔག་ཏུ་མ་མཆིས་པའི་འབྲུའི་ཕུང་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་འབྱུང་བར་འགྱུར་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, the entire world filled with crops would have an infinitely greater pile of grains,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེས་སེམས་ཅན་གྲངས་མ་མཆིས་དཔག་ཏུ་མ་མཆིས་པ་རྣམས་ཚིམ་པར་འགྱུར་གྱི།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>which would be able to nourish uncountable, limitless beings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་གྲོག་སྦུར་ཕྲ་མོས་འཚལ་བའི་ཟས་ཀྱི་འབྲས་བུས་ལྟ་ཅི་ཞིག་བགྱི་སྟེ། དེས་སེམས་ཅན་གང་ཡང་འཚོ་བར་མི་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>At the same time, Blessed One, the single grain that the small insect carried off to eat could not even sustain a single being.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོད་སྲུང་ཇི་ལྟར་གྲོག་སྦུར་ཕྲ་མོས་ཁྱེར་བའི་ཟས་ཀྱི་འབྲུ་གཅིག་པོ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་འོད་སྲུང་ཉན་ཐོས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ཟག་པ་མེད་པའི་རྣམ་པར་གྲོལ་བའི་འབྲས་བུར་བལྟའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Kāśyapa, you should see the result that is the undefiled liberation of all hearers and solitary buddhas who rely on reference points as being just like the single grain that the small insect carried off to eat.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོད་སྲུང་ཇི་ལྟར་ལོ་ཏོག་མང་པོས་རབ་ཏུ་གང་བའི་ས་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>On the other hand, Kāśyapa, it is as being like the entire earth filled with crops that you should see,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོད་སྲུང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་མི་གནས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་ཀུན་རྫོབ་དང་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་ལ་གནས་པས། ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ་དྲུག་ལ་སོགས་པ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་། བླ་ན་མེད་པར་བསྡུས་པའི་བསོད་ནམས་དང་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཀྱི་ཚོགས་ཀྱི་དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བའི་ལོ་ཏོག་ཏུ་བལྟའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Kāśyapa, the crops of the bodhisattva great beings’ roots of virtue; they are the accumulations of merit and wisdom that in an unsurpassed manner embody the entire buddhadharma, such as the six perfections, by means of abiding, without abiding, within the relative and ultimate truths.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཡོངས་སུ་སྨིན་པར་གྱུར་ནས་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>When they have ripened,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བླ་ན་མེད་པ་རྣམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་མཆོག་དང་ལྡན་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཀྱི་བདེ་བ་མི་དམིགས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་འཚོ་བར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the bliss of the unsurpassed wisdom that is endowed with the supreme of all aspects becomes, in a manner that is beyond reference points, the sustenance of all beings.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་འོད་སྲུང་ཆེན་པོས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Venerable Mahākāśyapa exclaimed to the Blessed One,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ངོ་མཚར་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, that is amazing!</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ་ངོ་མཚར་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Blissful One, that is amazing!</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་མི་འཆད་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་ཇི་ལྟར་བཤད་པ་དེ་དེ་བཞིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>It is exactly as the Blessed One has explained, without explaining.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་ལྟར་རྣམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་མཆོག་དང་ལྡན་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Blessed One, that is how the bodhisattva great beings, by means of the unsurpassed wisdom beyond focus,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བླ་ན་མ་མཆིས་པ་མི་དམིགས་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཀྱིས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དད་པས་སྤྱོད་པའི་ས་ལ་མི་སྤྱོད་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་སྤྱོད་པས་ཉན་ཐོས་དང་། རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཟིལ་གྱིས་ནོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>which is endowed with the supreme of all aspects, engage in, without engaging in, the level of faithful practice—and thereby outshine the hearers and solitary buddhas who rely on reference points.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག་གི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ནས་འཕགས་པ་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་དང་། ལྷན་ཅིག་ཏུ་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་མི་མཇེད་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་འདིར་འོངས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དག་གིས་བསྟན་པ་འདི་ཐོས་ནས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The bodhisattva great beings from the buddha realm of the Blessed Thus-gone Ratnaketu, who had arrived here in the Sahā world together with noble Mañjuśrī,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>now addressed the Blessed One.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, it is like this.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཉན་ཐོས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The instructions of the hearers</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རང་སངས་རྒྱས་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and solitary buddhas who rely on reference points,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མོངས་པ་སྤོང་བའི་བཀའ་མཆིད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>such as the way to abandon disturbing emotions</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྟུང་བ་རྣམ་པར་གཞག་པའི་བར་གྱི་བཀའ་མཆིད་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and determine downfalls,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་སྤྲོས་པའི་བཀའ་མཆིད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>are all conceptual and specific instructions</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རྣམ་པ་ཐ་དད་པའི་བཀའ་མཆིད་དོ། །དམིགས་པའི་བཀའ་མཆིད་དེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>that involve reference points.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག་གི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ན་དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་གྱི་བཀའ་མཆིད་མ་མཆིས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“In the buddha realm of the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Ratnaketu, there are no such instructions that involve reference points.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ལྟ་བུའི་དམིགས་པ་ཅན་གྱི་བཀའ་མཆིད་མི་གདའ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Such instructions that involve focus do not exist there.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་ནི་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དག་པའི་བཀའ་མཆིད་མི་ཐོས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་ཐོས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Instead, Blessed One, the beings there listen, without listening, to the pure instructions of the bodhisattva great beings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཕྱིར་མི་ལྡོག་པའི་བཀའ་མཆིད་མི་ཐོས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་ཐོས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They listen, without listening, to the irreversible instructions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མི་དམིགས་པའི་བཀའ་མཆིད་མི་ཐོས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་ཐོས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They listen, without listening, to the instructions beyond reference points.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་པའི་བཀའ་མཆིད་མི་ཐོས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་ཐོས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They listen, without listening, to the instructions on how all phenomena are ultimately utterly unborn.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་བྱུང་བའི་བཀའ་མཆིད་མི་ཐོས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་ཐོས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They listen, without listening, to the instructions on how all phenomena are ultimately utterly unarisen.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ་ནི་ཤིན་ཏུ་དཀའ་བ་མཛད་དེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“The Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Śākyamuni underwent great hardship.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གང་འདི་སྙེད་ཀྱི་ཉམ་ང་བ་བཟོད་ཅིང་གང་ཐམས་ཅད་དོན་དམ་པར་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་པ་ལ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Having patience with so much suffering, and understanding that ultimately all phenomena are utterly unborn,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཆོས་རྣམས་རབ་འབྲིང་ཐ་མར་སྟོན་པར་མཛད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>he taught the higher, middling, and lower Dharma.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“It is like this:</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>ultimately all phenomena are utterly unborn,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མ་བྱུང་བ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>utterly unarisen,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དངོས་པོ་མ་མཆིས་པའི་རྣམ་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and utterly unreal.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་ལྟར་དོན་དམ་པར་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་རྣམ་པ་གཅིག་ལས་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དམིགས་པ་གཞོམ་པའི་སླད་དུ་མི་སྟོན་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་རྣམ་པ་དུ་མར་ཆོས་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>However, from this single identity that all phenomena share on the ultimate level, the Blessed One teaches the Dharma, without teaching, in many ways in order to accommodate the reference points of beings.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The bodhisattva great beings then began to venerate the Blessed, Thus-gone, Worthy, Perfect Buddha Śākyamuni with exquisite offerings,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་མེ་ཏོག་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>such as divine flowers,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྤོས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>fragrant herbs,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བདུག་པ་དང་། ཕྲེང་བ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>incense, flower garlands,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱུག་པ་དང་། ཕྱེ་མ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>unguents, powders,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཆོས་གོས་དང་། གདུགས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>robes, parasols,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རྒྱལ་མཚན་དང་། བ་དན་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>standards, banners,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རྣམ་པར་རྒྱལ་བའི་བ་དོན་དང་བཅས་པའི་བླ་རེས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and canopies with victory banners.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ་ལ་བླ་ན་མེད་པའི་མཆོད་པ་བྱས་ནས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They addressed Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī,” they said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་བདག་ཅག་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་འདོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“we will now proceed to Jewel World.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī told them,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་དག་ད་དེའི་དུས་ལ་བབ་པར་ཤེས་ན་དེང་ཤིག །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Children of noble family, if you know that the time has come to leave, then do so.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དག་གིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The bodhisattva great beings asked him,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཅི་ཁྱོད་ད་མི་འགྲོའམ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, are you not coming with us?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་གཅིག་གོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Children of noble family, all buddha realms are a single buddha realm.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་སངས་རྒྱས་གཅིག་གོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Likewise, all buddhas are a single buddha.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཆོས་གཅིག་གོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Likewise, all dharmas are a single dharma.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་སེམས་ཅན་གཅིག་གོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Likewise, all beings are a single being.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་དག་འདི་ལས་ཁྱད་པར་ཅི་ཡོད་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Since there are no differences between these,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་བདག་དེར་འགྲོ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>children of noble family, I will also go there.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་པ་དང་། བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དག་གིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The bodhisattva great beings asked,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཇི་ལྟར་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ཐམས་ཅད་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་གཅིག །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Mañjuśrī, in what way are all of the buddha realms a single buddha realm?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཇི་ལྟར་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་སངས་རྒྱས་གཅིག །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī, in what way are all buddhas a single buddha?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཇི་ལྟར་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཆོས་གཅིག །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī, in what way are all dharmas are a single dharma?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་ཇི་ལྟར་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་སེམས་ཅན་གཅིག །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī, in what way are all beings a single being?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གྱིས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī answered,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་དག་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཞིང་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Children of noble family, none of the buddha realms are realms.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Because ultimately they are utterly unborn.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་དག་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་སངས་རྒྱས་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Children of noble family, none of the buddhas are buddhas.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་བྱུང་བའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Because ultimately they are utterly unarisen.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་དག་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་ཆོས་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Children of noble family, none of the dharmas are dharmas.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་དངོས་པོ་མེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Because ultimately they are utterly unreal.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་དག་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ནི་སེམས་ཅན་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Children of noble family, no beings are beings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཤིན་ཏུ་ཀུན་ནས་མ་བྱུང་བའི་ཕྱིར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Because ultimately they are all utterly and entirely unarisen.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་དེའི་ཚེ་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་ཅི་ནས་སྟོང་གསུམ་གྱི་སྟོང་ཆེན་པོའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་འདི་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག་གི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དེ་ཅི་འདྲ་བ་དེ་འདྲ་བར་ལྷག་ཆད་མེད་པར་སྣང་བ་དེ་ལྟ་བུར་བསམ་པ་རབ་ཏུ་རྫོགས་ནས་དེ་འདྲ་བར་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>With these words, Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta caused this trichiliocosm to appear precisely, without any difference, like the Jewel World of the Blessed, Thus-gone Ratnaketu.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དག་གིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག་དེ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>As he had thus fulfilled his intention, he rested evenly in absorption. Then the bodhisattva great beings also saw the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་དེའང་མཐོང་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>perfect Buddha Ratnaketu and the Jewel World.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དག་འདི་སྙམ་དུ་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་ཕྱིན་པར་སེམས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>In fact the bodhisattva great beings all thought that they had arrived in the Jewel World.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་དག་གིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ་ཡང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག་གི་ཁ་དོག་དང་དབྱིབས་ཅི་འདྲ་བ་བཞིན་དུ་མཐོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Looking at the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Śākyamuni, they saw him in the precise colors and shape of the Blessed, Thus-gone Ratnaketu.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཉན་ཐོས་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དག་ཀྱང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ཡིན་སྙམ་དུ་སེམས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Even the great hearers thought that they had become bodhisattva great beings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དག་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ་ལ་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག་ཡིན་སྙམ་པ་བྱེད་ནས་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The bodhisattva great beings, who thought that they were beholding Ratnaketu,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>asked the Blessed,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ཅག་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཞེས་བགྱི་བ་འདིར་སུས་ཕྱིན་པར་བགྱིས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Thus-gone Śākyamuni, “Blessed One, who has brought us to this Jewel World?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed Śākyamuni asked them,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་དག་ཁྱེད་སུས་ཁྲིད།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Children of noble family, who has led you?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དག་གིས་གསོལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The bodhisattva great beings replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་བདག་ཅག་ཁྲིད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta led us.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed Śākyamuni said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་ཁྱེད་ནི་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་མ་འོངས་མ་སོང་བའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་ཕྱིན་པར་བྱས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Children of noble family, Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta has brought you here without coming and going.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དག་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་སྨྲས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta told the bodhisattva great beings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་དག་ཁྱེད་གང་དུ་ཁྲིད། གང་ནས་ཁྲིད་པར་བྱས་པ་མཉམ་པར་ཞོག་ལ་ལྟོས་ཤིག །དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དག་གིས་རང་རང་གི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་མཉམ་པར་གཞག་སྟེ་བལྟས་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Children of noble family, to find out where you are being led to, and from where you are being led, look with your equipoise!”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་མི་མཇེད་དེ་ཉིད་ནས་བདག་ཉིད་གང་དུ་ཡང་མ་གཡོས་པར་མཐོང་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>When the bodhisattva great beings each looked through their meditative absorption, they saw that they had never moved from this Sahā world.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ངོ་མཚར་དུ་གྱུར་རྨད་དུ་གྱུར་ནས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Amazed,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ལྟར་བདག་ཅག་སྟན་འདི་ཉིད་ལས་མ་འཕགས་པར་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་ཡང་ཕྱིན་པ་སྙམ་བྱེད་དེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>they were full of astonishment and exclaimed, “Although we never got up from our seats, we thought that we had traveled to the Jewel World.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པའི་བྱིན་གྱི་རླབས་མེད་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བྱིན་གྱི་རླབས་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་པོ་ཞེས་ཆེད་དུ་བརྗོད་པ་ཆེད་དུ་བརྗོད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>But it was Mañjuśrī who caused it all by means of his inconceivable blessing without blessing!”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་དག་གིས་ཡང་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They then added,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་ཀྱང་མི་དམིགས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བྱིན་གྱི་རླབས་འདི་ཐོབ་པར་གྱུར་ཅིག །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, may all beings also attain this blessing in a manner beyond reference point!”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དག་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Then the Blessed Śākyamuni spoke to the bodhisattva great beings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་དག་འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ། དཔེར་ན་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Children of noble family, consider this analogy.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ནི་སའི་སྣོད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Space contains the earth,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤིང་གི་སྣོད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and also wood,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཁར་བའི་སྣོད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>zinc,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཟངས་ཀྱི་སྣོད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>copper,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དངུལ་གྱི་སྣོད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>silver,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གསེར་གྱི་སྣོད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>gold,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ནོར་བུ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>as well gems,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མུ་ཏིག་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>pearls,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཻ་དཱུརྱ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>beryl,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དུང་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>conch,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མན་ཤེལ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>crystal,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱི་རུ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>coral,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཨ་མྲ་གར་བ་དང་། སྤུག་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The list also includes one type of stone cat’s eye,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དུང་གཡས་ཕྱོགས་སུ་འཁྱིལ་བ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>conch shells that coil to the right,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མུ་ཏིག་དམར་པོའི་སྣོད་ལ་སོགས་པའི་ནང་དུ་ཞུགས་པར་གྱུར་པ་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and red pearls, so that all these are contained within space.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་དག་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཏུ་སྣོད་ལ་ཐ་དད་པ་ཡོད་མོད་ཀྱི་ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་ཐ་དད་ཡོད་པ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Yet at the same time, children of noble family, although relatively there are of course different items contained, space itself remains undifferentiated.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ནམ་མཁའ་ཤིན་ཏུ་དངོས་པོ་མེད་པའི་ཕྱིར་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Because ultimately space is utterly unreal.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་བཞིན་དུ་རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་དག་དོན་དམ་པར་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Likewise, children of noble family, ultimately all phenomena are surely utterly unborn,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མ་བྱུང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>utterly unarisen,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དངོས་པོ་མེད་མོད་ཀྱི།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and utterly unreal.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཀྱི་ཐ་སྙད་ཀྱིས་ཐ་སྙད་དུ་འདོགས་ཤིང་རབ་ཏུ་འཇོག་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And yet, through the relative conventions of the world, they are imputed and designated in a conventional manner:</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་གཟུགས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>‘This is form,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་ཚོར་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>this is feeling,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་འདུ་ཤེས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>this is perception,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་དག་ནི་འདུ་བྱེད་རྣམས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>this is formation,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་རྣམ་པར་ཤེས་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>this is consciousness.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་དག་ནི་སྐྱེ་མཆེད་རྣམས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>These are the sense fields.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་དག་ནི་ཁམས་རྣམས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>These are the elements.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་སངས་རྒྱས་དཀོན་མཆོག་གོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This is the Jewel of the Buddha.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་ཆོས་དཀོན་མཆོག་གོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This is the Jewel of the Dharma.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་དགེ་འདུན་དཀོན་མཆོག་གོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This is the Jewel of the Saṅgha.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་ཉན་ཐོས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This is the vehicle of the hearers.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་རང་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཐེག་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This is the vehicle of the solitary buddhas.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་བླ་ན་མེད་པའི་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This is the unexcelled vehicle.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་དག་ནི་དགེ་བ་བཅུའི་ལས་ཀྱི་ལམ་རྣམས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>These are the paths of the ten virtuous actions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་དག་ནི་མི་དགེ་བ་བཅུའི་ལས་ཀྱི་ལམ་རྣམས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>These are the paths of the ten nonvirtuous actions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་དག་ནི་སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>These are hell beings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་དག་ནི་དུད་འགྲོའི་སྐྱེ་གནས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>These are the animal existences.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་དག་ནི་ཡི་དགས་ཀྱི་ཡུལ་ལོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>These are the abodes of the hungry spirits.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་དག་ནི་ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་ནོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>These are demigods.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་དག་ནི་མིའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>These are humans.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་དག་ནི་ལྷའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>These are gods.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་དག་ནི་འདོད་པ་ན་སྤྱོད་པའི་ལྷའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>These are gods who experience desire.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་དག་ནི་གཟུགས་ན་སྤྱོད་པའི་ལྷའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>These are gods who experience form.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་དག་ནི་གཟུགས་མེད་པ་ན་སྤྱོད་པའི་ལྷའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>These are gods who experience the formless.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་འདོད་པའི་ཁམས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This is the desire realm.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་གཟུགས་ཀྱི་ཁམས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This is the form realm.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་གཟུགས་མེད་པའི་ཁམས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This is the formless realm.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་ལུས་ཀྱིས་ལེགས་པར་སྤྱོད་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>These are good physical actions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་ངག་གིས་ལེགས་པར་སྤྱོད་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>These are good verbal actions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་ཡིད་ཀྱིས་ལེགས་པར་སྤྱོད་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>These are good mental actions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་སྦྱིན་པའི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This is the perfection of generosity.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ཀྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This is the perfection of discipline.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་བཟོད་པའི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This is the perfection of patience.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་ཀྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This is the perfection of diligence.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་བསམ་གཏན་གྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This is the perfection of concentration.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This is the perfection of knowledge.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་ཐབས་ཀྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This is the perfection of skillful means.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་སྨོན་ལམ་གྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This is the perfection of aspirations.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་སྟོབས་ཀྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This is the perfection of strength.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཀྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This is the perfection of wisdom.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ནི་ས་བཅུ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>These are the ten levels,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དབང་བཅུ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the ten powers,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའི་སྟོབས་བཅུ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the ten strengths of the bodhisattvas,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་སྟོབས་བཅུ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the ten strengths of the thus-gone ones,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མི་འཇིགས་པ་བཞི་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the fourfold fearlessness,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སོ་སོ་ཡང་དག་པར་རིག་པ་བཞི་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the four genuine discriminations,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དབང་པོ་ལྔ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the five faculties,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྟོབས་ལྔ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the five power‌s,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཇི་ཙམ་དུ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་མ་འདྲེས་པ་བཅོ་བརྒྱད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the eighteen unique qualities of a buddha,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཇི་ཙམ་དུ་རྣམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་མཆོག་དང་ལྡན་པའི་ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the omniscient wisdom that is endowed with the supreme of all aspects,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཇི་ཙམ་དུ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་བྱང་ཆུབ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the awakening of a buddha,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཇི་ཙམ་དུ་དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>suchness,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the limit of reality,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྟོང་པ་ཉིད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>emptiness,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མཚན་མ་མེད་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>signlessness,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྨོན་པ་མེད་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>wishlessness,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མངོན་པར་འདུས་མ་བྱས་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the unconditioned,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཇི་ཙམ་དུ་འདུས་བྱས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>all conditioned</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདུས་མ་བྱས་པའི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and unconditioned phenomena,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཇི་ཙམ་དུ་འཁོར་བ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>saṃsāra</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདའ་བ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and nirvāṇa,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཇི་ཙམ་དུ་སྨྲ་བ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>all speech</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྨྲ་བར་བྱ་བ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and objects of speech,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤེས་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>consciousness and objects of consciousness.’</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤེས་བྱར་ཐ་སྙད་འདོགས་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“In this way, as conventions are designated and connected,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འབྲེལ་པར་འཇུག་པ་དེ་ཙམ་དུ་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཀྱི་ཐ་སྙད་འཇུག་གོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the relative conventions of the world are applied.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པར་ན་སྤྱོད་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་མེད་པར་གྱུར་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ultimately, however, all experiences are nonexistent.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ཞེ་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>And why?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་དོན་དམ་པར་ན་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཤིན་ཏུ་མ་སྐྱེས་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Children of noble family, ultimately all phenomena are utterly unborn,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མ་བྱུང་བ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>utterly unarisen,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དངོས་པོ་མེད་པའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and utterly unreal.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དག་ཤིན་ཏུ་ངོ་མཚར་དུ་གྱུར་ནས་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The bodhisattva great beings were amazed.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྟན་ལས་ལངས་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They rose from their seats</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ་ལ་ཡང་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྒྱ་ཆེ་བ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and performed a very elaborate</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཤིན་ཏུ་ཁྱད་པར་དང་ལྡན་པའི་མཆོད་པ་བྱས་ནས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and unique worship of the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Śākyamuni.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་ཞབས་ལ་མགོ་བོས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They bowed down their heads to the feet of the Blessed One</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཚིག་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་འདི་ལྟ་བུའི་སེང་གེའི་སྒྲ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, a lion’s roar,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱེ་བྲག་ཏུ་འཕགས་པའི་སྒྲ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>an especially exalted sound,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཁྱུ་མཆོག་གི་སྒྲ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the sound of the supreme leader,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྐྱེས་བུ་ཆེན་པོའི་སྒྲ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the sound of a great being,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཡང་དག་པའི་སྒྲ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>a sound of the genuine,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཁོ་ནའི་སྒྲ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the sound of thatness,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མི་དམིགས་པའི་སྒྲ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>a sound beyond reference point,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པའི་སྒྲ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the sound of the ultimate.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མི་དམིགས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་འབྱིན་པར་གྱུར་ཅིག །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>in a manner beyond reference point, please emit your sound to all beings:</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དག་དགའ་མགུ་རངས་ནས་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Those bodhisattva great beings happily</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ་ལ་ལན་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མར་བསྐོར་བ་བྱས་ནས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and joyfully circumambulated the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Śākyamuni several hundred thousand times before</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་གན་ནས་སླར་དོང་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>finally departing from the presence of the Blessed One.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་དག་ཕྱོགས་བཅུར་སོང་ནས་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Proceeding into the ten directions,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མི་དམིགས་པའི་བརྩོན་འགྲུས་ཀྱི་གོ་ཆ་ཆེན་པོ་གོ་ཆ་མེད་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བགོས་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>they donned, in the manner of having no armor, the great armor of diligence beyond reference point.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ནས་དོན་དམ་པ་དང་། ཀུན་རྫོབ་ཀྱི་བདེན་པ་གཉིས་ལ་གནས་པའི་ཆོས་བསྟན་པ་འདི་ཉིད་མི་སྟོན་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>In this way they taught, without teaching, this Dharma teaching, which abides within both the ultimate and the relative truths.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཆོས་འདུལ་བ་འདི་ཉིད་ལ་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་འདུལ་ཞིང་སྟོན་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>They taught this very Dharma-vinaya to tame all beings and,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མི་འཇོག་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་རབ་ཏུ་འགོད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>without establishing, they established these beings in the teaching.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་སྟན་དེ་ལ་འདུག་སྟེ་མ་ལངས་པར་འདི་འདྲ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་མཉམ་པར་བཞག་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta did not get up, but remained on his seat, resting evenly in absorption.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པའི་གཙུག་ཏོར་གྱི་གསེབ་སྤྱི་བོའི་གཙུག་ནས་སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་དམིགས་པ་དང་། མི་ཤེས་པ་སེལ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་འོད་ཟེར་བྱུང་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>By means of his absorption, a light known as eradicating the reference points and ignorance of all beings shone forth above his head from his crown protuberance.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་བྱུང་ནས་ཕྱོགས་བཅུའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་ཐམས་ཅད་དུ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་རབ་འབྱམ་ཐམས་ཅད་སྣང་བར་བྱས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>As the light appeared, it illuminated all the infinite buddha realms within all the worlds in the ten directions.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འོད་ཟེར་སྣང་བ་དེས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པས་ཆོས་བཤད་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The light rays caused the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Śākyamuni to teach the Dharma</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་རྫོབ་དང་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་གཉིས་ལ་བརྟེན་པ་མི་ཐོས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་ཐོས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>so that the teaching on relying on both the relative and ultimate truth was heard, without being heard.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ལྟར་ཕྱོགས་བཅུ་མཐའ་ཡས་མུ་མེད་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་ཐམས་ཅད་ན་བཞུགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>In order to pay homage to all the buddhas and the bodhisattva great beings in all the infinite and limitless worlds in the ten directions,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ཐམས་ཅད་ལ་མཆོད་པ་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་འོད་ཟེར་གྱི་སྣང་བ་དེ་ལས་ལྷའི་མེ་ཏོག་གི་ཆར་འབེབས་པའི་སྤྲིན་བྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the light produced clouds that rained down divine flowers,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བདུག་པའི་ཆར་འབེབས་པའི་སྤྲིན་བྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>clouds that rained down divine fragrant herbs,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་སྤོས་ཀྱི་ཆར་འབེབས་པའི་སྤྲིན་བྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>clouds that rained down divine incense,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་ཕྲེང་བའི་ཆར་འབེབས་པའི་སྤྲིན་བྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>clouds that rained down divine garlands,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བྱུག་པའི་ཆར་འབེབས་པའི་སྤྲིན་བྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>clouds that rained down divine unguents,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་ཕྱེ་མའི་ཆར་འབེབས་པའི་སྤྲིན་བྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>clouds that rained down divine powders,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་གོས་ཀྱི་ཆར་འབེབས་པའི་སྤྲིན་བྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>clouds that rained down divine garments,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་གདུགས་ཀྱི་ཆར་འབེབས་པའི་སྤྲིན་བྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>clouds that rained down divine parasols,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་རྒྱལ་མཚན་གྱི་ཆར་འབེབས་པའི་སྤྲིན་བྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>clouds that rained down divine standards,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བ་དན་གྱི་ཆར་འབེབས་པའི་སྤྲིན་བྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>clouds that rained down divine banners,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་རྣམ་པར་རྒྱལ་བའི་བ་དན་གྱི་ཆར་འབེབས་པའི་སྤྲིན་བྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>clouds that rained down divine victory banners,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་བླ་རེའི་ཆར་འབེབས་པའི་སྤྲིན་གྱི་བར་དུ་བྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>clouds that rained down divine canopies.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷའི་མེ་ཏོག་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>There were clouds that rained down divine flowers,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བདུག་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>fragrant herbs,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སྤོས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>incense,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཕྲེང་བ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>garlands,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱུག་པ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>unguents,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཕྱེ་མ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>powders,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཆོས་གོས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>garments,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>གདུགས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>parasols,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རྒྱལ་མཚན་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>standards,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བ་དན་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>banners,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རྣམ་པར་རྒྱལ་བའི་བ་དན་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>victory banners,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བླ་རེའི་ཆར་འབེབས་པའི་སྤྲིན་བྱུང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and canopies.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རྣམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་མཆོག་དང་ལྡན་པ། བླ་ན་མེད་པའི་བདེ་བ་ཆེན་པོ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་པའི་ལྷའི་མེ་ཏོག་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Thus they sent forth clouds that rained down divine flowers,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བདུག་པ་དང་། སྤོས་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>fragrant herbs, incense,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཕྲེང་བ་དང་། བྱུག་པ་དང་། ཕྱེ་མ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>garlands, unguents, powders,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཆོས་གོས་དང་། གདུགས་དང་། རྒྱལ་མཚན་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>garments, parasols, standards,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བ་དན་དང་། རྣམ་པར་རྒྱལ་བའི་བ་དན་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>banners, victory banners,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བླ་རེའི་ཆར་གྱི་སྤྲིན་རབ་ཏུ་གཏོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and canopies that were all of the finest quality and produced all forms of unexcelled exuberance.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ལས་ལངས་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Now Mañjuśrī Kumārabhuta emerged from his absorption.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལངས་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ་ལ་ལན་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་དུ་མར་མི་དམིགས་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བསྐོར་བ་བྱས་ནས་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>In a manner beyond reference points, he circumambulated the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Śākyamuni several hundred thousand times before</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་མི་མཇེད་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་འདི་ནས་སླར་སོང་ངོ་། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>he departed from this Sahā world.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One now told Venerable Ānanda,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་སངས་རྒྱས་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་འབྱུང་གནས་འདི་ཟུང་ཤིག །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Ānanda, you should uphold</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རྒྱས་པར་གྱིས་ཤིག །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and propagate this Dharma teaching, which is the source of all buddhas and bodhisattva great beings.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Venerable Ānanda answered the Blessed One,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་བདག་གིས་གཟུང་བ་ནི་ལགས་ན།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, I can indeed uphold this teaching,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རྒྱས་པར་བགྱིད་ནི་མི་ནུས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>but I would be unable to propagate it.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཅིའི་སླད་དུ་ཞེ་ན། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དོན་དམ་པར་དམིགས་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་ཞེན་པའི་སེམས་ཅན་ཤིན་ཏུ་མང་སྟེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The reason, Blessed One, is that ultimately there are so many beings who cling to reference points;</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རྫས་ལ་མངོན་པར་ཞེན་པ་ནས་དངོས་པོའི་བར་ལ་མངོན་པར་ཞེན་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>they also cling to physical matter,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལོག་པར་འཛིན་པ་དེ་ལས་དབྱེ་བ་ཤིན་ཏུ་དཀའོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and they cling to substance, and it is extremely difficult to break them away from this mistaken grasping.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་པ་དང་། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One said to Venerable Ānanda,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ནི་འདས་པ་དང་། མ་འོངས་པ་དང་། ད་ལྟར་གྱི་སངས་རྒྱས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱིས་བྱིན་གྱིས་མི་རློབ་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་སོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Ānanda, all the blessed buddhas in the past, present, and future have blessed, without blessing, this Dharma teaching.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་ཁྱོད་རྐྱེན་ཙམ་གྱིས་ཤིག །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ānanda, you only need to act as a mere circumstance.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་དགའ་བོས་གསོལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Venerable Ānanda asked him,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>རིགས་ཀྱི་བུའམ། རིགས་ཀྱི་བུ་མོ་གང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ཆུང་ངུ་ན་ཉན་པར་འགྱུར་བ་དེ་དག་ཅི་འདྲ་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>what happens if a son or daughter of noble family should hear just a little of this teaching?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One replied,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ལས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པས་ཡང་དག་པར་བསྟན་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Ānanda, it is based on this Dharma teaching that the Thus-gone One genuinely teaches,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ཁོ་ན་བསྟན་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>shows reality,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མི་དམིགས་པ་བསྟན་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>shows the absence of reference points,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དོན་དམ་པ་བསྟན་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>shows the ultimate,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>མི་སྟོན་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་བསྟན་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and teaches without teaching.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བསྟན་པ་དེ་ཡང་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This teaching is inconceivable</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་དེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and limitless.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་དེ་བཞིན་དུ་གང་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ལས་ཆུང་ངུ་ན་ཡི་གེ་འབྲུ་གཅིག་ཙམ་ཡང་མི་ཉན་པའི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་མཉན་ན་</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Ānanda, whoever hears, without hearing, a little of this Dharma teaching, even if it is just a single syllable,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་ཐམས་ཅད་བསམ་གྱིས་མི་ཁྱབ་ཅིང་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་པར་འགྱུར་རོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>will encounter all the inconceivable and limitless teachings of the Buddha.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Then Venerable Ānanda asked the Blessed One,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདིའི་མིང་ཅི་ལགས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Blessed One, what is the name of this Dharma teaching?</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འདི་ཇི་ལྟར་གཟུང་བར་བགྱི།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>How should one apprehend it?”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>The Blessed One said,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་དེའི་ཕྱིར་ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས་འདི་ཀུན་རྫོབ་དང་། དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་བསྟན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བར་ཟུང་ཤིག །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>“Ānanda, you should know this Dharma teaching as Teaching the Relative and Ultimate Truths.”</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ནས།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>When the Blessed One had spoken,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དག་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the bodhisattva great beings,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཉན་ཐོས་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་དག་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>the great hearers,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ཚེ་དང་ལྡན་པ་ཀུན་དགའ་བོ་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>Venerable Ānanda,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཁོར་དེ་དག་ཐམས་ཅད་དང་།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and the entire retinue,</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>ལྷ་དང་། མི་དང་། ལྷ་མ་ཡིན་དང་། དྲི་ཟར་བཅས་པའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་ཡི་རངས་ཏེ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>as well as the world with all its gods, humans, demigods, and gandharvas, rejoiced</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཤད་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་བསྟོད་དོ། །</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>and praised the Blessed One’s teachings.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
<tu>
<tuv xml:lang="BO">
<seg>འཕགས་པ་ཀུན་རྫོབ་དང་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་བསྟན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ་རྫོགས་སོ།</seg>
</tuv>
<tuv xml:lang="EN">
<seg>This completes the Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra, Teaching the Relative and Ultimate Truths.</seg>
</tuv>
</tu>
</body>
</tmx>