<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tmx xmlns="http://www.lisa.org/tmx14">
    <header creationtool="84000-translation-memory" creationtoolversion="1.0.0.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="phrase" adminlang="en" srclang="bo" o-tmf="TEI" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:19:33.676Z" creationid="S.J."/>
    <body>
        <tu tuid="1">
            <prop name="folio">f.158.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:19:33.676Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དཔལ་ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་གོས་སྔོན་པོ་ཅན་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ། །སངས་རྒྱས་དང་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་དུས་གསུམ་དུ་བཞུགས་པ་རྣམས་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ལོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:19:33.676Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>I prostrate to the Blue-Clad Blessed Vajrapāṇi! I prostrate to the buddhas and bodhisattvas of the three times!</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="2">
            <prop name="folio">f.158.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">113</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:20:40.777Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།འདི་སྐད་བདག་གིས་ཐོས་པ་དུས་གཅིག་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:20:40.777Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Thus have I heard at one time.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="3">
            <prop name="folio">f.158.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">144</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:23:12.27Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མི་བསྐྱོད་པ་རྡོ་རྗེའི་རིགས་ཀྱི་སངས་རྒྱས་ལྕང་ལོ་ཅན་གྱི་ཕོ་བྲང་ན་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་དང་། རྡོ་རྗེ་སྡེ་དང་། རྡོ་རྗེ་ཀུན་ཏུ་འཛིན་པ་དང་། །རྡོ་རྗེ་རབ་ཏུ་འདུལ་བྱེད་དང་། །རྡོ་རྗེ་མི་བཟད་འཇོམས་དང་། རྡོ་རྗེ་གདུག་པ་ཀུན་འདུལ་དང་། རྡོ་རྗེ་དབྱིངས་ལས་རྒྱལ་བ་དང་། རྡོ་རྗེ་དགྱེས་གནས་སྐྱོབ་ལ་སོགས་པའི་འཁོར་བྱེ་བ་ཕྲག་སྙེད་རྣམས་དང་ཐབས་ཅིག་ཏུ་བཞུགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:23:12.27Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Blessed Akṣobhya, the buddha of the vajra family, was residing in the palace in Alakāvatī together with a retinue of millions of bodhisattvas, including Vajrapāṇi, Vajra Regiment, Constant Vajra Holder, Vajra Tamer, Terrible Vajra Conqueror, Vajra Tamer of All Evil, Vajra Victor of Basic Space, Vajra Joyfully Abiding Protector, and others.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="4">
            <prop name="folio">f.158.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">374</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:23:54.324Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ལག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཐུགས་ཀར་ལན་གསུམ་གསོར་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:23:54.324Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>At that time, the great being, the bodhisattva Vajrapāṇi himself, brandished a vajra three times at his heart center.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="5">
            <prop name="folio">f.158.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">492</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:24:57.055Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་བསྐོར་བ་ལན་གསུམ་བྱས་ནས་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ། པུས་མོ་གཡས་པའི་ལྷ་ངས་ལ་བཙུགས་ཏེ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:24:57.055Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>He made three circumambulations of the Blessed One and prostrated himself. Then, kneeling on his right knee, Vajrapāṇi requested,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="6">
            <prop name="folio">f.158.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">622</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:26:16.09Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཛིན་པ་ཆེན་པོ་འབྱུང་པོ་ཀུན་འདུལ་བར་བྱེད་ཅིང་། ས་འོག་གི་གདུག་པ་ཅན་འདུལ་བར་བྱེད་པའི་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཀུན་འདུལ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་རྒྱུད་ཆེན་པོ་བཤད་དུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:26:16.09Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Blessed One, Thus-Gone One, Great Vajra Holder, please explain the great tantra called The All-Subjugating Vajra that subjugates all bhūtas and that tames the evil ones that dwell beneath the earth.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="7">
            <prop name="folio">f.158.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">822</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:28:09.712Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་འཛིན་པ་ཆེན་པོ་བཤད་དུ་གསོལ་ཁྱབ་བདག་ཆེན་པོ་བཤད་དུ་གསོལ། གདུག་པ་ཀུན་འདུལ་བར་བྱེད་པ་ཆེན་པོས་བཤད་དུ་གསོལ། མུན་པ་ཀུན་འཇོམས་པ་ཆེན་པོ་བཤད་དུ་གསོལ་ཞེས་</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:28:09.712Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Great Vajra Holder, I supplicate you to teach! Great Lord of All, I supplicate you to teach! Great Tamer of All Evil Forces, I supplicate you to teach! Great Dispeller of All Darkness, I supplicate you to teach!”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="8">
            <prop name="folio">f.158.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1035</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:29:23.065Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེས་གསོལ་བ་བཏབ་བོ། །དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་པ་དང་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་ལ་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:29:23.065Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>At this request from Vajrapāṇi, the Blessed One declared,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="9">
            <prop name="folio">f.158.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1093</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:31:42.898Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>རྡོ་རྗེ་འཆང་ཆེན་པོ་གསང་བ་པ་ཁྱོད་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དོན་དུ་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཀུན་འདུལ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་རྒྱུ་དང་ལ་ཞུ་བ་ལེགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:31:42.898Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“It is excellent that you, Great Vajradhara, Secret One, have, for the benefit of sentient beings, requested from me the tantra called The All-Subjugating Vajra.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="10">
            <prop name="folio">f.158.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1255</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:32:10.235Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གསང་བ་པའི་བདག་པོ་ལེགས་སོ། །བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ལེགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:32:10.235Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Lord of Secrets, that is excellent! Great Bodhisattva, that is excellent!</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="11">
            <prop name="folio">f.158.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1329</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:33:29.588Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེའི་ཕྱིར་ལག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེའི་རིགས་རྣམས་ཁྱེད་རྗེས་སུ་ཉོན་ལ་ཡིད་ལ་ཟུང་ཤིག</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:33:29.588Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Thus, you who share Vajrapāṇi’s lineage, listen and remember this!</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="12">
            <prop name="folio">f.158.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1396</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:34:15.761Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ངས་རྣམ་པར་ཕྱེ་སྟེ་རྡོ་རྗེ་ས་འོག་འབྱུང་པོ་འདུལ་བ་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་རྒྱུད་བཤད་ཀྱིས་རྗེས་སུ་ཟུང་ཤིག</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:34:15.761Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>I will reveal and explain the tantra called The Vajra that Subjugates the Evil Forces Below the Vajra Earth. Receive it!”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="13">
            <prop name="folio">f.158.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1518</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:35:04.139Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:35:04.139Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>After pronouncing these words,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="14">
            <prop name="folio">f.158.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1549</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:36:19.042Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཀུན་འདུལ་གྱི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་གྱིས་</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:36:19.042Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>the Blessed One, by means of the absorption of the all-subjugating vajra,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="15">
            <prop name="folio">f.158.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1623</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:36:59.235Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ས་འོག་གི་གདོན་དང་། འབྱུང་པོ་ཀུན་འཇོམས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:36:59.235Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>entered equipoise in the absorption called vanquishing all grahas and bhūtas from below the earth.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="16">
            <prop name="folio">f.158.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1722</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:40:08.469Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་དེ་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་མ་ཐག་ཏུ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་སྐུའི་བ་སྤུའི་བུ་ག་ཐམས་ཅད་ནས་ཁྲོ་བོ་གདུག་པ་ཀུན་འདུལ་བར་བྱེད་པ་དུ་མ་སྤྲོས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:40:08.469Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>No sooner had the Blessed One entered equipoise than a multitude of wrathful subjugators of evil forces emanated from all the pores of his body and</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="17">
            <prop name="folio">f.158.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1870</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:40:44.059Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ས་འོག་ས་སྟེངས་ས་བླ་གསུམ་གང་བར་མཛད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:40:44.059Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>filled the space under the earth, on the earth, and above the earth.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="18">
            <prop name="folio">f.158.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1939</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:41:51.74Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ས་འོག་གི་ཀླུ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་གནས་རྣམས་གདུག་པའི་ཧཱུཾ་སྒྲས་ཀུན་ཏུ་གང་བར་བྱས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:41:51.74Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>The entire land of the underground nāgas was filled with the horrible sound hūṃ.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="19">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">299</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:43:48.852Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་བརྒྱད་པོ་འཁོར་དང་བཅས་པ་བཏུལ་ཏེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་སྤྱན་སྔར་བཀུག་གོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:43:48.852Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>The eight nāga kings together with their retinues were tamed, and bowed before the Blessed One.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="20">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">395</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:46:04.104Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་མཐའ་ཡས་གདུག་པའི་སེམས་ལངས་ཏེ་དབུགས་ཤིན་ཏུ་ཚ་བར་གཏོང་བར་སེམས་པ་</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:46:04.104Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>But the nāga king Anantaka then gave rise to an evil thought, intending to release a scalding breath.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="21">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">497</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:48:28.058Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>དེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་མཁྱེན་ཏེ། གསང་བའི་བདག་པོ་ལག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་ལག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་ལ་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:48:28.058Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>But the Blessed One knew his intention and blessed the Lord of Secrets, Vajrapāṇi,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="22">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">580</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:48:54.512Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ཀླུ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ཞེ་སྡང་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བར་བྱེད་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་སྔགས་འདི་གསུངས་སོ། །ཨོཾ་ནཱི་ལ་བཛྲ་ཀྲོ་དྷ་ནཱ་ག་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་ཅེས་བཟླས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:48:54.512Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>who spoke this mantra called the mantra that completely pacifies the anger of all nāgas: “Oṃ nīlavajra krodhanāga hūṃ phaṭ.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="23">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">705</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:51:15.565Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ཀླུ་མཐའ་ཡས་སེམས་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་སྟེ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དང་ལྡན་པར་གྱུར་པས་ཀླུ་ཐམས་ཅད་སེམས་རབ་ཏུ་ཞིའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:51:15.565Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Now the mind of the nāga Anantaka was completely pacified; he became endowed with the awakened mind, through which the minds of all the nāgas were completely pacified.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="24">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">873</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:52:26.955Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་མཐའ་ཡས་ལ་སོགས་པའི་ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ས་འོག་ན་བཞུགས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཛིན་པ་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:52:26.955Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then all of the nāga kings like Anantaka, who live below the earth, supplicated the Blessed One, the Great Vajra Holder, with these words:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="25">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1012</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:55:01.692Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཕྱི་མའི་དུས་ན་སླད་མའི་ཚེ་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ལ་ས་འོག་གི་གདོན་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བར་དུ་མི་གཅོད་ཅིང་དེ་དག་གི་གདུག་པ་ཞི་བར་བྱེད་པའི་ཆོ་ག་བཤད་དུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-22T23:55:01.692Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Blessed One, we supplicate you to explain a ritual that will, in future times and onward, prevent the grahas that are living below the earth from making obstacles for sentient beings, and that will also pacify the evil of those spirits.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="26">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1250</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:00:28.155Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>བདག་ཅག་ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་རྣམས་དང་བདག་ཅག་གི་འཁོར་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་སེམས་ཅན་ཆེན་པོ་དེ་ལ་བར་དུ་གཅད་པར་མི་ནུས་པ་བཤད་དུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:00:28.155Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>We supplicate you to explain why we, the nāga kings and our retinues, are unable to create obstacles for that great being.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="27">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1373</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:02:50.528Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>བདག་ཅག་ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དོན་དུ་འགྱུར་བ་བཤད་དུ་གསོལ་ཞེས་གསོལ་བ་བཏབ་བོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:02:50.528Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>We supplicate you to explain to us, the nāga kings, our purpose.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="28">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1439</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:03:33.661Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཛིན་པ་ཆེན་པོས་ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་རྣམས་ལ་ཅུང་ཟད་སྤྱན་གྱིས་གཟིགས་ནས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:03:33.661Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>The Blessed One, the Great Vajra Holder, glanced at the nāga kings and replied,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="29">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1519</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:05:10.459Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་དག་ལེགས་སོ། །ཞུ་བའི་དུས་ལ་བབ་བོ། །ངས་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དོན་དུ་རབ་ཏུ་ཕྱེ་སྟེ་བཤད་ཀྱིས་ཉོན་ཅིག</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:05:10.459Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Nāga kings, that is excellent! Your request is timely. I will reveal this for the benefit of sentient beings. I will explain; listen!”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="30">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1655</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:05:54.632Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལེགས་སོ། །ཞེས་གསོལ་ཏེ་ཀླུ་ལ་སོགས་པ་རྣམས་ལྟར་ཉན་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:05:54.632Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>The nāgas and the others replied, “Excellent, Blessed One!” They then listened appropriately.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="31">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1749</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:06:37.513Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཀླུ་འདུལ་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ལེའུ་འདི་བཤད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:06:37.513Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>At that point, the Blessed One explained the following chapter called “Taming the Nāgas.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="32">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1857</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:14:43.696Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ཧཱུྃ། སེམས་ཅན་ཀུན་གྱི་དོན་གྱི་ཕྱིར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:14:43.696Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Hūṃ! For the benefit of all sentient beings,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="33">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1902</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:15:08.033Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རྡོ་རྗེ་འཛིན་ཆེན་སྟོན་པ་དེས། །ཉིད་ཀྱི་འཁོར་ལ་རབ་གཟིགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:15:08.033Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>The Teacher, the Great Vajra Holder, Carefully observed his own retinue,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="34">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1975</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:15:23.369Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།འོད་ཟེར་ཀུན་ཏུ་རབ་བཀྱེ་ནས། །གདོན་རྣམས་རླག་བྱེད་ཐབས་གསུངས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:15:23.369Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Projected light into all directions, And then taught the method for destroying all grahas:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="35">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">2066</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:15:59.172Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དཀར་པོའི་ཕྱོགས་ཀྱི་ཚེས་བརྒྱད་དང་། །དེ་བཞིན་བཅུ་བཞི་བཅྭ་ལྔ་ལ། །རབ་ཏུ་དབེན་པའི་ས་ཕྱོགས་སུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:15:59.172Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“On the eighth day of the waxing moon, Or likewise on the fourteenth and fifteenth days, In an extremely isolated place,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="36">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">2187</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:16:54.23Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་རབ་ཁྲོས་པ། །གཞོན་ཚུལ་འགྱིད་བ་རབ་བསམས་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:16:54.23Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Contemplate wrathful Vajrapāṇi, Youthful and with majestic poise.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="37">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">415</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:18:57.788Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རིན་ཆེན་སྣོད་དམ་ཁམ་ཕོར་དུ། །གསེར་ལ་སོགས་པའི་རིན་ཆེན་བདུན། །དག་པར་བསྒྲུབས་ཏེ་རབ་བཅུག་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:18:57.788Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Next, purify gold and so forth, the seven precious things, And place these in a jeweled vessel or clay pot.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="38">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">524</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:19:20.959Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གསང་སྔགས་བརྒྱ་རྩ་བརྒྱད་བཟླས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:19:20.959Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Recite 108 mantras.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="39">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">544</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:19:52.192Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དཀོན་མཆོག་གསུམ་གྱི་བཀའ་བདེན་པས། །འབྱུང་པོ་དེ་ལ་གཏོར་བྱིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:19:52.192Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Resorting to the true utterance of the Three Jewels, Give an oblation to the bhūtas.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="40">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">630</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:20:19.546Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གང་གནས་བརྟན་སར་རབ་སྦས་ལ། །འབྱུང་པོ་ཀླུ་གདུག་ཞི་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:20:19.546Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Bury it in firm ground wherever they abide, And the bhūtas and evil nāgas will be pacified.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="41">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">722</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:20:46.652Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གང་ཚེ་ཞི་བས་མ་ཕན་ན། །དེ་ཚེ་གདུག་པའི་མཚོན་ཆ་རྣམས། །རང་གི་ཁང་པར་རབ་ཏུ་འབར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:20:46.652Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“When these peaceful methods are not sufficient, With terrible weapons Set their homes ablaze.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="42">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">817</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:22:31.115Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྡུག་བསྔལ་མི་བཟད་དྲག་པོ་སྟེ། །དེ་ཚེ་སྔོན་གྱི་སེམས་དྲན་པས། །ཞི་བར་འགྱུར་བར་ཐེ་ཚོམ་མེད། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:22:31.115Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“This fierce, unbearable suffering Will remind them of their previous intentions, And they will undoubtedly be pacified.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="43">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">983</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:23:10.613Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་འདིར་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ལས་ཀྱི་ལྷའི་ཆོ་ག་རབ་ཏུ་གསུངས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:23:10.613Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then the Blessed One explained the ritual for the action deity:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="44">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1047</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:24:20.101Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>རྟག་ཏུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་ཐོབ་ཅིང་། །དམ་ཚིག་སྡོམ་པ་ཀུན་ལྡན་པ། །ཁྲུས་ཀྱི་ལས་རྣམས་ཀུན་བྱ་སྟེ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:24:20.101Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Always in possession of the awakened mind, And endowed with all commitments and vows, Engage in all of the acts of bathing.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="45">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1172</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:24:52.998Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>རྣམ་པར་དག་པའི་ས་གཞི་ལ། །དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ཇི་ལྟར་མཛེས་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:24:52.998Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“In a clean and pure place, Beautify the maṇḍala as is fitting.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="46">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1236</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:27:27.282Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ཧཱུྃ་ཡིག་ལས་བྱུང་ལྕགས་ཀྱུ་ཡིས། །སངས་རྒྱས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་རྣམས། །སྐད་ཅིག་མདུན་བསམས་མཆོད་སོགས་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:27:27.282Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Visualize an iron hook that emerges from the syllable hūṃ, Bringing the buddhas and bodhisattvas instantaneously before you. Make offerings and so forth to them.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="47">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1398</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:27:47.824Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ཨོྃཤཱུནྱ་ཏཱ་ཛྙཱ་ན་བཛྲ་སྭ་བྷཱ་བ་ཨཱ་ཏཱ་ཀོ྅ཧྃ། སྟོང་པའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་རྣམས་བསྒོམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:27:47.824Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Oṃ śūnyatā­jñāna­vajra­svabhāvātmako 'haṃ Meditate on the absorption of emptiness.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="48">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1482</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:28:26.682Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ནམ་མཁའི་ཁམས་སུ་ཨ་དང་ནི། །ཟླ་བ་དང་པོ་ཡི་གེ་ཧཱུྃ། །འོད་ཟེར་ཀུན་དུ་འབར་བར་བསྒོམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:28:26.682Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“In the expanse of space, visualize the letter āḥ, And the first moon, the letter hūṃ Blazing with great light.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="49">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1594</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:28:55.797Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>འགྲོ་དྲུག་ཉོན་མོངས་ཀུན་སྦྱངས་ཏེ། །རྣམ་གྲོལ་ས་ལ་ངེས་བཀོད་ནས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:28:55.797Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>This purifies the negative emotions of the six classes of beings, Definitively placing them in the state of complete liberation.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="50">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1723</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:29:16.855Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>འོད་བསྡུས་ཧཱུྃ་གི་རྣམ་པར་བསམ། །དེ་ཉིད་རྡོ་རྗེ་རྩེ་ལྔ་ཅན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:29:16.855Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Imagine the light gathered back in the form of hūṃ Marked with a five-pronged vajra.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="51">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1809</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:29:40.711Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>འོད་ཟེར་ཕྲེང་བ་འཕྲོ་བར་བསམ། །དེ་ཡི་འོད་ཀྱིས་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས། །རྡོ་རྗེའི་ངོ་བོར་ཐིམ་པར་བྱ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:29:40.711Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>A garland of light shines forth from this, Causing all sentient beings To dissolve into the vajra essence.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="52">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1916</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:29:59.904Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>དེ་ལས་ཁྲོ་བོ་ཆེན་པོའི་སྐུ། །སྐུ་མདོག་སྔོན་པོ་ཆེར་འབར་བ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:29:59.904Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“From this the Great Wrathful One Blue in color, blazes forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="54">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2102</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:31:14.759Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>སྐུ་མདོག་ནག་པོའི་གཟུགས་ཅན་དེ། །ཞལ་གཅིག་ཕྱག་གཉིས་རྡོ་རྗེ་བསྣམས། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:31:14.759Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“His form is dark in color, With one face and two hands, holding a vajra.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="55">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1979</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:31:29.727Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>གཡོན་བརྐྱང་ན་ཚོད་བཅུ་དྲུག་འཆང་། །མཐའ་ཡས་ལ་སོགས་བརྒྱད་ཀྱིས་བརྒྱན། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:31:29.727Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Seated with his left leg extended, he is sixteen years of age. He is adorned with eight ornaments, Anantaka, and so forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="56">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2176</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:32:22.251Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ན་བཟའ་སྔོན་པོའི་ཟེར་འཇོལ་ཅན། །སྤྱན་གསུམ་དམར་མཛེས་གྱེན་དུ་འཇིལ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:32:22.251Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>His clothing is blue and luminous, His three eyes are beautifully red and looking upward.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="57">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2266</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:32:49.249Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>རལ་བ་གྱེན་བརྫེས་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཡི། །དབུ་རྒྱན་ཅན་དུ་བསམ་པར་བྱའོ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:32:49.249Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>His dreadlocks stream upward Bound by a vajra ornament—imagine him like this.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="58">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2344</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:33:10.844Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཁྲོ་བོ་ཆེ། །སྤྱན་དྲངས་ཛཿཧཱུྃ་བྃ་ཧོཿས་གཞུག །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:33:10.844Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Then great wrathful wisdom Is invoked and ushered in with jaḥ hūṃ vaṃ hoḥ</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="59">
            <prop name="folio">f.159.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2419</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:34:40.946Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>མགོ་དང་ལྐོག་མ་སྙིང་ག་རུ། །ཨོྃ་ཨཱཿཧཱུྃ་གི་རྣམ་པ་ཡི། །ཡི་གེ་བཅུ་གསུམ་སྔགས་ཀྱིས་བརྒྱན། །འཁོར་ལོ་པདྨ་རྡོ་རྗེ་བསམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:34:40.946Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Visualize, at his head, throat, and heart center, A wheel, a lotus, and a vajra Marked by the syllables oṃ āḥ hūṃ, Ornamented with the thirteen-syllable mantra.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="60">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">163</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:36:03.96Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>མི་བསྐྱོད་རྡོ་རྗེས་དབང་བསྐུར་ཏེ། །ཀུན་འཇོམས་རྣམ་པར་དག་པར་བསམ། །</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:36:03.96Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Visualize that Akṣobhya-Vajra confers empowerment, And all is conquered and perfectly purified.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="61">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">261</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:38:13.751Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འདིའི་རྩ་བའི་སྔགས་ལས་ཐམས་ཅད་པ་གསུངས་པ། ཨོྃ་ནཱི་ལཱྃ་བ་ར་དྷ་ར་བཛྲ་པཱ་ཎི་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ། རབ་ཏུ་བརྗོད་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:38:13.751Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then the Blessed One resolutely spoke his root mantra, the statement of all activity: “Oṃ nīlāmbara­dhara­vajra­pāṇi hūṃ hūṃ phaṭ.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="62">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">392</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:39:21.913Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྔགས་ཀྱི་ཕྲེང་བ་དེ་དག་ཀྱང་། །ཞི་ལ་རབ་དཀར་དབང་ལ་དམར། །རྒྱས་ལ་སེར་པོ་དྲག་ལ་གནག</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:39:21.913Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“The garlands of mantra as well Should be white for peaceful, red for magnetizing, Yellow for increasing, and black for wrathful activity.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="63">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">531</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:40:14.291Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རྟོག་པ་ཀུན་ཏུ་སྤངས་ཏེ་བཟླས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:40:14.291Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Completely abandon thoughts and recite this.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="64">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">576</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:40:41.994Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྤྲོ་དང་བསྡུ་བའི་བྱེ་བྲག་གིས། །ཇི་ལྟར་མོས་པའི་བསམ་གཏན་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:40:41.994Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“With the distinct techniques of emanating and absorbing, Engage in concentration on whatever you wish for.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="65">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">684</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:40:55.648Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།མི་མོས་རྣལ་འབྱོར་རབ་ཏུ་སྤང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:40:55.648Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Give up the practice of what you do not desire.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="66">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">954</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:51:21.09Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དཔལ་རྡོ་རྗེས་འོག་གི་རྒྱུད་ལས་ཞི་བའི་ལས་སྒྲུབ་པ་དང་ལྷའི་ལེའུ་སྟེ་དང་པོའོ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-23T00:51:21.09Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>This was the first chapter from The Glorious Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld, “Accomplishing Peaceful Activity” or the “Chapter of the Gods.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="67">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1127</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:18:00.094Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ་ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:18:00.094Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then the great bodhisattva, the great being Vajrapāṇi, supplicated the Blessed One with these words:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="68">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1228</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:19:04.043Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་སྟོན་པ་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཛིན། །བར་ཆད་ཞི་བྱེད་གཏོར་མ་ཡི། །ཆོ་ག་མཆོག་ནི་བཤད་དུ་གསོལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:19:04.043Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Blessed One, Teacher, Vajra Holder, Please explain the supreme ritual For the oblation that pacifies obstacles.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="69">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1341</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:19:27.087Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སེམས་ཅན་དོན་དུ་བརྩོན་ལྡན་བགྱི།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:19:27.087Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Make this effort for the benefit of beings!”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="70">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1413</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:20:44.593Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ལེགས་སོ་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཆང་བ་གཙོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:20:44.593Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Excellent, principal Vajra Holder!</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="71">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1449</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:21:09.063Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བར་ཆད་ཞི་བའི་ཆོ་ག་དང་། །དངོས་གྲུབ་ཐབས་ཀྱི་ཆོ་ག་ནི། །གཏོར་མ་ཀུན་གྱི་གཏེར་འགྱུར་བཤད།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:21:09.063Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>I will explain the basis of all oblations: The ritual for pacifying obstacles, And the ritual that is a method for gaining spiritual accomplishment.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="72">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1598</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:21:36.113Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རབ་ཏུ་མཛེས་པའི་སྣོད་མཆོག་ཏུ། །བཟའ་དང་བཅའ་བ་ལ་སོགས་པའི། །ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས་པ་རབ་ཏུ་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:21:36.113Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“In a beautiful vessel, Place many excellent articles Such as food, drink, and so forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="73">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1687</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:22:11.293Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྟོང་པའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་འགྲོ་བས། །བྲུྃ་ལས་མཛེས་པའི་སྣོད་བསྐྱེད་དེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:22:11.293Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Through entering the absorption of emptiness, From bruṃ generate a beautiful vessel.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="74">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1773</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:23:18.287Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཁྃ་ལས་ཁ་ཟས་ནམ་མཁའི་ཁམས། །མཉམ་པར་བསམས་ཏེ་སྔགས་འདི་བརྗོད། །ཨོྃ་ཨ་ཀཱ་རོ་མུ་ཁྃ་སརྦྦ་དྷརྨྨཱ་ཎཱྃ་ཨཱ་དྱ་ནུ་ཏྤནྣ་ཏྭཱད་ཨོཾ་ཨཱཿཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ་</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:23:18.287Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>With kham visualize food and drink Filling all of space, and recite this mantra: Oṃ āḥkāro mukhaṃ sarva­dharmāṇām ādyanta­panna tathā oṃ āḥ hūṃ phaṭ svāhā.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="75">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1929</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:24:37.007Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བདུད་རྩིར་བསམས་ཏེ་རབ་ཏུ་སྤེལ། །སྤེལ་བ་གཉིས་ཀྱིས་རྣམ་པར་སྦྱང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:24:37.007Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Visualizing it as nectar, expand it greatly. Through two expansions, purify it.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="76">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">2010</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:24:54.934Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ནམ་མཁར་ཧྲཱིཿལས་པདྨ་བརྒྱད། །དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་པ་བསམ་བྱ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:24:54.934Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>In space, from the letter hrīḥ Visualize eight lotuses, immeasurably large.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="77">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">158</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:25:43.582Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གཙོ་བོ་མགོན་པོ་རྣམ་ཐོས་བུ། །གནོད་སྦྱིན་བྱེ་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས་བསྐོར་ཅིང་། །ཀླུ་བརྒྱད་ཀྱིས་མཆོད་སྤྱན་དྲང་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:25:43.582Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Then invite the protector Vaiśravaṇa, The central figure surrounded by a retinue of ten million yakṣas, The recipient of the offerings of the eight nāga kings.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="78">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">319</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:26:52.54Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གནོད་སྦྱིན་རྒྱལ་པོ་དེ་དག་ལ། །རྨུགས་འཛིན་གང་བ་བཟང་པོ་དང་། །ནོར་བཟངས་ཀུ་བེ་ར་དང་ནི། །ཡང་དག་འབྲོག་གནས་ལྔས་རྩེན་དང་། །པི་ཙི་ཀུཎྜ་ལི་རྣམས་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:26:52.54Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Imagine that the yakṣa kings— Jambhala and Pūrṇabhadra, Maṇibhadra, Kubera, Samprajñāna, Guhyasthāna, Pāñcika, And Bījakuṇḍalī—</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="79">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">448</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:27:11.657Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།འཁོར་གྱི་ཚུལ་གྱིས་གཙོ་ལ་བསྐོར། །ཕྱོགས་དང་མཚམས་སུ་བསམ་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:27:11.657Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Gather round the central figure like a retinue In all the main and intermediate directions.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="80">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">540</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:27:34.691Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བྱེ་བའི་འཁོར་ཚོགས་ཐུན་མོང་ཡིན། །ཀླུ་བརྒྱད་གནོད་སྦྱིན་ཕྱི་ནའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:27:34.691Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“The common retinue of ten million Are behind the eight nāgas and yakṣas.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="81">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">614</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:27:55.237Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ལྕགས་ཀྱུས་སྤྱན་དྲངས་ལ། །མ་བྲལ་གཙོ་དང་ལྕགས་ཀྱུའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:27:55.237Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Next, for the invitation, use hooks That are conjoined from the central deity.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="82">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">693</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:28:27.955Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བཞོན་པ་སེང་གེ་རྟ་ཡི་ཚོགས། །ཀུན་ཀྱང་ཞལ་གཅིག་ཕྱག་གཉིས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:28:27.955Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Imagine them on mounts of lions and horses, All with one face and two hands,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="83">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">771</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:28:58.906Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རིན་ཆེན་འབར་བའི་རྒྱལ་མཚན་དང་། །ནོར་བུ་རིན་ཆེན་བུམ་པ་དང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:28:58.906Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>With victory banners, blazing with gems And the vase of precious jewels.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="84">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">844</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:29:36.474Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རིན་ཆེན་འབར་བ་རལ་གྲི་དང་། །གྲི་མདུང་ཁང་བརྩེགས་རལ་གྲི་ཕུབ། །མཚོན་ཆ་སྣ་ཚོགས་འཕྱར་བར་བསྒོམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:29:36.474Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“They hold swords blazing with gems, Daggers and spears, celestial chariots, swords, and shields, And various weaponry raised on high; visualize them thus.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="85">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1000</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:30:28.414Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྤྱན་འདྲེན་ཚེ་ན་རྔ་སོགས་དང་། །དུང་ཆེན་འབྲས་སྤོས་དག་ནི་དབུལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:30:28.414Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“At the time of invitation, offer drum And trumpet music, fruits and incense.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="86">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1078</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:30:48.136Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ཨོྃ་བཻ་བ་ཤྲ་བ་ཎ་ས་པ་རི་བཱ་ར་ས་མཱ་ཛཿཛཿཧཱུྃ་བྃ་ཧོཿ། ཨོྃ་བཻ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་བཻ་ཤྲ་བ་ཎ་ཨཱ་ཀཪྵ་ཡ་ཧཱུྃ་ཛཿ། ཞེས་སྤྱན་དྲང་བའི་སྔགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:30:48.136Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Oṃ vaiśravaṇa saparivāra samāja jaḥ hūṃ vaṃ hoḥ Oṃ ve svāhā Oṃ vaiśravaṇa ākarṣaya hūṃ jaḥ Is the mantra for the invitation.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="87">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1204</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:31:03.723Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཨོྃྃ་ཨ་མྲྀ་ཏ་ཀུཎྜ་ལི་ཧ་ན་ཧ་ན་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ། ཅེས་པ་ནི་བགེགས་བསྐྲད་པའི་སྔགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:31:03.723Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Oṃ amṛta­kuṇḍalī hana hana hūṃ phaṭ Is the mantra for dispelling obstructors.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="88">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1283</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:31:33.688Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་མེ་ཏོག་ལ་སོགས་པས། །མཆོད་པ་དག་ནི་ནམ་མཁའ་རུ། །རབ་ཏུ་མཆོད་དེ་སྤྲོ་བར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:31:33.688Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Then with flowers and so forth, Make pure offerings in the sky, Offering them with joy.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="89">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1372</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:33:19.602Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཨོྃ་ནཱི་ལཱྃ་པ་ར་དྷ་ར་བཛྲ་པཱ་ཎི་ཨཱ་ཛྙཱ་པ་ཡ་ཏི་ཨི་མྃ་བ་ལི་གྲྀཧྞ་ཏུ། ས་མ་ཡ་རཀྵ་ནྡུ། མ་མ་སརྦྦ་སིདྡྷི་མྨེ་པྲ་ཡཙྪནྟུ་མ་མ་ཀརྨྨཱ་མོ་གྷ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་བཻ་ཤྲ་བ་ཎཱ་ཡ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་ཛམ་བྷ་ལཱ་ཡ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་པཱུརྞ་བྷ་དྲཱ་ཡ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་མ་ཎི་བྷ་དྲཱ་ཡ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་ཀུ་བཻ་རཱ་ཡ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་སྃ་པྲ་ཛྙཱ་ནཱ་ཡ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་གུ་ཧྱ་སྠཱ་ནཱ་ཡ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་པཱཉྩི་ཀཱ་ཡ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་ཙི་པི་ཀུཎྜ་ལི་ནེ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། གཏོར་མ་དབུལ་བའི་སྔགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:33:19.602Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Oṃ nīlāmbara­dhara­vajra­pāṇi ājñāpayati imaṃ baligṛhnantu Samayarakṣantu Mama sarva­siddhiṃ me prayacchantu mama karmāmogha svāhā Oṃ vaiśravaṇāyā svāhā Oṃ jambhalāya svāhā Oṃ pūrṇavhadrāya svāhā Oṃ maṇibhadrāya svāhā Oṃ kuberāya svāhā Oṃ samprajñānāya svāhā Oṃ guhyasthānāya svāhā Oṃ pāñcikāya svāhā Oṃ bījakuṇḍaline svāhā These are the mantras for offering the oblation.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="90">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1746</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:34:00.878Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་མཆོད་དེ་མགྲོན་རྣམས་བཏང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:34:00.878Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Then make that offering to the guests.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="91">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1786</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:34:46.753Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།འོད་ཟེར་ལྕགས་ཀྱུ་བཀྲོལ་ནས་སུ། །བཀྲོལ་བའི་དུས་ན་གཤེགས་དང་མཉམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:34:46.753Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Hooks of light rays shine forth, And immediately they arrive.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="92">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1848</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:35:01.871Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།མཉམ་ལངས་སྤྱོད་པའི་ཆོ་ག་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:35:01.871Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Perform the ritual of equal enjoyment.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="93">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1888</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:35:28.829Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རྡོ་རྗེས་འོག་གི་རྒྱུད་ལས་གཏོར་མའི་ལེའུ་སྟེ་གཉིས་པའོ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-24T23:35:28.829Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>This was the second chapter of The Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld, “The Oblation.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="94">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2001</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:18:49.481Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་འཇིག་རྟེན་པའི་དངོས་གྲུབ་བསྒྲུབ་པར་འདོད་པའི་དོན་དུ་</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:18:49.481Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then, for the benefit of those who wish to attain worldly accomplishment, the Blessed One</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="95">
            <prop name="folio">f.160.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2091</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:19:59.148Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་པའི་འཁོར་ལོ་ཀུན་འབྱུང་བ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ལ་སྙོམས་པར་ཞུགས་ནས་སྐུའི་བ་སྤུ་ནས་འོད་ཟེར་སྤྲོས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:19:59.148Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>entered the absorption called the origination of all worldly wheels and emanated rays of light from the pores of his body.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="96">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">214</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:20:26.128Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>རྣམ་ཐོས་སྲས་འཁོར་བཅས་ཀྱི་ཐུགས་བསྐུལ་ནས་འཁོར་དེར་འདུས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:20:26.128Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Vaiśravaṇa and his retinue were thus inspired and gathered around him.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="97">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">285</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:21:06.205Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ཏེ་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཕྱེ་མས་གཏོར་ནས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:21:06.205Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>He prostrated to the Blessed One, scattered dust made from precious gems, and made this request:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="98">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">382</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:23:46.889Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ནི་ཆོས་སྐྱོང་བའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུ་ཞེས་བགྱི་བ་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:23:46.889Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Blessed One, I am the Dharma-upholding king named Vaiśravaṇa.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="99">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">445</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:24:53.992Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>བདག་གིས་ཆོས་དང་ལྡན་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་བསྲུང་ཞིང་ཡུན་རིང་དུ་གནས་པར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་བདག་ཉིད་ཀྱིས་གསང་བ་བཤད་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:24:53.992Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>If I myself were to proclaim a secret in order to protect the Dharma of the pious and ensure that the Dharma abides for a long time,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="100">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">578</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:26:34.306Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་སྐབས་དབྱེ་བར་ཅི་གནང་ཞེས་གསོལ་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:26:34.306Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>would the Blessed One grant me an opportunity?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="101">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">648</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:28:07.157Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ་ལེགས་སོ། །རང་གི་གསང་བ་ལེགས་པར་ཤོད་ཅིག །ངས་ཀྱང་རྗེས་སུ་ཡི་རང་ཞིང་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབ་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:28:07.157Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Great King, excellent! Explain your secret well! I rejoice and give my blessings.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="102">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">731</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:28:37.289Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རྡོ་རྗེ་འཆང་བ་ཀུན་གྱིས་ཀྱང་བྱིན་གྱིས་རློབ་པར་འགྱུར་གྱིས་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ལེགས་པར་སྨྲོས་ཤིག་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:28:37.289Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>May all vajra holders also bless you. Speak well!”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="103">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">782</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:30:16.623Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུ་རང་གི་སྟན་ལས་ལངས་ཏེ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་ནས་རང་གི་རིག་པ་འདི་སྨྲས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:30:16.623Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then Vaiśravaṇa got up from his seat, prostrated to the Blessed One, and spoke his own incantation:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="104">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">882</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:30:50.991Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཨོྃ་བཻ་ཤྲ་བ་ཎཱ་ཡ་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ། པ་ཙ་པ་ཙ། ཙྪིནྡ་ཙྪིནྡ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:30:50.991Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Oṃ vaiśravaṇāya hūṃ hūṃ paca paca chinda chinda svāhā. ”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="105">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1002</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:31:24.477Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་གི་སྔགས་འདིའི་སྒྲུབ་པ་ནི་འདི་ལགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:31:24.477Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“O Blessed One, the accomplishment of this, my mantra, is excellent.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="106">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1071</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:31:48.612Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་བདག་སྒྲུབ་པར་འདོད་པ་དེས་དུས་གསུམ་དུ་མཆོད་པ་རྒྱ་ཆེན་པོ་བཤམས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:31:48.612Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Whoever wants to accomplish my state of being should arrange great offerings in the three times.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="107">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1168</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:43:55.33Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>བདག་འཁོར་དང་བཅས་པ་མཆོད་ལ་སེམས་རྩེ་གཅིག་དང་ལྡན་པས་གནས་དབེན་པར་འདུག་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:43:55.33Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>To make the offering to me and my retinue, the practitioner should remain with one-pointed concentration in an isolated place.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="108">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1295</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:45:20.896Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་སྒོམ་པ་པོས་བདག་གི་སྔགས་དེ་ཁྲི་ཕྲག་གཅིག་བཟླས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:45:20.896Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>A practitioner of the blessed Vajrapāṇi must recite my mantra ten thousand times,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="109">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1377</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:45:31.791Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>དེ་ནས་ལས་རྣམས་བསྒྲུབ་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:45:31.791Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>and then accomplish the activities.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="110">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1413</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:48:01.379Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ལྟར་བདག་སྒྲུབ་པ་དང་བདག་གི་ལས་སྒྲུབ་པ་པོ་དེས་བདག་འཁོར་དང་བཅས་པ་ལ་གཏོར་མ་དང་མཆོད་པ་རྒྱ་ཆེན་པོས་མཆོད་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:48:01.379Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>One who thus accomplishes my state of being and my activity should offer an oblation and make vast offerings to me and to my retinue.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="111">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1547</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:48:53.075Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ལ་བདག་དང་བདག་གི་འཁོར་རྣམས་ལ་མཆོད་པ་དང་གཏོར་མ་རྒྱ་ཆེན་པོ་དབུལ་བའི་སྔགས་ནི་འདི་རྣམས་ཡིན་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:48:53.075Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>The mantra to recite for making vast offerings and offering the oblation to me and my retinue is this:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="112">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:50:40.415Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ཨོྃ་བཻ་ཤྲ་བ་ཎཱ་ཡ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་ཛམ་དྷ་ལཱ་ཡ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ ཨོྃ་པཱུརྞ་བྷ་དྲཱ་ཡ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་མ་ཎི་པྷ་དྲཱ་ཡ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་ཀུ་བེ་རཱ་ཡ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་སྃ་པྲ་ཛྣཱ་ནཱ་ཡ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་གུ་ཧྱ་སྠཱ་ནཱ་ཡ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་པཱཉྩི་ཀཱ་ཡ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་པི་ཙི་ཀུཎྜ་ལི་ནེ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ་</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:50:40.415Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Oṃ vaiśravaṇāya svāhā Oṃ jambhalāya svāhā Oṃ pūrṇabhadrāya svāhā Oṃ maṇibhadrāya svāhā Oṃ kuberāya svāhā Oṃ samprajñānāya svāhā Oṃ guhyasthānāya svāhā Oṃ pāñcikāya svāhā Oṃ bījakuṇḍaline svāhā</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="113">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">195</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:51:05.335Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ཞེས་པའི་སྔགས་དེ་རྣམས་ནི་བདག་གི་འཁོར་དང་བཅས་པ་ལ་མཆོད་པ་དང་གཏོར་མ་སྦྱིན་པའི་སྔགས་གཉིས་སུ་ཤེས་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:51:05.335Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Know that these are the mantras both for making offerings and giving an oblation to me and my retinue.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="114">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">299</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:54:12.34Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བདག་གི་ལས་སྒྲུབ་པ་ནི་བདག་གིས་བཤད་ཀྱིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབ་ཏུ་གསོལ་ཞེས་གསོལ་ནས་</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:54:12.34Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Then, with respect to accomplishing my activity, I requested the Blessed One to bless me with his explanation.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="115">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">411</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:54:22.624Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>འདིའི་ལས་བཤད་པ་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:54:22.624Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>The explanation of the activity is this:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="116">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">452</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:55:20.603Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>གང་ཟག་གང་གིས་སྒྲུབ་འདོད་པས། །གསང་དང་སྦྱིན་སྲེག་མནན་པ་གསུམ། །རིམ་པ་ཇི་བཞིན་ཤེས་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:55:20.603Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Whoever wishes to gain accomplishment Must know the stages Of killing, the burnt offering, and the suppression ritual.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="117">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">572</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:56:38.802Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བསྒྲུབ་བྱ་བསྟན་ལ་སྡང་བ་རྣམས། །སྤྲ་ཚིལ་ལ་སོགས་གཟུགས་བྱས་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:56:38.802Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Make an effigy out of beeswax Of the target—those hostile toward the teachings.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="118">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">653</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:56:51.535Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དགུག་དང་གཞུགས་སོགས་དབང་དུ་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:56:51.535Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Draw him, make him enter, and then take control.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="119">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">702</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:57:37.559Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ཡིག་འབྲུ་བཅྭ་བརྒྱད་སྔགས་ཀྱིས་ནི། །དུས་གསུམ་བརྡེག་པར་རབ་བྱས་ནས། །འཕྲལ་དུ་ཡིད་ཆེས་འཇོམས་པ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:57:37.559Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“The eighteen-syllable mantra Forcefully strikes down in the three times, And suddenly his spirit is broken.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="120">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">811</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:57:55.129Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བསྒྲུབ་བྱ་གསོད་པར་ཐེ་ཚོམ་མེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:57:55.129Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>There is no doubt that the target will be slain.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="121">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">860</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:58:58.592Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གལ་ཏེ་སྦྱིན་སྲེག་བྱེད་པ་ན། །ཞི་རྒྱས་དབང་དང་མངོན་སྤྱོད་ལས། །འདིར་ནི་དྲག་པོས་བསྒྲལ་བར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T15:58:58.592Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“If one is practicing the burnt offerings From among peaceful, increasing, magnetizing, and wrathful activities, Here one should perform liberation wrathfully.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="122">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1020</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:00:36.709Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ནེར་སྤ་ཚ་ལ་རབ་བསྲེག་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:00:36.709Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Thoroughly burn with a blazing fire.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="123">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1057</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:01:57.928Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཐབ་ཁུང་རབ་དང་འབྲིང་ཐ་མ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:01:57.928Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“With respect to the superior, average, and inferior hearth,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="124">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1118</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:02:51.743Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རབ་ཀྱིས་མཐོ་གསུམ་འབྲིང་གིས་དོ། །ཐ་མས་མཐོ་གང་ཚད་དུ་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:02:51.743Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Construct the superior one in three measures, the average in two, And the inferior in whatever measure is possible.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="125">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1234</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:03:24.156Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བུད་ཤིང་ཚེར་མ་ཅན་ཤིང་གིས། །ཀུན་ཏུ་དྲག་པོ་རབ་ཏུ་བསྒྲུབ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:03:24.156Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“With fuel of thorny wood, Great wrath is accomplished.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="126">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1290</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:03:40.929Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བག་ཟན་ཡུངས་ཀར་མེར་བསྲེག་ཅིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:03:40.929Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Burn dough and mustard seeds in the fire;</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="127">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1332</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:04:06.272Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྡང་བའི་ལུས་ངག་ཡིད་གསུམ་རྣམས། །རྫས་ལ་བསྟིམས་ཏེ་སྦྱིན་བསྲེག་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:04:06.272Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Dissolve the body, speech, and mind of the aggressor Into the substances, and make the burnt offering.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="128">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1435</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:05:35.279Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།འཁོར་བཅས་གནོད་སྦྱིན་མེར་བསམས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:05:35.279Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Imagine the retinue of yakṣas in the fire</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="129">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1478</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:06:04.839Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བསྲེག་པའི་རྫས་ཀྱིས་མཆོད་པའམ། །ལས་མེ་གནོད་སྦྱིན་རྫས་ཀྱིས་བྲབ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:06:04.839Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>And present them with the burnt substances, Or scatter the activity-fire yakṣas with the substances.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="130">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1579</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:06:18.035Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གང་ལྟར་བྱས་ཀྱང་འགྲུབ་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:06:18.035Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>However you do it, it will be accomplished.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="131">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1623</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:06:43.437Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ཚེ་བསྟོད་པ་འདིས་ཀྱང་ནི། །རྩེ་གཅིག་སེམས་ཀྱིས་བསྟོད་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:06:43.437Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“At that time, also, with these words of praise Focus your mind one-pointedly and offer praise:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="132">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1719</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:07:24.52Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཧཱུྃ་ཀུན་འདུལ་མི་བཟད་གནོད་སྦྱིན་སོགས། །གདུག་པ་དཔལ་ཚ་རབ་ཏུ་འཇིགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:07:24.52Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Hūṃ! All-conquering, terrifying yakṣa and the rest, Terrorizing with your noxious brilliant heat,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="133">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1818</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:07:49.073Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཁྲོ་བོ་རྔམ་པ་ཆེར་སྒྲོགས་པ། །འཁོར་བཅས་རྣམས་ལ་ཕྱག་འཚལ་བསྟོད།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:07:49.073Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Bellowing loudly with wrathful splendor. Homage and praise to you and your retinue!</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="134">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1902</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:08:18.682Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཨོྃ་བཻ་ཤྲ་བ་ཎ་པུ་ཥྤེ་ཧཱུྃ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃབཻ་ཤྲ་བ་ཎ་དྷུ་པེ་ཧཱུྃ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་བཻ་ཤྲ་བ་ཎ་དཱི་པྃ་ཧཱུྃ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་བཻ་ཤྲ་བ་ཎ་གན་དྷེ་ཧཱུྃ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་བཻ་ཤྲ་བ་ཎ་ནཻ་བི་དྱེ་ཧཱུྃ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:08:18.682Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Oṃ vaiśravaṇa puṣpe hūṃ svāhā Oṃ vaiśravaṇa dhupe hūṃ svāhā Oṃ vaiśravaṇa dīpaṃ hūṃ svāhā Oṃ vaiśravaṇa gandhe hūṃ svāhā Oṃ vaiśravaṇa naivedye hūṃ svāhā</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="135">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2057</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:08:47.581Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>གཙོ་བོ་མཆོད་ཅིང་འཁོར་ཀྱང་མཆོད། །དེ་ནས་རིམ་པས་མཆོད་པ་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:08:47.581Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Worship the central deity and also his retinue; Make offerings in sequence.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="136">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2134</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:09:18.135Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གསང་སྔགས་ཀུན་ཏུ་སྤེལ་ཏེ་བཟླས། །སྤྲོ་དང་བསྡུ་བ་ཀུན་དུ་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:09:18.135Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Recite, spreading secret mantras; Perform the projection and reabsorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="137">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2209</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:09:34.475Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྤེལ་བྱེད་ཀུན་གྱི་ཐུན་མོང་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:09:34.475Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>This is the ordinary form of propagation.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="138">
            <prop name="folio">f.161.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2251</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:10:10.226Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཨོྃ་བཻ་ཤྲ་ཝ་ཎཱ་ཡ་ཆེ་གེ་མོ་མཱ་ར་ཡ་ཕཊ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:10:10.226Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Oṃ vaiśravaṇaya chegemo māraya phaṭ svāhā</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="139">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">44</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:10:34.8Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>གཙོ་བོ་ཇི་ལྟར་འཁོར་ཀྱང་དེ། །རང་གི་རིག་པས་མཆོད་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:10:34.8Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“For the retinue, just as for the main deity, Worship them with their own incantations.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="140">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">132</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:10:53.577Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རིག་པ་ཀུན་ཏུ་བརྟན་བྱས་ནས། །རྡུལ་ཕྲན་བཞིན་དུ་བརླག་པར་བསམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:10:53.577Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Fully supported by incantations, Imagine that they crush them into dust.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="141">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">205</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:11:18.028Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཕྲིན་ལས་བཅོལ་ལ་གཏོར་མ་བཏང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:11:18.028Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Enjoin them to perform activity and give an oblation.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="142">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">260</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:11:48.341Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གཏོར་དང་གཏོར་མའི་རིམ་པ་ནི། །གོ་རིམས་བཞིན་དུ་དབུལ་བར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T16:11:48.341Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>As for the stages of sprinkling and offering the oblation, Offer them in order.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="143">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">340</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:08:43.468Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཞི་བའི་ལས་ཀྱི་རིམ་པ་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:08:43.468Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>The sequence for the peaceful activity is as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="144">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">394</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:09:03.977Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཐབ་ཁུང་མཐོ་གང་ཚད་ཉིད་ལ། །བསྲེག་རྫས་ལ་སོགས་རབ་ཏུ་དབུལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:09:03.977Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“On a hearth of sufficient size, Offer the burning substances and so forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="145">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">470</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:09:21.124Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ལུས་ངག་ཡིད་གསུམ་སྡིག་བཅོམ་ནས། །ཡེ་ཤེས་མེ་ཡི་ངོ་བོར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:09:21.124Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Having conquered the evil deeds of body, speech, and mind, Transform them into the essence of wisdom fire.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="146">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">577</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:09:39.457Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྣོད་དང་ཐབ་ནི་དོར་བར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:09:39.457Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Discard the vessel and the hearth.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="147">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">613</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:11:27.124Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེར་ནི་གདོན་རྣམས་ཀུན་སྲེག་ཅིང་། །བགེགས་ཆེན་ཞི་བའི་ཡས་ཀྱང་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:11:27.124Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Completely burn all grahas there, And also make a ransom rite to pacify the great obstructors.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="148">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">708</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:12:03.261Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རྒྱས་དང་དབང་དུ་བྱ་བ་ལ། །ལས་དང་བྱེ་བྲག་རིམ་པ་རྣམས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:12:03.261Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>In order to increase and magnetize For the activity and specific stages,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="149">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">781</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:12:27.479Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྔར་བཤད་པ་ཡི་ལས་བཞིན་དུ། །ཐབ་དབྱིབས་བྱེ་བྲག་ཤེས་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:12:27.479Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Know that the details of the shape of the hearth Are in accordance with the previously explained activities.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="150">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">890</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:12:50.138Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སེར་དང་དམར་བའི་བུད་ཤིང་སོགས། །རིམ་པ་རྫས་ལྡན་དབུལ་བ་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:12:50.138Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“As for the substantial offering, With the stages of red and yellow firewood and so forth:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="151">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">981</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:13:09.946Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཨོྃ་བཻ་ཤྲ་བ་ཎཱ་ཡ་དྷ་ནྃ་པུཥྚིྃ་ཀུ་རུ་ཡེ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་བཻ་ཤྲ་བ་ཎ་བ་ཤྃ་ཀུ་རུ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། ཨོྃ་བཻ་ཤྲ་བ་ཎཱ་ཡེ་ཤཱིནྟ་ཀུཾ་རུ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:13:09.946Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Oṃ vaiśravaṇāya dhanapuṣṭiṃ kuru ye svāhā Oṃ vaiśravaṇa vaśaṃ kuru svāhā Oṃ vaiśravaṇāye śāntiṃ kuru svāhā</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="152">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">1089</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:13:32.071Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>གཙོ་བོ་ཇི་བཞིན་འཁོར་བཅས་ནི། །རིག་པའི་རྫས་ཀྱིས་མཆོད་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:13:32.071Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Just as for the main deity, for the retinue also Make offerings with the incantatory substances.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="153">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">1187</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:14:12.725Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བསྲེག་པའི་རྫས་ནི་བག་ཟན་དང་། །ཡུངས་ཀར་མངར་སོགས་རིམ་པས་མཆོད།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:14:12.725Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Offer the burned substances of dough, Mustard seeds, sweets, and so forth in sequence.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="154">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">1274</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:14:36.16Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཕྲིན་ལས་རྣམ་བཞི་ཀུན་འགྲུབ་སྟེ། ། བརྩེ་བར་བརྩོན་པས་ཉེ་བར་འགྲུབ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:14:36.16Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“The four activities are perfectly accomplished. With superior diligence, they are fully accomplished.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="155">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">1377</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:14:56.476Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།འབྲིང་དང་ཐ་མས་འབྲིང་དང་ནི། །ཐ་མ་ཉིད་དུ་ཤེས་པར་གྱིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:14:56.476Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>With middling and lesser diligence, know that They are accomplished in a middling and lesser way.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="156">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">1476</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:15:30.332Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུ་འཁོར་དང་བཅས་པ་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:15:30.332Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then Vaiśravaṇa and his retinue declared to the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="157">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">1537</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:16:21.238Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་བདག་ཅག་རྣམས་ཀྱིས་བཤད་པའི་ལས་འདི་རྣམས་སྒྲུབ་པ་པོ་དེས་དུས་རྒྱུན་དུ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་དང་། གནོད་སྦྱིན་རྣམས་ལ་དཀར་གསུམ་གྱིས་མཆོད་པར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:16:21.238Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Blessed One, whoever engages in the practices that we have explained here should continually worship the Blessed Vajrapāṇi and the yakṣas with the three white substances.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="158">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">1709</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:16:43.532Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཆང་ཀུན་ཏུ་སྤང་བར་བགྱིའོ། །ཤ་རྣམས་ནི་འོས་པ་དང་ཤིས་པ་དྲང་བར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:16:43.532Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>He must completely avoid alcohol. He must acquire meats that are suitable and auspicious.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="159">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">1799</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:19:04.091Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ལྟར་རྩེ་གཅིག་གིས་བདག་ཅག་སྒྲུབ་པ་དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་ཕྲིན་ལས་ཇི་ལྟ་བ་བཞིན་དུ་བདག་ཅག་གིས་མ་བསྒྲུབས་ན་</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:19:04.091Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>If we fail to accomplish, properly and one-pointedly, the activities that are our accomplishments,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="160">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">1898</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:19:32.177Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>བདག་ཅག་གིས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འཁུས་པར་གྱུར་ཅིང་། བདག་ཅག་གིས་ཆོས་མ་བསྐྱངས་པར་བྱས་པ་ཡིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:19:32.177Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>then we will have insulted the Blessed One and we will have failed to protect the Dharma.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="161">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.a </prop>
            <prop name="position">1988</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:19:48.971Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ལ་བདག་གི་བྲོ་ཚིག་ནི་འདི་ཡིན་ནོ། །ཨོྃ་བཻ་ཤྲ་བ་ཎ་ཨར་ཐ་ཁ་ཐམ་ཞེས་པའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:19:48.971Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>This is our oath. Oṃ vaiśravaṇa arthakathama. ”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="162">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">561</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:20:24.771Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུ་ཆེན་པོ་ལེགས་སོ། །ཤིན་ཏུ་རབ་ཏུ་ལེགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:20:24.771Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Great Vaiśravaṇa, that is excellent. So very excellent!”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="163">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">641</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:22:09.069Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།མ་འོངས་པའི་གང་ཟག་གི་དོན་དུ་རང་གི་གསང་བ་སྨྲས་པ་ནི་དོན་ཆེན་པོ་དང་ལྡན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:22:09.069Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“So very excellent! The secret of which you have spoken will be of great benefit for the people of the future.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="164">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">752</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:22:34.13Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ངས་ཀྱང་དེ་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དོན་ངེས་པར་འགྲུབ་པར་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར་སྔགས་འདི་བཤད་ཀྱིས་ཉོན་ཅིག</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:22:34.13Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>In order that their benefit will certainly be accomplished, I also will pronounce this mantra. Listen!”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="165">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">856</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:23:04.28Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་ལེགས་སོ་ཞེས་རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུ་ལ་སོགས་པ་རྣམས་ལྟར་ཉན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:23:04.28Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Excellent!” said Vaiśravaṇa and the others to the Blessed One, and listened accordingly.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="166">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">973</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:23:30.739Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ཨོཾ་བཛྲ་པཱ་ཎི་ནཱི་ལཱྃ་བ་རདྷ་ར་བཛྲ་སྥོ་ཊ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་སྭཱ་ཧཱ། རིག་པ་འདི་ནི་ལས་ཐམས་ཅད་དབང་དུ་སྡུད་པའི་སྔགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:23:30.739Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Oṃ vajrapāṇi nīlāmbara­dhara vajrasphoṭa hūṃ phaṭ svāhā. This incantation is a mantra that brings control over activities.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="167">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1097</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:23:52.379Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུ་ཆེན་པོས་ཇི་ལྟར་ཁས་བླངས་པ་ལྟར་གསང་བ་དང་ལྡན་པར་བྱེད་པའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:23:52.379Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Great Vaiśravaṇa brings about possession of the secret just as he promised.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="168">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1174</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:24:30.257Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་བཞིན་གྱུར་ཞེས་སྨྲས་ནས་གནོད་སྦྱིན་མི་སྣང་བར་གྱུར་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:24:30.257Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“That is so,” said the yakṣas, and vanished.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="169">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1219</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:24:47.409Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རྡོ་རྗེས་འོག་གི་རྒྱུད་ལས་རྣམ་ཐོས་སྲས་ཀྱི་ལེའུ་སྟེ་གསུམ་པའོ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-26T18:24:47.409Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>This was the third chapter of The Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld, the chapter on Vaiśravaṇa.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="170">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1427</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:12:38.829Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་མ་འོངས་པའི་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དོན་དུ་གདུག་པ་ཅན་ལ་བསྣུན་པའི་འཁོར་ལོ་བཤད་དུ་གསོལ་ཞེས་</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:12:38.829Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Lord, for the sake of sentient beings of the future, please teach a wheel that strikes all wicked ones!”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="171">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1533</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:15:09.04Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་ཅང་མི་གསུང་བར་ཐུགས་ཀྱིས་གནང་</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:15:09.04Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>The Blessed One mentally consented to this request, yet remained completely silent.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="172">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1617</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:16:01.504Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ནས་རང་གི་ཐུགས་ཀ་ནས་འོད་ཟེར་ཀུན་ཏུ་ཁྱབ་པར་སྤྲོས་ཏེ། སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་འཁྱམས་པས་ཁྱབ་པར་མཛད་</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:16:01.504Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Instead he projected an all-pervading light from his heart center that embraced all sentient beings with love.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="173">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1752</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:18:37.594Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ལག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་ངས་ས་འོག་གི་བགེགས་ལ་བསྣུན་པའི་འཁོར་ལོ་བཤད་ཀྱིས་ཁྱོད་རྩེ་གཅིག་ཏུ་ཉོན་ཅིག་དེ་ལྟར་འཚལ་ལོ་ཞེས་</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:18:37.594Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Vajrapāṇi, I shall now teach a wheel that strikes the obstructors within the ground below. So listen one-pointedly, and I will teach.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="174">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1956</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:19:54.749Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>གང་ཞིག་འཁྲུལ་འཁོར་བྱེད་འདོད་པས། །ཉམས་དགའ་དབེན་པའི་གནས་དག་ཏུ། །ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེའི་རྣལ་འབྱོར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:19:54.749Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Whoever wishes to construct such a diagram Should go to pleasant and solitary places And perform the practice of Vajrapāṇi.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="175">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2081</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:20:11.399Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྣོད་བཅུད་རྡོ་རྗེ་གཏུམ་པོར་བསྒོམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:20:11.399Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Visualize the world and its contents as Vajracaṇḍa.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="176">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2133</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:34:31.638Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རླུང་ནས་རི་རབ་མཐར་ཐུག་པ། །རྡུལ་སྙེད་གྲངས་ཀྱི་སྐུ་རུ་བསམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:34:31.638Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“From the element of wind up until the central mountain, Imagine it to consist of enlightened bodies as numerous as there are particles.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="177">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2270</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:34:55.862Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དབུས་ན་ཕྱག་རྡོར་རྣལ་འབྱོར་བསྒོམ། །རི་བོང་འཛིན་པ་ཞབས་ཀྱིས་བརྡེབས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:34:55.862Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Amid this, cultivate the practice of Vajrapāṇi. His feet are placed on the holder of the hare.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="178">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2365</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:35:56.384Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྟོང་གསུམ་ཚད་ཀྱི་ཟླ་བ་ལ། །བགེགས་ཆེན་ཀུན་ཏུ་འདར་བར་བསྒོམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:35:56.384Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“On this moon, the size of the trichiliocosm, Visualize the great obstructor, utterly shaking.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="179">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2460</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:37:57.047Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྐུ་ལ་ཉི་མ་སྟོང་ལྡན་པའི། །གཟི་བརྗིད་བཟོད་དཀའི་འོད་ཟེར་གྱིས། །བགེགས་རྣམས་མ་ལུས་འཚིག་པར་བསྒོམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:37:57.047Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Vajrapāṇi’s body shines with the splendor of a thousand suns. “Visualize that this light, which is unbearable to watch, Burns away all obstructors without exception.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="180">
            <prop name="folio">f.162.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2626</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:38:17.31Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ལྗགས་ལས་བཟླས་པའི་སྔགས་ཕྲེང་གིས། །སྟོང་གསུམ་གང་བར་རབ་ཏུ་བསྒོམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:38:17.31Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>The mantra chain recited from the tongue Is seen to fill the trichiliocosm.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="181">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">181</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:40:46.246Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རྒྱན་དུ་བྱས་པའི་ཀླུ་བརྒྱད་ཀྱིས། །ཁ་རླངས་ཆེན་པོ་བཏང་བ་ལས། །ལྷ་ཀླུ་ཐམས་ཅད་སྐྲག་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:40:46.246Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“The eight adorning nāgas Release a giant breath of steam That terrifies all gods and nāgas.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="182">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">274</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:41:28.512Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཐུགས་ལས་ཁྲོ་སྤྲོས་དེ་དག་གིས། །བསྐལ་པའི་རླུབ་ལྟར་འཐོར་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:41:28.512Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Wrathful ones are projected from his heart center And, like the winds at the end of an eon, cause them to disperse.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="183">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">390</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:42:19.68Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཕྱག་གིས་རྡོ་རྗེ་རབ་བསྣུན་པས། སྒྱོགས་གཟེར་བཞིན་དུ་བསྣུན་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:42:19.68Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“With his hand, he strikes with the vajra; Like a bolt shot from a crossbow, it strikes down.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="184">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">484</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:43:22.442Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་འབྲུག་ལྟར་རབ་ཏུ་སྒྲོགས། །སྐད་ཀྱིས་ཀུན་ཏུ་བཀུག་པར་བསམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:43:22.442Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Hūṃ hūṃ resounds like thunder; They are thoroughly suppressed by his voice.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="185">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">560</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:43:46.402Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ལྟར་བྱས་འགྱུར་ཐམས་ཅད་འགྲུབ། །ལས་ཀྱིས་མནར་བ་འཇིག་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:43:46.402Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Act like that, and all will be accomplished; Karmic torment will come to an end.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="186">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">642</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:44:11.949Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་མི་ཤེས་པར། །གང་ཞིག་གཞན་བསྒྲུབ་སྐལ་དམན་པར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:44:11.949Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>If one does not know Vajrapāṇi, Other accomplishments will be inferior.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="187">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">714</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:44:32.93Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།འདི་ལ་གང་འགྲུབ་ཐམས་ཅད་འགྲུབ། །མཆོག་དང་ཐུན་མོང་བྱེ་བྲག་གོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:44:32.93Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Whatever is accomplished hereby accomplishes all— In particular, the supreme and the common.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="188">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">809</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:44:49.885Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རྡོ་རྗེས་འོག་གི་རྒྱུད་ལས་བསྣུན་པའི་འཁོར་ལོ་སྟེ་ལེའུ་བཞི་པའོ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-27T23:44:49.885Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>This was the fourth chapter on the wheel of suppression from The Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="189">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">960</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:34:56.661Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།།དེ་ནས་གཞན་ཡང་འཁྲུལ་འཁོར་གྱི། །ཆོ་ག་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཛིན་པས་གསུངས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:34:56.661Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then, at another time, the Vajra Holder Taught the ritual of the diagram:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="190">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1034</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:35:38.758Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གྲོ་གའམ་ཤིང་ཤུན་དག་ལ་ནི། །རེའུ་མིག་ཉི་ཤུ་རྩ་གཅིག་པའི། །འཁོར་ལོ་དག་ནི་རབ་བྲིས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:35:38.758Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“On a piece of birch bark or rind, Draw a wheel With twenty-one sections.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="191">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1108</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:36:13.328Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཟླ་བ་ཡར་གྱི་ངོ་ལ་བརྩམ། །རྩེ་གཅིག་སེམས་ཀྱིས་རབ་ཏུ་བྲི།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:36:13.328Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Commence this on the waxing phase of the moon, “And write, with a one-pointed mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="192">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1192</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:39:14.731Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དབུས་སུ་དྲག་པོའི་ཡི་གེ་དགོད། །གཉིས་པར་ནོར་འཛིན་ཡི་གེ་སྟེ། །གསུམ་པ་བཛྲ་ཞེས་པ་དང་། །བཞི་པར་ཆུ་ཡིག་དང་པོ་དགོད། །ལྔ་པར་ཎི་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་དགོད། །མཚམས་བཞིར་བསྒྲུབ་བྱའི་གསོད་སྙིང་བྲི། །དེ་ནི་ནང་གི་རེའུ་མིག་གོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:39:14.731Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>In the center, place the wrathful syllable. In the second, the syllable of the wealth holder. In the third, comes the vajra. “In the fourth, place the first syllable of water. In the fifth, place the ṇi. At the four borders, write the essence mantra for killing the target. These are the inner sections.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="193">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1496</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:40:53.849Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཕྱི་ཡི་རེའུ་མིག་བཅུ་གཉིས་ལ། །ཨོཾ་སྤངས་ཡི་གེ་བཅུ་གཉིས་ལ། །དེ་ཡི་གསང་སྔགས་འདི་ཡིན་ཏེ། །ནཱི་ལཱྃ་བ་ར་དྷ་ར་བཛྲ་པཱ་ཎི་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་ཞེས་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:40:53.849Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“On the twelve outer sections Are the twelve syllables, omitting oṃ. On these the secret mantra is as follows: Nīlāmbara­dhara­vajra­pāṇi hūṃ phaṭ.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="194">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1644</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:42:09.2Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རབ་ཏུ་རྫོགས་པའི་འཁོར་ལོ་སྟེ། །བསྒྲུབ་བྱའི་སྙིང་གར་དྲིལ་དེ་གཞུག །དང་པོའི་མཐའ་ནས་དྲིལ་བར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:42:09.2Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“This completed wheel Should be rolled up and fixed to the heart center of the target; It should be rolled up from the front edge.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="195">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1775</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:42:27.688Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་སྦྱིན་སྲེག་ཆོ་ག་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:42:27.688Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then the fire-offering ritual should be performed.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="196">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1826</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:43:09.348Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གལ་ཏེ་མནན་པ་བྱེད་འདོད་པས། །སྔར་བཞིན་འཁྲུལ་འཁོར་རྫོགས་བྱས་ནས། །མཐའ་རུ་མནན་པའི་ཆོ་ག་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:43:09.348Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“If one wishes to subdue, The diagram should be completed as before. At the end, perform the ritual of subjugation.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="197">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1942</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:43:26.78Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཁམ་ཕོར་གསར་པ་ཁ་སྦྱར་དུ། །བཅུག་ནས་རྡོ་རྗེ་རྒྱ་གྲམ་བྲི།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:43:26.78Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Place the diagram in a fresh clay cup And draw a crossed vajra on the lid.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="198">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">2017</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:53:16.597Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རྡོ་ཡི་སྦྱིན་གྱིས་རབ་སྦྱར་ནས། །གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་སོགས་མནན་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:53:16.597Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Closing it with clay, Temples and the like can be suppressed.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="199">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">2079</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:54:03.601Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གལ་ཏེ་རེའུ་མིག་མི་འདོད་ན། །རྩིབས་བཅུ་གཉིས་པའི་འཁོར་ལོ་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:54:03.601Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“If you prefer not to have sections, Make a wheel with twelve spokes.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="200">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">2149</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:54:38.512Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ལྟེ་བར་ཧཱུྃ་དང་བསྒྲུབ་བྱའི་མིང་། །སྤེལ་ལ་རབ་དུ་དགོད་པར་བྱ། །ལྷག་མ་བཅུ་གཉིས་རྩིབས་ལ་དགོད།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:54:38.512Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>In the center, place and affix A hūṃ and the name of the target. “The remaining twelve are placed on the spokes.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="201">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">49</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:55:59.608Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>། བྲི་བ་རྫོགས་ན་སྙིང་གར་གཞུག །དགུག་དང་གཞུ་གསོགས་བྱས་ལ་བསྲེག</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:55:59.608Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>When the drawing is complete, insert it in the heart center. Summon, usher, and so forth, then burn.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="202">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">150</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:56:23.689Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།མི་འདོད་མནན་པའི་ཆོ་ག་བྱ། །མར་གྱི་དུས་ལ་ཤིས་པ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:56:23.689Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Perform the ritual for suppression of the unwanted; From that time onward, there is auspiciousness.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="203">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">251</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:57:01.14Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།འཁྲུལ་འཁོར་ཇི་ལྟར་བྲིས་པ་ལྟར། །གང་འདོད་ལས་ལ་ཐེ་ཚོམ་མེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:57:01.14Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Whenever the diagram is drawn, There is no doubt that things will occur as desired.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="204">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">335</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:57:33.009Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དཔེར་ན་མེ་ལྕེས་རྩྭ་བསྲེགས་འདྲ། །གང་ཡིན་གནས་པར་མི་འགྱུར་རོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:57:33.009Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Just like dry grass being burnt up by flames, The person will be unable to remain.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="205">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">420</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:57:54.337Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དཔལ་རྡོ་རྗེས་འོག་གི་རྒྱུད་ལས་བྲི་བའི་འཁྲུལ་འཁོར་གྱི་ཆོ་ག་སྟེ་ལེའུ་ལྔ་པའོ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:57:54.337Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>This was the fifth chapter on the ritual for drawing the diagram from The Glorious Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="206">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">633</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:59:47.447Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཟབ་མོའི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་ལགས་པས་སྦྱིན་སྲེག་ལ་སོགས་པས་གྲོལ་བར་ཅང་འགྱུར་ལགས་སམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T16:59:47.447Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Lord, since everything is the domain of the profound, does one get liberated through such rituals as fire offerings, or not?</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="207">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">759</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:00:15.045Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>བདག་གི་ཐེ་ཚོམ་བསལ་དུ་གསོལ་ཞེས་ཞུས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:00:15.045Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Please clear away my doubts!”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="208">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">814</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:01:27.66Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ལག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་སྙིང་རྗེ་ཆེ། །དད་པའི་ཤུགས་ཀྱིས་རབ་ཉམས་ཏེ། །དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་རྫས་ཀྱི་སྦྱོར་ལྡན་ཞིང་། །སྦྱིན་སྲེག་ལས་དང་དེ་ཉིད་ཤེས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:01:27.66Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Vajrapāṇi! Great compassion, Removal through the power of faith, The maṇḍala endowed with substantial riches, And the activity of the fire offering—these you should know.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="209">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">986</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:01:53.824Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྡོམ་པར་དམ་ཚིག་རྒྱུད་ལྡན་ན། །མཚན་མས་གྲོལ་བར་འགྱུར་བ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:01:53.824Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“If your stream of being keeps samaya vows as your pledge, You will be liberated through attributes.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="210">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1087</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:03:04.613Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་སྦྱིན་སྲེག་རྫས་ལ་སོགས། །མེད་ན་དངོས་གྲུབ་མི་འགྲུབ་པས། །སྦྱིན་སྲེག་ལས་ནི་འབད་པས་བརྩམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:03:04.613Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Without a maṇḍala, fire offering, substances, and so forth, Spiritual accomplishments will not be achieved. “Therefore be diligent in the activity of fire offering.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="211">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1252</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:03:37.754Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཕྲིན་ལས་བཞི་ཡི་སྦྱིན་སྲེག་ལས། དྲག་པོའི་རིམ་པ་བྱ་བ་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:03:37.754Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Among the fire offerings of the four enlightened activities, The stages of the wrathful one is as follows:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="212">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1359</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:06:35.826Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཁྲུ་བཞི་པ་ཡི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ལ། །དབུས་སུ་ཟུར་གསུམ་ཁྲུ་རེ་ཚད། །ཟབས་སུ་ཁྲུ་ཕྱེད་བརྐོ་བར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:06:35.826Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>In the center of a maṇḍala of four cubits, “There is a triangle of one cubit; It should be dug to a depth of half a cubit.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="213">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1482</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:07:13.843Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཕྱི་རོལ་རིམ་པ་གསུམ་ལྡན་པ། །དབུས་སུ་རྡོ་རྗེའི་མཚན་མ་བྲི།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:07:13.843Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Outside there are three levels; Draw the features of a vajra in the middle.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="214">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1558</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:09:48.88Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རིམ་པ་གསུམ་ལ་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཡི། །རྩེ་གསུམ་ཕྲེང་གིས་བསྐོར་བ་བྲི། །མཚམས་སུ་ལྕགས་ཀྱུ་བྲི་བར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:09:48.88Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“At the three levels, draw the three points of a vajra Encircled by a chain. In the intermediate spaces, draw iron hooks.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="215">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1680</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:10:30.301Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཚེར་མ་ཅན་གྱི་ཤིང་བུ་ནི། །ཁྲུ་གང་ཚད་ཀྱིས་རབ་ཏུ་ཤིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:10:30.301Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>A piece of thorny wood “The size of a cubit is very auspicious.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="216">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1744</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:11:03.466Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དུག་དང་ཁྲག་དང་སྐེ་ཚེ་སོགས། །རྫས་ནི་རིམ་པར་ཤེས་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:11:03.466Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Substances such as poison, blood, and black mustard seeds Should be gradually known.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="217">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1829</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:11:35.488Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བདག་ཉིད་ལྷ་ཡི་རྣལ་འབྱོར་གྱིས། །ཡེ་ཤེས་ཁྲོ་བོ་སྤྱན་དྲངས་ཏེ། །འཇིག་རྟེན་གསུམ་འདུལ་གཟུགས་སུ་བསམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:11:35.488Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Oneself, through the yoga of the deity, “Invites the wrathful wisdom, Visualized in the form that tames the three worlds.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="218">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1951</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:12:17.609Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།མཆོད་པའི་རིམ་པ་རབ་ཏུ་དབུལ། །དེ་ལ་སྦྱིན་སྲེག་གི་སྔགས་གསུངས་པ་འདི་ཡིན་ཏེ། ཨོཾ་ནཱི་ལཱྃ་བར་དྷ་ར། ཨོཾ་བཛྲ་ཛྭ་ལ་ཨ་ན་ལ་ཧ་ན་སརྦཱ་དུཥྚ་སརྦྦ་བྷི་རྨྨྃ་ཀུ་རུ་ནཱི་ལཱྃ་བར་དྷ་ར་བཛྲ་པཱ་ཎི་ཆེ་གེ་མོ་མཱ་ར་ཡ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ་ཅེས་པས་རྫས་རྣམས་བསྲེག་གོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:12:17.609Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Perform the stages of worship. For that, the mantra of the fire offering to be uttered is this: “Oṃ nīlāmbara­dhara oṃ vajra­jvalānala hana sarva­duḥkha sarva­vighna samma kuru­nīlāmbara­dhara vajra­pāṇi chegemo māraya hūṃ phaṭ. “Say this while burning the substances.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="219">
            <prop name="folio">f.163.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2220</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:12:51.939Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དུག་ཁྲག་སྐེ་ཚེ་ལན་ཚྭ་ལས། །གཟུགས་བྱས་རབ་ཏུ་བསྒྲུབས་ཏེ་བསྲེག</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:12:51.939Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“From poison, blood, black mustard, and salt, Create the form, accomplish it, and burn it.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="220">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">92</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:13:21.805Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཨོཾ་ནཱི་ལཱྃ་བ་ར་དྷ་ར་བཛྲ་པཱ་ཎི་ཡཀྵ་ཁཱ་ད་ཡ་ཁཱ་ད་ཡ་བན་དྷ་ཡ་བན་དྷ་ཡ་མོ་ཧ་ཡ་མོ་ཧ་ཡ་ཤ་ཏྲཱུཾ་ཨཱ་ན་ཡ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ། གཟུགས་ལ་བྲབ་པའི་སྔགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:13:21.805Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Oṃ nīlāmbara­dhara vajrapāṇi yakṣa khādaya khādaya bandhaya bandhaya mohaya mohaya sha hum ānaya hūṃ phaṭ. “This was the mantra for scattering the form.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="221">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">246</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:13:43.984Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཨོཾ་ནཱི་ལཱཾ་བ་ར་དྷ་ར་བཛྲ་པཱ་ཎི་ཤ་ཏྲཱུཾ་གྲྀ་ཧྞ་ཨཱ་ཀཪྵ་ཡ་ཧཱུཾ་ཛཿཛཿ། འགྲོ་བ་དགུག་པའི་སྔགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:13:43.984Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Oṃ nīlāmbara­dhara vajrapāṇi sha hum gṛham ākarṣaya hūṃ jaḥ jaḥ. “This was the mantra for summoning beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="222">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">355</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:14:18.168Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ལྟར་སྦྱིན་སྲེག་རབ་བྱས་ནས། །ཆུ་བོ་སྐམས་དང་ཀླུ་ཤིང་གཅད། །གླང་ཆེན་གཡང་ལྟུང་མེ་ཆེན་འབར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:14:18.168Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Having performed the fire offering in that manner, Go to a dried-up river, fell a nāga tree, And make a large fire with elephant dung.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="223">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">491</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:14:38.954Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ནད་དང་ཡམས་སོགས་བྱུང་བའི་ཚེ། །ཞི་བ་མཆོག་གི་ལས་བསྒྲུབས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:14:38.954Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Should illness and disease occur, “Perform the activity of supreme pacification.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="224">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">572</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:15:26.58Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཐབ་ཁུང་ཟླུམ་པོ་རབ་དཀར་བ། །རིམ་པ་གསུམ་ལྡན་ཁྲུ་གང་ཚད། །ཟབས་སུ་ཁྲུ་ཕྱེད་བརྐོས་བྱས་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:15:26.58Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Dig a suitable spherical fire pit in three levels; It should be one cubit wide And half a cubit deep.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="225">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">674</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:16:08.431Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>། ཞི་བའི་ལས་ཀྱི་ཆོ་ག་བྱ། །དེ་ལྟར་བྱས་ན་མཚན་མ་ཡི། །དངོས་གྲུབ་ཐོབ་པར་ཐེ་ཚོམ་མེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:16:08.431Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Then perform the ritual of peaceful activity. If done in this manner, there is no doubt that one obtains Spiritual accomplishments with the marks of success.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="226">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">833</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:16:56.598Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ལག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཛིན། །གུས་པས་རྒྱུད་དོན་རབ་ཏུ་ཟུང་། །འགྲོ་བའི་དོན་ལ་རབ་བརྩོན་གྱིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:16:56.598Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Vajrapāṇi, Vajra Holder! “With devotion, keep the meaning of the tantra, And be diligent for the sake of living beings!</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="227">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">953</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:17:30.135Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཀྱེ་མ་རྒྱུད་ཆེན་མཆོག་ཏུ་གསང་། །བྱིན་རླབས་སྔོན་དུ་ཆེར་འབྱུང་བ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:17:30.135Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“O! This most secret great tantra Grants great blessings from the start.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="228">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1026</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:17:45.554Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྟོན་པ་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཆང་གིས་གསུངས། །རབ་ཏུ་འབད་པས་བསྒྲུབ་པར་གྱིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:17:45.554Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>It was spoken by the teacher Vajradhara. Be diligent in its practice.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="229">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1097</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:18:08.02Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དཔལ་རྡོ་རྗེས་འོག་གི་རྒྱུད་ལས་སྦྱིན་སྲེག་གི་རིམ་པ་སྟེ་ལེའུ་དྲུག་པའོ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:18:08.02Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>This was the sixth chapter on the stages of fire offering from The Glorious Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="230">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1247</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:21:05.215Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།།དེ་ནས་སྟོན་པ་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཆང་། །དཔལ་ཆེན་གདན་ལ་རབ་བཞེངས་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:21:05.215Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then the teacher, the Vajra Holder, The Great Glorious One, stood up on his seat.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="231">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1329</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:21:51.798Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ལག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་ལ་གཟིགས་ནས། ། ལས་ཀྱི་ཆོ་ག་བཤད་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:21:51.798Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>He gazed at Vajrapāṇi and said: “One should know the ritual of activity.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="232">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1402</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:22:17.778Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དུག་ལ་སོགས་པའི་རྫས་རྣམས་ལ། །གང་འདོད་པ་ཡི་གཟུགས་བྱས་ཏེ། །སྙིང་གར་འཁྲུལ་འཁོར་རབ་ཏུ་གཞུག</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:22:17.778Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>With substances such as poison, Produce the form that you wish for, Then insert the diagram at the heart center.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="233">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1515</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:22:36.887Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བདག་ཉིད་ལས་ཀྱི་ལྷར་གསལ་བས། །ག་འུ་ནང་དུ་རབ་བཅུག་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:22:36.887Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Visualize yourself as the deity of activity, And place it in a box.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="234">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1584</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:23:03.837Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཚོན་གྱི་ཐ་གུ་སྣ་ལྔ་དཀྲི། །སྙིང་གའི་ལྕགས་ཀྱུས་རབ་བཀུག་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:23:03.837Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Tie it with five strings of various colors, Then summon your target with the hook at the heart center.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="235">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1687</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:23:39.873Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཡི་གེ་བཅུ་གསུམ་འཁྲུལ་འཁོར་བཟླས། །འགུལ་གཡོ་ཡི་ནི་རྟགས་བྱུང་ནས། །ཆུ་ཆེན་གཞུང་ལ་གཏང་བར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:23:39.873Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Next recite the thirteen letters of the diagram. When the signs of shivering and trembling occur, Throw it in the middle of a river.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="236">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1821</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:24:17.593Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གལ་ཏེ་རྟགས་དེ་མ་བྱུང་ན། །དྷ་རུ་ར་ཡི་ཁུ་བ་དང་། །ཁྲག་དང་དུག་བསྲེས་རབ་བྱུགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:24:17.593Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>If the signs should not occur, “Mix the fluid of datura, With blood and poison, and apply it.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="237">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1915</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:24:56.582Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཚེར་མ་ཅན་གྱི་ཤིང་མེས་བསྲེག ། ཨོཾ་ནཱི་ལཱཾ་བ་ར་དྷ་ར་བཛྲ་པཱ་ཎི་སྟམ་བྷ་ཡ་མོ་ཧ་ཡ་བན་དྷ་ཡ་ད་ཧ་ན་ཡ་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:24:56.582Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then burn it in the fire of a thorny tree. “Oṃ nīlāmbara­dhara vajrapāṇi stambhaya mohaya bandhaya dāhanaya hūṃ hūṃ phaṭ.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="238">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">2037</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:25:35.149Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>དུས་གསུམ་དག་དུ་བདུགས་བྱས་ནས། །སྐད་ངན་སྣ་ཚོགས་གདོན་པར་བྱེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:25:35.149Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Fumigate it at the three times, And utter many negative words.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="239">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">2101</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:26:03.491Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་སྔགས་འདིས་ཆུ་ལ་དོར། །ཨོཾ་ཙཎྜ་མ་ཧཱ་རོ་ཥ་ཎ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:26:03.491Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then throw it in the water, using this mantra: “Oṃ caṇḍa­mahā­roṣaṇa hūṃ phaṭ.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="240">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">2180</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:26:51.012Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཚོན་གྱིས་དྲིལ་ནས་རབ་ཏུ་བོར། །བསམ་པས་བ་ཚྭའི་རྒྱ་མཚོར་སྐྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:26:51.012Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Roll it around in pigment and throw it away; Imagine that you throw it into a salty ocean.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="241">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">93</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:28:02.795Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་མི་ལྡོག་བྱ་བའི་ཕྱིར། །སྔགས་འདི་རྒྱུན་དུ་བཟླ་བར་བྱ། །ཨོཾ་ནཱི་ལཱྃ་བ་ར་དྷ་ར་བཛྲ་པཱ་ཎི་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་སྟམ་བྷ་ཡ་ནན་ཕཊ་ཅེས་རྒྱུན་དུ་བཟླ་བར་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:28:02.795Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then, for the sake of irreversibility, Recite this mantra continuously: “Oṃ nīlāmbara­dhara vajrapāṇi hūṃ hūṃ stambhaya nan phaṭ. “Recite this continuously.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="242">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">250</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:28:23.127Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ལས་དེ་ངེས་པར་འགྲུབ་བོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:28:23.127Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then the activity will certainly be accomplished.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="243">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">301</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:28:43.56Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རྡོ་རྗེས་འོག་གི་རྒྱུད་ལས་བསྐྲད་པའི་འཁོར་ལོའི་ལེའུ་སྟེ་བདུན་པའོ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:28:43.56Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>This was the seventh chapter on the wheel of expulsion from The Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="244">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">423</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:30:09.741Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།།དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཛིན་པས་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དོན་དུ་སྔགས་ཀྱི་ལེའུ་འདི་གསུངས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:30:09.741Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then the Blessed One, the Vajra Holder, taught this chapter on mantra for the sake of living beings:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="245">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">524</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:30:38.793Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཨོཾ་ནཱི་ལཱཾ་བ་ར་དྷ་ར་བཛྲ་པཱ་ཎི་ཧཱུྃ་ཧཱུྃ་ཕཊ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱི་རྩ་བའི་སྔགས་ལས་ཐམས་ཅད་སྒྲུབ་པའོ། །འདི་ནི་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ཐུགས་ཀྱི་གསང་བའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:30:38.793Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Oṃ nīlāmbara­dhara vajrapāṇi hūṃ hūṃ phaṭ. “The root mantra of the Blessed One accomplishes all activities; This is the secret of the awakened mind of all buddhas.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="246">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">689</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:31:11.134Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།འདིས་ནི་མ་བསྒྲུབས་པར་ཡང་ལས་ཐམས་ཅད་འགྲུབ་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:31:11.134Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>It accomplishes all activity, even without practice;</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="247">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">742</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:31:29.644Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ཕྱག་རྒྱ་ཐམས་ཅད་འཆིང་བསྒྲུབ་པ་ལ་ནི་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཁུ་ཚུར་གྱིས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:31:29.644Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>With the vajra fists, you accomplish the binding of all mudrās.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="248">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">806</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:32:12.877Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དམ་ཚིག་ཐམས་ཅད་སྒྲུབ་པ་ལ་ནི་རྡོ་རྗེ་རབ་ཏུ་གདེངས་པས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:32:12.877Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“With vajra confidence, you accomplish all samaya vows!</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="249">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">862</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:32:42.61Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་རྗེས་སུ་ཆགས་པར་བྱ་བ་ལ་ནི་རྡོ་རྗེ་བཞད་པས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:32:42.61Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>With the vajra smile, you are affectionate toward all sentient beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="250">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">933</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:33:02.191Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཐམས་ཅད་ལྐུགས་པར་བྱ་བ་ལ་ནི་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཧཱུྃ་སྒྲས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:33:02.191Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>By uttering the vajra hūṃ, you make everyone mute.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="251">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">984</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:34:50.312Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ནམ་མཁའ་ལ་འཕྲོ་བའི་དངོས་གྲུབ་ལ་ནི་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཀུ་མུ་དས་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:34:50.312Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Through the vajra lotus, you gain the spiritual accomplishment of traversing the sky.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="252">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1070</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:35:10.093Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཀླུ་ཐམས་ཅད་འདུལ་བ་ལ་ནི་རྨ་བྱའི་མཇུག་སྒྲོས་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:35:10.093Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“With the tail of the peacock, you tame all nāgas.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="253">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1121</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:35:33.202Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དགྲ་ཐམས་ཅད་གསད་པ་ལ་ནི་འཁྲུལ་འཁོར་གྱིས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:35:33.202Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>With the diagram, you kill all enemies.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="254">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1161</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:35:56.753Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ནོར་བསྒྲུབ་པར་འདོད་ན་ཛམ་བྷ་ལའི་ཆུ་སྦྱིན་གྱིས་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:35:56.753Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>If you wish to accomplish wealth, perform the water offering to Jambhala.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="255">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1235</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:36:15.023Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བགེགས་འཕང་བར་འདོད་ན་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་གྱིས་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:36:15.023Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>If you wish to repel obstacle makers, do so through absorption.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="256">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1299</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:36:32.734Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཐམས་ཅད་འགུགས་པ་ལ་ནི་རྡོ་རྗེ་ལྕགས་ཀྱུས་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:36:32.734Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>With the vajra iron hook, you summon all.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="257">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1341</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:36:56.238Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རིམས་བསྲུང་བ་ལ་ནི་རྩྭ་ཀུ་ཤའི་འབྲུམ་བུས་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:36:56.238Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Protect against epidemics with the kuśa grass pock.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="258">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1394</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:37:48.318Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཀླུ་སྒྲུབ་པར་འདོད་ན་མཚར་བུའི་ལྕུག་མ་དང་བདུད་རྩི་ཆུས་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:37:48.318Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>If you wish to accomplish nāgas, use the shoots of hardwood trees and nectar.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="259">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1472</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:38:14.262Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཕ་རོལ་གྱི་དཔུང་འཇོམས་པར་འདོད་ན་གུ་གུལ་གྱིས་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:38:14.262Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>If you wish to destroy an opposing army, do so with frankincense.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="260">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1538</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:38:42.001Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ལས་རྣམས་ལ་སྔགས་འབུམ་གྱིས་བྱའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:38:42.001Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>For all actions, recite a hundred thousand mantras.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="261">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1591</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:39:01.217Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རྡོ་རྗེ་ས་འོག་གི་རྒྱུད་ལས་སྔགས་ཀྱི་ལེའུ་སྟེ་བརྒྱད་པའོ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-28T17:39:01.217Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>This was the eighth chapter on mantra from The Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="262">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1710</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:37:07.801Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།།དེ་ནས་གཞན་ཡང་བཟླས་པ་ཡི། །ངེས་པ་འདིར་ནི་བཤད་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:37:07.801Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Then, moreover, the certainty of recitation Will be taught now.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="263">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1775</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:38:50.857Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གང་ཞིག་དངོས་གྲུབ་སྒྲུབ་འདོད་པས། །དམ་ཚིག་སྡོམ་དང་རབ་ལྡན་པས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:38:50.857Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Whoever wishes to gain spiritual accomplishments Should fully possess commitments and pledges,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="264">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1870</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:39:08.174Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བདག་ཉིད་ལས་ཀྱི་ལྷར་བསྒོམས་ཏེ། །ཡེ་ཤེས་ཁྲོ་བོ་སྤྱན་དྲངས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:39:08.174Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“And visualize oneself as the deity of activity. Then invite the wrathful wisdom.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="265">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1952</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:39:41.986Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཛཿཧཱུྃ་བྃ་ཧོཿདགུག་སོགས་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:39:41.986Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Summon and the rest with jaḥ hūṃ vaṃ hoḥ.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="266">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1994</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:39:59.302Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རང་སྙིང་ཟླ་བར་སྔགས་ཀྱི་ཕྲེང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:39:59.302Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>In your heart, on a moon, is the mantra chain.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="267">
            <prop name="folio">f.164.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2041</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:40:39.991Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དངུལ་སྦྲམ་ལྟ་བུར་རབ་བསམས་ཏེ། །མྱུར་དལ་གསལ་དང་མི་གསལ་སྤང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:40:39.991Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Visualize it like a silver viper, Swift, free, and clear—without vagueness.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="268">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">78</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:41:05.463Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཡིད་ཀྱིས་བསྒྲིམ་པའི་བཟླས་པ་བྱ། །མཆོད་པ་རྣམ་པ་ལྔས་ཀྱང་མཆོད།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:41:05.463Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Mentally perform a concentrated recitation, Then make the fivefold offering.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="269">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">155</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:41:30.277Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རབ་ཏུ་བསྒྲིམ་པའི་བཟླས་པ་འདིས། །གང་འདོད་དངོས་གྲུབ་ངེས་པར་འགྲུབ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:41:30.277Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Through this fully concentrated recitation, All desired spiritual accomplishments will surely be accomplished.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="270">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">267</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:41:49.529Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཨོཾ་ཨཱཿཧཱུྃ་སྐུ་གསུང་ཐུགས་བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབ་པའི་སྔགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:41:49.529Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Oṃ āḥ hūṃ. “That is the mantra for the blessings of enlightened body, speech, and mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="271">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">356</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:42:11.171Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཨོཾ་བཛྲ་པཱ་ཎི་ཨ་བྷི་ཥིཉྩ་མཱཾ། དབང་བསྐུར་བའི་སྔགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:42:11.171Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Oṃ vajrapāṇi abhiṣiñca mām. “Such is the mantra for bestowing empowerment.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="272">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">432</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:42:26.573Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཨོཾ་བཛྲ་པཱ་ཎི་ཏིཥྛ་ཧཱུཾ། ཐུགས་བརྟན་པའི་སྔགས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:42:26.573Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Oṃ vajrapāṇi tiṣṭha hūṃ. “That is the mantra for stabilizing enlightened mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="273">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">512</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:44:04.989Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྐུ་དང་ཐུགས་ཀྱི་གསང་བ་དང་། །གསུང་གི་གསང་བ་མ་ལུས་པས། །མྱུར་དུ་བྱང་ཆུབ་ལ་རེག་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:44:04.989Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Through all the secrets of enlightened body and mind, And enlightened speech in their entirety, One will quickly meet with awakening.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="274">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">647</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:44:26.352Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གང་ཚེ་སྒྲུབ་ལ་བརྩོན་ལྡན་པ། །ཚེ་གཅིག་འབྲས་བུ་མྱུར་ཐོབ་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:44:26.352Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Whenever someone is practicing diligently, “The result will swiftly be attained within a single life.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="275">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">749</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:44:47.746Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>། གཉིས་མེད་རང་བཞིན་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཅན། །མཁའ་དབྱིངས་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཀུན་ཏུ་ཁྱབ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:44:47.746Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>The nondual nature is the vajra possessor; It fully pervades the vajra sky.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="276">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">825</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:45:32.858Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བརྗོད་མེད་རྟོག་བྲལ་དེ་ཉིད་དོན། །ལྷུན་གྲུབ་དང་ལ་རབ་ཏུ་གཞག</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:45:32.858Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>It is inexpressible, nonconceptual, the meaning of thatness. “Let go in this spontaneously accomplished state.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="277">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">936</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:46:05.717Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཧཱུྃ་དང་ཨ་ཡི་རྣམ་པ་ཅན། །ཇི་ལྟར་ཆུ་ཡི་ཟླ་བ་བཞིན། །མ་ཡེངས་སེམས་ཀྱིས་རྒྱུན་དུ་བསྒོམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:46:05.717Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>On the form of hūṃ and āḥ, Like a moon reflected in water, Meditate continually, with an undistracted mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="278">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1044</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:46:39.518Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཨེ་མ་ཧོ་མགོན་པོ་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས། ། མཆོག་ལས་མཆོག་ཏུ་རྣམ་པར་རྒྱལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:46:39.518Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Amazing! The Protector, the Blessed One, Is the utterly supreme victor.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="279">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1117</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:47:01.637Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཨེ་མ་ཧོ་སྤྲུལ་པའི་རྣམ་པ་སྐུ། །སྒྲ་ལ་རབ་ཏུ་དམིགས་པ་མེད།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:47:01.637Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Amazing! This emanated body Has no focus on sound.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="280">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1168</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:47:39.958Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དགྱེས་ཆེན་ཀུན་གྱི་སྤྱོད་ཡུལ་ཡིན། །རང་གསལ་ཉིད་ལ་རྣམ་པར་དག །མཆོག་གི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཚུལ་དུ་གནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:47:39.958Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“It is the domain of all joyful ones. This natural luminosity is purity; It abides as supreme awakening.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="281">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1274</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:48:01.007Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རྡོ་རྗེས་འོག་གི་རྒྱུད་ལས་ངེས་པ་དང་རྣམ་པར་དག་པའི་ལེའུ་སྟེ་དགུ་པའོ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-29T16:48:01.007Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>This was the ninth chapter on certainty and purity from The Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="282">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1397</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:15:23.328Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།།དེ་ནས་སྟོན་པ་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཆང་། །འགྲོ་བའི་མགོན་ལ་རབ་གཟིགས་ཏེ། །བསྲུང་བའི་ཆོ་ག་རབ་ཏུ་གསུངས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:15:23.328Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then the teacher Vajradhara Gazed at the protector of beings And taught the ritual of protection:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="283">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1495</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:15:54.739Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ལག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་རབ་ཏུ་ཉོན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:15:54.739Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Vajrapāṇi, listen well!</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="284">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1520</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:17:02.16Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།འགྲོ་བ་གདུག་པས་ཟིན་འགྱུར་བ། །ཟངས་མ་དག་ལ་དུད་འགྲོའི་གཟུགས། །ལེགས་པ་དག་ཏུ་རབ་བྱས་ཏེ། །ཁོང་པ་དངུལ་ལ་སོགས་པས་དགང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:17:02.16Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Those beings who are seized by wicked ones Should skillfully craft an image Of an animal in pure copper And fill its interior with silver and the like.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="285">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1673</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:17:32.017Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གང་ནས་འདོད་པའི་ས་ཕྱོགས་སམ། །རང་ལུས་དག་ལ་ལེགས་སྦས་ནས། །བསྲུང་བ་དམ་པར་འགྱུར་བའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:17:32.017Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Once filled, it should be well concealed In a desirable place or on one’s own body. This is the best protection.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="286">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1787</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:18:13.349Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བདེ་གཤེགས་སྐུ་གདུང་རིང་བསྲེལ་ཅན། །རབ་ཏུ་གནས་པ་ལེགས་བྱས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:18:13.349Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“A reliquary of the bliss-gone ones together with its relics Should be skillfully fashioned and consecrated.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="287">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1896</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:18:54.684Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གང་གནོད་སར་ནི་རབ་སྦས་ན། །བདེན་སྟོབས་བརྗོད་པས་ཞི་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:18:54.684Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>If it is concealed wherever harm might occur, There will be peace by pronouncing the power of truth.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="288">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1997</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:27:38.553Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སངས་རྒྱས་གང་གཱའི་བྱེ་ཚོགས་ཀྱིས། །གསུངས་པའི་གཟུངས་སྔགས་དག་གིས་ནི།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:27:38.553Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“The buddhas, as numerous as the grains of sand in the Ganges, Taught these incantation mantras.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="289">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">2094</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:27:54.927Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བྱ་ལ་སོགས་པའི་བྱོལ་སོང་ཚོགས། །ཡིད་འོང་མཛེས་པའི་དུད་འགྲོ་ལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:27:54.927Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>To many creatures, such as birds— All pleasant and beautiful animals.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="290">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">2164</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:28:21.965Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྐུད་པ་སྔོན་པོ་དག་དང་ནི། །དར་ལ་བརྒྱ་རྩ་བརྒྱད་བསྔགས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:28:21.965Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“With these mantras, one should consecrate One hundred and eight blue cords and strings of silk.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="291">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">2261</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:29:06.663Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བདེན་པ་བདར་ལ་རབ་ཏུ་བསྔོས། །གཏོར་མ་གཏང་ན་ཞི་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:29:06.663Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Invoke the truth and perform a dedication; When the oblation is given, there will be pacification.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="292">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">197</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:29:37.499Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཁམ་པོར་ལ་སོགས་སྣོད་གཙང་མར། །སྨན་དང་དར་སོགས་བར་བཅུག་སྟེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:29:37.499Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“In a clean vessel, such as a cup, Place such things as medicine and silk.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="293">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">272</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:29:54.442Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།མེ་ཏོག་བདུག་སོགས་མཆོད་བྱས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:29:54.442Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Make an offering of flowers, incense, and so forth.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="294">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">324</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:31:04.115Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ས་ལ་སྦས་ན་གནོད་པ་རྣམས། །ཞིབ་བ་དག་ཏུ་འགྱུར་བ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:31:04.115Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>If it is hidden in the ground, All harmful influences will become pacified.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="295">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">400</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:31:36.106Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྐུད་པ་དཀར་པོ་ལུས་བསྒྲིལ་ལ། ། མདུད་པ་ཉི་ཤུ་རྩ་གཅིག་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:31:36.106Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Braid together three white cords And make twenty-one knots.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="296">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">461</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:31:54.656Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྒྲུབ་དང་བསྒྲུབ་པའི་མཆོད་པ་བྱ། །རྒྱལ་ལ་རབ་ཏུ་མགུལ་དུ་བཏགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:31:54.656Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Accomplish it and make the offering of accomplishment, Then tie it around the neck of a victor.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="297">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">557</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:32:06.244Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བར་ཆད་ཟློག་པར་འགྱུར་བར་ངེས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:32:06.244Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>It is certain to reverse all obstacles.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="298">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">597</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:32:38.658Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཡུངས་ཀར་མར་དང་མུ་ཟི་རྣམས། །ཆ་སྙོམས་ལུས་ལ་རབ་བྱུགས་ན། །གདུག་པས་ཟིན་ལས་ཐར་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:32:38.658Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“If one smears the body, in equal measure, With mustard seed, clarified butter, and brimstone, One will be freed from the grasp of vicious beings.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="299">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">744</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:33:45.423Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བ་སུ་ན་དའི་མེ་ཏོག་དང་། །འདའ་ཧུ་ན་དའི་འབྲས་བུ་ལ། །སྨིན་དྲུག་དུས་སུ་རབ་བསྒྲུབས་ན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:33:45.423Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“If one practices during the month of Kārttika, On the bagunada flower, And the dahunada fruit,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="300">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">840</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:33:56.07Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གདུག་པ་ཕྱོགས་སུ་མི་གནས་སོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:33:56.07Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>All vicious ones will have nowhere to remain.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="301">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">886</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:34:21.553Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྟག་དང་དྲེད་དང་འཇའ་ཐར་གྱི། །སྤུས་ནི་གདུག་པ་ལས་གྲོལ་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:34:21.553Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“With the hairs of tiger, bear, and jackal, One will be free from vicious ones.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="302">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">966</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:34:47.435Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།འབབ་ཆུ་རྒྱ་མཚོ་ལ་སོགས་པ། །ལུས་བསྲུང་བྱ་བ་མཐར་ཕྱིན་པར། །བྱས་ན་མཆོག་ཏུ་བསྲུང་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:34:47.435Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“If, in a waterfall, a lake, and so forth, The acts of protecting the body are perfectly performed, It will be the supreme protection.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="303">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1101</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:35:05.14Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རྡོ་རྗེ་འཆང་བ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ཟུང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:35:05.14Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“You should accept the Vajra Holder!</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="304">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1138</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:35:52.616Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།མཐར་ཕྱིན་ཟླ་བ་སྤྲིན་གཟའ་ལས། །གྲོལ་བ་ལྟ་བུར་འགྱུར་བ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:35:52.616Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then, just as the full moon Is freed from the grasp of the clouds, So shall you be free.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="305">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1228</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:36:24.985Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དཔལ་རྡོ་རྗེ་ས་འོག་གི་རྒྱུད་ལས་བསྲུང་བའི་ལེའུ་སྟེ་བཅུ་པའོ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:36:24.985Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>This was the tenth chapter on protection from The Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="306">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1357</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:38:54.025Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།།ལག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེས་ལེགས་སྨྲས་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:38:54.025Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Vajrapāṇi then said these well-spoken words:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="307">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1402</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:40:00.911Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བཏུབ་སྔགས་ཀྱི་ཆོ་ག་ནི། །ཇི་ལྟར་ལེགས་སོ་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཆང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:40:00.911Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“The ritual of arranging mantras, How might that be?”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="308">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1456</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:40:19.557Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཁྱེད་ལ་རབ་ཏུ་ཉན་པར་འཚལ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:40:19.557Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Vajra Holder, please listen well.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="309">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1491</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:40:36.716Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཉོན་ཅིག་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཆང་བ་ཁྱོད། །སྔགས་བཏུ་ཁྱོད་ལ་བཤད་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:40:36.716Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Vajra Holder, listen well, And I will teach you the arrangement of mantras.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="310">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1567</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:40:57.039Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གྲུ་གསུམ་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ཉམས་དགའ་བར། །པདྨ་འདབ་མ་བརྒྱད་པ་བྲི།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:40:57.039Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“In a pleasing, triangular maṇḍala, Draw a lotus with eight petals.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="311">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1635</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:41:14.025Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།འདོད་དོན་ཐམས་ཅད་རབ་འགྲུབ་པ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:41:14.025Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>This accomplishes all desired aims.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="312">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1671</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:42:05.859Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེར་ནི་གསང་སྔགས་བཏུ་བར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:42:05.859Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Within that, arrange the secret mantras.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="313">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1713</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:43:33.658Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དབུས་སུ་ཡི་གེའི་བདག་པོ་གཞག</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:43:33.658Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>In the center, place the lord of syllables.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="314">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1757</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:43:50.269Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བཞི་པ་ཡི་ནི་ལྔ་པ་ལ། །ཡི་གེ་ཨི་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་སྦྱར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:43:50.269Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>In the fifth of the fourth, Place the syllable i.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="315">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1807</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:44:06.353Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།མཐར་གནས་པ་ཡི་གསུམ་པ་ལ། །ལྔ་པ་ཡི་ནི་མཐའ་དང་སྦྱར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:44:06.353Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“In the third of the final, Place the last of the fifth.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="316">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1864</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:45:05.538Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ལྔ་པའི་བཞི་པ་གཞག །དེ་ནས་མཐར་གནས་གཉིས་པ་གཞག །དེ་ནས་བཞི་པའི་བཞི་པ་གཞག །དེ་ནས་མཐར་གནས་གཉིས་པ་གཞག</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:45:05.538Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then place the fourth of the fifth. Next place the second in the last. “Then place the fourth of the fourth, And the second in the last.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="317">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2001</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:45:33.606Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ལྔ་པའི་གསུམ་པ་དང་། །གཉིས་པ་ཡི་ནི་གསུམ་པ་ལ། །ར་དང་བཅས་པ་གཞག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:45:33.606Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then in the third of the fifth, “And the third of the second, One should place a ra.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="318">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2086</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:45:59.663Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་ལྔ་པའི་དང་པོ་ལ། །ཨཱ་ཡིག་རབ་ཏུ་སྦྱར་བར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:45:59.663Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then, in the first of the fifth, The syllable ah should be placed.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="319">
            <prop name="folio">f.165.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2153</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:46:25.014Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དེ་ནས་གསུམ་པའི་ཐ་མ་ལ། །ཨི་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་སྦྱར་ཏེ་གཞག</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:46:25.014Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Then, in the last of the third, Place the syllable i.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="320">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">56</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:46:51.367Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བདུན་པ་ཡི་ནི་བཞི་པ་ལ། །ཡི་གེ་ཨཱུ་ནི་རབ་ཏུ་སྦྱར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:46:51.367Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>In the fourth of the seventh, Place the syllable ū.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="321">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">108</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:49:09.043Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྟོང་པས་མནན་པས་ཉིས་འགྱུར་དང་། །ལྔ་པ་ཡི་ནི་གཉིས་པ་ལ། །གསུམ་པ་ཡི་ནི་དང་པོ་སྦྱར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:49:09.043Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“By suppressing with emptiness, it becomes two. In the second of the fifth, Apply the first of the third.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="322">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">214</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:49:26.138Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཡི་གེ་བཅུ་གསུམ་རིག་པའི་སྔགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:49:26.138Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>The thirteen syllables are the incantation.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="323">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">258</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:49:49.341Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བརྩེ་བས་བརྩོན་པར་རབ་བཟླས་ན། །གང་འདོད་དངོས་གྲུབ་ངེས་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:49:49.341Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“If they are recited diligently with love, All desired spiritual accomplishments are certain.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="324">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">353</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:50:17.715Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཀྱེ་མ་ཧོ་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཅན་གྱིས་གསུངས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:50:17.715Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Amazing, thus spoke the vajra possessor.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="325">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">394</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:50:35.95Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྔགས་ཀྱི་རྒྱལ་པོ་བླ་མེད་ལམ། །ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེའི་དངོས་གྲུབ་ཐོབ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:50:35.95Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>This is the king of mantras, the unsurpassable path, That manifests the spiritual accomplishments of Vajrapāṇi.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="326">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">506</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:50:51.867Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དཔལ་རྡོ་རྗེས་འོག་གི་རྒྱུད་ལས་སྔགས་བཏུ་བའི་ལེའུ་སྟེ་བཅུ་གཅིག་པའོ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:50:51.867Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>This was the eleventh chapter on the arrangement of mantras from The Glorious Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="327">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">670</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:57:21.734Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།།དེ་ནས་སྟོན་པ་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཆང་། ། སྤྱན་མིག་འོད་ཟེར་སྤྲུལ་མཛད་ནས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:57:21.734Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>The teacher, Vajradhara, Emanated light from his eyes.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="328">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">725</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:57:36.827Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སློབ་མ་རབ་ཏུ་སྨིན་བྱའི་ཕྱིར། །དབང་བསྐུར་ཆོ་ག་རབ་ཏུ་བཤད།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:57:36.827Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then, in order to ripen students, He taught the ritual of conferring empowerment:</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="329">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">807</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:58:03.375Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རྡོ་རྗེ་སློབ་དཔོན་དཀའ་ཐུབ་ཆེ། །གསང་དང་ལྡན་པ་དབང་ཐོབ་ཅིང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:58:03.375Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“The vajra master, the great ascetic, Has obtained empowerment, replete with secrets.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="330">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">893</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:58:33.561Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>དུལ་དང་དྲང་དང་ཤེས་ཉེན་ཆེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:58:33.561Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>He is disciplined, upright, and a great spiritual friend.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="331">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">951</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:58:49.326Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གཡོ་ཆུང་ངང་བཟང་བྱང་སེམས་ཐོབ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:58:49.326Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>In the excellent state of little movement, he obtained the awakened mind.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="332">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1025</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:59:31.54Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་ཆོ་ག་རབ་མཁས་པ། །སློབ་མ་དམ་པ་དབང་བསྐུར་ཕྱིར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:59:31.54Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Learned in the maṇḍala ritual, He should bestow empowerment on the foremost student.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="333">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1110</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:59:59.71Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཡིད་འོང་གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་སོགས་སུ། །བརྟུལ་ཞུགས་སྔོན་དུ་ལེགས་སྤྱད་ནས། །དེ་ནས་ས་ཡི་ཆོ་ག་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T18:59:59.71Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“For that, in a place such as a beautiful temple, First train well in disciplined conduct, Then perform the ritual of the ground.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="334">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1240</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:00:54.127Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བརྟག་དང་སྦྱང་ཞིང་བསླང་བ་དང་། །མཆོད་དང་གསོལ་བ་གདབ་པ་དང་། །རྨི་ལམ་མཚན་མའི་སྒོ་ནས་བརྟག</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:00:54.127Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Examine, purify, and prepare, Then make offerings and requests. Examine by means of signs in dreams.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="335">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1341</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:01:14.225Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཞི་བའི་ཚོགས་སྤྱན་སྲེག་ནི། །བརྒྱ་རྩ་བརྒྱད་ཀྱི་ཆོ་ག་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:01:14.225Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“The fire offering should be performed A total of 108 times with the peaceful ritual.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="336">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1427</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:01:38.405Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།འབྱུང་པོ་རྣམས་ལ་མཆོད་ཅིང་བསྒོ། །དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་དབུས་སུ་རབ་གནས་ཏེ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:01:38.405Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Make offerings to the bhūtas and instruct them; They abide in the center of the maṇḍala.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="337">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1516</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:03:22.772Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཧཱུྃ་ལས་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོ་བསྒོམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:03:22.772Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“From hūṃ, visualize a great vajra.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="338">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1552</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:03:35.682Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བྲུྃ་ལས་གཞལ་ཡས་ཁང་ཆེན་བསྒོམ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:03:35.682Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>From bhrūṃ, visualize the great celestial palace.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="339">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1602</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:03:55.235Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྤྱན་གཉིས་ཉི་ཟླའི་འོད་ཟེར་གྱིས། །བགེགས་རྣམས་མ་ལུས་ཚར་གཅོད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:03:55.235Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>The light from the two eyes, the sun and the moon, Annihilates all obstructing forces without exception.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="340">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1707</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:04:17.958Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རྡོ་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོ་གར་འགྲོས་ཀྱིས། །ས་གཞི་ལན་གསུམ་བསྐོར་བར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:04:17.958Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“With the dance movement of the great vajra, Circumambulate the ground three times</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="341">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1790</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:04:42.22Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བ་ཡི་རྣམ་ལྔས་ལེགས་བྱུགས་ཏེ། །ཚོམ་བུ་གཅིག་གིས་ལྷ་དགོད་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:04:42.22Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>And smear it with the five substances of a cow, Then arrange the deities in a single group.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="342">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1882</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:05:09.364Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།མཆོད་དང་བསྟོད་དང་སྙན་གསན་དབབ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:05:09.364Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Make offerings, praises, and requests.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="343">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1922</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:05:51.884Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བུམ་པ་ལྷག་པར་གནས་པར་བྱ། །སློབ་མ་ཚོ་གསར་བ་སྨིན་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:05:51.884Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Place the vase especially well, Then ripen the student in the ritual.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="344">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">1992</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:06:34.678Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཐིག་དང་ཚོན་གྱི་ཆོ་ག་ནི། །ལས་ཀྱི་ཆོ་ག་བཞིན་དུ་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:06:34.678Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“The ritual of threads and colors Should be done just as the activity ritual.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="345">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">2070</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:06:56.026Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གདོང་གཡོགས་དར་ནི་སྔོན་པོ་ཡིས། །སློབ་མ་དག་ནི་གཞུག་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:06:56.026Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Then, with the blue blindfold, Let the students enter.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="346">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">2126</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:07:36.653Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྡོམ་ལྡན་དབང་བསྐུར་རྣམ་ལྔས་བསྐུར། །བུམ་པ་དང་པོ་རྡོ་རྗེ་དང་། །དྲིལ་བུ་དབུ་རྒྱན་མིང་གི་དབང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:07:36.653Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>On the vow holders, bestow the fivefold empowerment: The empowerments of the vase, the vajra, The bell, the crown, and the name.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="347">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">186</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:08:14.495Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ལས་ཀྱི་ཆོ་ག་ཇི་བཞིན་ནོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:08:14.495Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“The activity ritual is the same.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="348">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">220</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:08:48.53Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཚེས་བཅུ་བཞི་དང་བཅུ་གསུམ་ལ། །སློབ་མ་ལས་ལ་གཟུད་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:08:48.53Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>On the fourteenth and the thirteenth day, Introduce the students to the activity.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="349">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">302</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:09:18.421Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བྱིན་རླབས་རིམ་པས་འཕོ་བ་དང་། །འཕྲལ་དུ་ཡིད་ཆེས་བསྐྱེད་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:09:18.421Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>The blessings should be transferred gradually, While confidence should be produced immediately.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="350">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">398</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:09:45.721Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རིན་ཆེན་སྙིང་པོ་དྲི་མེད་རྒྱུད། །རྒྱུད་རྣམས་ཀུན་གྱི་རྩ་བར་ནི། །འདིར་དབང་བསྐུར་བ་དམ་པ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:09:45.721Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“This stainless tantra, the precious essence, Is the root of all tantras. It contains the sacred bestowal of empowerment.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="351">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">520</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:10:46.559Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།སྨིན་པའི་ལས་ལ་བརྟེན་པ་ཡི། །དབང་བསྐུར་མཆོག་གི་རྒྱུད་གསུངས་པས། །རབ་གནས་དགེ་བསྡོམ་པ་ལྡན། །དམ་པ་ཡོན་གྱིས་མཉེས་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:10:46.559Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Virtuous vow-holders who have been consecrated Through the empowerment based upon the activities of ripening, Which is taught in the supreme tantras, Should please the sacred one with gifts.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="352">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">712</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:11:27.027Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གྲོལ་བ་མཐར་ཕྱིན་རབ་ཏུ་གནས། །སློབ་མ་སྨིན་པའི་ཆོ་གའོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:11:27.027Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>This is the rite for perfecting liberation, for consecration, And for the maturing of students.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="353">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">809</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:11:51.808Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རྡོ་རྗེས་འོག་གི་རྒྱུད་ལས་སློབ་མ་ལ་དབང་བསྐུར་བའི་ལེའུ་སྟེ་བཅུ་གཉིས་པའོ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:11:51.808Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>This was the twelfth chapter on bestowing empowerment on the students from The Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="354">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">964</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:12:19.113Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།།དེ་ནས་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ལ་འདི་སྐད་ཅེས་གསོལ་ཏོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:12:19.113Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Then the bodhisattva Vajrapāṇi requested the Blessed One,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="355">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1022</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:14:15.24Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་སེམས་ཅན་རྣམས་ཀྱི་དོན་དུ་ཐུགས་ཀྱི་གསང་བ་བཤད་དུ་གསོལ་ཞེས་</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:14:15.24Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Lord, for the sake of all sentient beings, please explain the secret of enlightened mind.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="356">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1114</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:15:35.317Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>གསོལ་བ་བཏབ་བོ། །བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་བཀའ་སྩལ་པ། ལག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་མི་བཟད་ཁྱོད། །གཞན་དོན་བག་བརྩོན་ལེགས་སོ་ལེགས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:15:35.317Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>The Blessed One answered this request by saying: “Vajrapāṇi, terrifying one, It is excellent that you consider the welfare of others so diligently.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="357">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1262</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:16:01.855Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གང་ཞིག་དུས་ཀྱི་སྙིགས་མ་ལ། །གདུལ་དཀའི་སེམས་ཅན་འདུལ་འདོད་པས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:16:01.855Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>In the degenerated age, whoever wishes To tame those sentient beings that are difficult to tame,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="358">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1359</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:16:20.194Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དང་པོར་བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་བསྐྱེད་ལ། །ཚོགས་གཉིས་ཀུན་རྫོགས་མཐར་ཕྱིན་པས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:16:20.194Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Should first give rise to the mind of awakening, And completely perfect the two accumulations.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="359">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1455</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:17:08.316Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རིན་ཆེན་སྣོད་དུ་པདྨའི་གཏེར། །དབུས་སུ་གསང་བའི་བདག་པོ་ཅན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:17:08.316Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>On a lotus base within a jeweled vessel, Array the Lord of Secrets in the center,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="360">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1537</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:17:29.891Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།འདབ་མ་བརྒྱད་ལ་ཀླུ་ཆེན་བརྒྱད། །སྦྲུལ་མགོས་བརྒྱན་པ་དགོད་པར་བྱ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:17:29.891Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Surrounded by the eight great nāgas on eight petals, Each with the head of a snake.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="361">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1622</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:17:53.461Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཁྲུས་དང་གཙང་སྦྲ་དང་ལྡན་པས། །ལས་ཀྱི་ལྷ་ཡི་རྣལ་འབྱོར་གྱིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:17:53.461Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>When washed and pure, Perform the practice of the deity of activity.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="362">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1691</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:18:13.832Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དང་པོ་སྤྱན་དྲངས་རབ་མཆོད་ནས། །བདག་དང་ལྷ་གཉིས་འཕྲོ་འདུར་བཟླས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:18:13.832Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“First invite and make offerings, Then recite while projecting and absorbing oneself and the deity.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="363">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1791</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:18:30.845Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཀླུ་བརྒྱད་ཞི་བར་འགྱུར་སེམས་ཀྱིས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:18:30.845Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Think that the eight nāgas are pacified.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="364">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1832</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:19:26.466Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཧཱུྃ་དང་ཧཱུྃ་གི་ཐག་པ་ལས། །བསྒྲུབ་བྱ་འོད་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོར་བྱ། །སྐད་ཅིག་མས་ནི་ཧཱུྃ་དུ་བསླང་།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:19:26.466Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Thus, from hūṃ and the rope of hūṃ, The one to be accomplished is turned into a mass of light, And, in an instant, caught within the hūṃ.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="365">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">1970</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:19:57.195Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཨོཾ་བཛྲ་ཀྲོ་དྷ་ཨ་ཧཱི་ཙཎྜ་ཕཊ། ཁྲི་བཟླས་གདོན་ལས་ངེས་གྲོལ་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:19:57.195Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Oṃ vajrakrodha ahicaṇḍa phaṭ. “With ten thousand repetitions, one will certainly be freed from the grahas.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="366">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2078</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:20:17.413Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ལག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་ཁྱོད་ཀྱིས་ནི། །ཐུགས་ཀྱི་འཕྲོས་འདུ་གསང་བ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:20:17.413Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Vajrapāṇi, Your radiation and absorption of enlightened mind is secret.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="367">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2151</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:20:58.394Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།བསྒྲུབ་བྱའི་ལུས་ནི་ཚོན་གྱིས་དཀྲི། །ཧཱུྃ་ཆེན་ཕྲེང་བའི་འཕྲོ་འདུས་གཅད།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:20:58.394Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>Cover the body of the one to be accomplished in color, And cut it with the radiation and absorption of the garland of the great hūṃ.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="368">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2284</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:21:24.843Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རྫས་ཆེན་རྣམས་ལ་རབ་བརྟགས་ན། །ངེས་པར་གདོན་ལས་གྲོལ་བར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:21:24.843Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“When examining the great substances, One will surely be freed from grahas.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="369">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2360</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:22:17.876Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།གལ་ཏེ་དེས་ཀྱང་མ་གྲུབ་ན། །སྔགས་ཀྱི་ཕྲེང་བ་བཟློག་སྟེ་བཟླས།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:22:17.876Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>However, if this should not accomplish it, Reverse the mantra chain and do the recitation.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="370">
            <prop name="folio">f.166.b</prop>
            <prop name="position">2451</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:22:46.079Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།རྡོ་རྗེ་ཕྲེང་བས་རབ་བཅད་ནས། །ཐེ་ཚོམ་མེད་པར་འགྲུབ་པར་འགྱུར།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:22:46.079Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“Having cut with the vajra chain, It will be accomplished without any doubt.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="371">
            <prop name="folio">f.167.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">78</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:23:16.108Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།འོག་གི་བགེགས་བཟློག་ཆོ་ག་མཆོག །ཡིད་བཞིན་ནོར་ལྟར་འབྱུང་བ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:23:16.108Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>The supreme ritual for repelling the obstructors below Appears like a wish-fulfilling jewel.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="372">
            <prop name="folio">f.167.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">171</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:23:52.906Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།ཐེག་པ་གསུམ་ལས་ངེས་རྒྱལ་བའི། །རྒྱུད་ཆེན་གསང་བ་མཐར་ཐུག་པ། །སྐྱོབ་པའི་ཐུགས་ཀྱི་དམ་པ་ཡིན།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:23:52.906Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>“This great tantra is the ultimate secret, Which, without doubt, is victorious among the three vehicles And supreme among all protective intentions.”</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="373">
            <prop name="folio">f.167.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">321</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:24:37.987Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>། དེ་ནས་བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཀྱིས་དེ་སྐད་ཅེས་བཀའ་སྩལ་མ་ཐག་ཏུ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:24:37.987Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>As soon as the Blessed One had spoken,</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="374">
            <prop name="folio">f.167.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">360</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:25:38.703Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>ལག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་ལ་སོགས་པའི་རིགས་ཀྱི་འཁོར་རྣམས་དང་། ལྷའི་ཚོགས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡི་རངས་ཏེ། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་རྡོ་རྗེ་འཆང་གིས་གསུངས་པ་ལ་མངོན་པར་བསྟོད་དོ།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:25:38.703Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>the retinues of the family, including Vajrapāṇi, along with all the hosts of deities, rejoiced and praised what the Blessed Vajradhara had said.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="375">
            <prop name="folio">f.167.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">505</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:25:59.8Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།དཔལ་རྡོ་རྗེ་ས་འོག་གི་རྒྱུད་ལས་གསང་བ་གཏན་ལ་དབབ་པའི་ལེའུ་སྟེ་བཅུ་གསུམ་པའོ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:25:59.8Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>This was the thirteenth chapter on establishing the secret from The Glorious Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
        <tu tuid="376">
            <prop name="folio">f.167.a</prop>
            <prop name="position">621</prop>
            <tuv xml:lang="bo" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:26:16.587Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>།།ཁ་ཆེའི་པཎྜི་ཏ་ཙེ་ལུ་དང་། བོད་ཀྱི་ལོ་ཙྪ་བ་འཕགས་པ་ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱིས་བསྒྱུར་བ་རྫོགས་སོ།།</seg>
            </tuv>
            <tuv xml:lang="en" creationdate="2018-09-30T19:26:16.587Z" creationid="S.J.">
                <seg>The translation was completed by the Kashmiri scholar Celu and the Tibetan translator Phakpa Sherab.</seg>
            </tuv>
        </tu>
    </body>
</tmx>